<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3004">To Bishop Constantine of Seleucia</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">3-11</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.1">
            <pb n="3"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">To Constantine the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 2nd book the 12th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The contents of your sanctity's former epistle to me are as far from applying to my
               vileness as the heaven is far from the earth, to use the words of the prophet. For
               you thought fit to recite to me the passage of the Song of Songs, I mean, "Thou art
               all fair, my neighbour, and there is no spot [in thee." ...]. I [am turned] into
               another man, as it is written and prophesy, and that not one of all your words shall
               fall <pb n="4"/> to the ground. For he is faithful who said to you high priests, "Ye
               shall call my name upon the sons of Israel, and I the Lord will hallow them."!
               However, let these things be so. But know, father ours, that, after the holy Asterius
               the bishop and those with him came here, many various [...] will cast those that are
               deceived into a pit of destruction. But all, so to speak, have the one object only,
               to bring to naught the <foreign>typos</foreign> or formula of satisfaction which
               seemed good to the pious king, which he also sent to Flavian, the prelate of the city
               of Antiochus, and either altogether to remove and abolish it, or to cut away some of
               its exactitude, because they do not intend to drink the still water, as says Ezekiel,
               but strive to foul it with their own feet, in order that the sheep which have learned
               to hear the voice of the Good Shepherd, and to drink "the water of Shiloah that goeth
               softly," may not be able to avoid the pollution of the drink. Which John of
               Claudiupolis also tried to do when he came here. When he received me in the house of
               the glorious Patrick, the Master of the Soldiers, and conversed with me by order of
               our pious king, he said, "There ought to be introduced into the formula of
               satisfaction <pb n="5"/> this statement, 'We receive the synod at Chalcedon, not as a
               definition of faith, but as a rejection of Nestorius and of Eutyches.' Thus both
               those that are pleased with the Synod will not be angry, and you will receive
               contentment in that the doctrines which offend you are rejected." But I said, "This
               argument is silly, and the offspring of a drunken mind. Who is there among
               right-minded persons who will accept and praise us on account of this disturbance and
               confusion? If the Synod of Chalcedon introduced the doctrine of Nestorius into the
               churches, though it called Nestorius 'of small intelligence' in order to entice and
               deceive those that are more simple, how can we say that it rejected the opinion of
               Nestorius? But, if the formula of satisfaction in so many words rejects the doctrines
               of the Synod and of the impious Tome of Leo, which are the life blood of the
               abomination of Nestorius, how can we honestly say that we accept this synod as
               against Nestorius? [...] rather we shall be tripped up as by [...]" "What then? Were
               not those at Chalcedon rightly moved against Eutyches? why, [if] you accept them on
               this point, do you think them fit [...] an anathema?" [But] I said, "What I am about to
               say is strange, but nevertheless true. It is especially for this reason that we say
               that they are men that deserve anathema, because they unnecessarily extended the <pb
                  n="6"/> heresy of Eutyches. Owing to the fact that they wished to heal the
               disorder in an unintelligent way by means of an opposite infection, mean by the evil
               impiety of Nestorius, thenceforward those who were infected with the belief in a
               phantasy, seeing that they were inviting them to man-worship, recoiled from this
               vicious remedy, and thought themselves all the more pious, and carried their own
               corruption further. But, if they had been cured and healed by means of right
               doctrines, they would perhaps have abandoned their infection. [If] we accept those
               [who] met together [at] Chalcedon as being adversaries [of] the heresy of Eutyches,
               and praise them on the ground that they spoke well up to a certain point, and do not
               rather blame them, it is time for us to accept also the Arian heresy, which contends
               against the evil opinion of Sabellius, and agrees up to a certain point with the
               right doctrines of the Church, in that it glorifies God the unbegotten Father, and in
               that it does not confound the three substances, but confines them within their own
               attributes or persons. But we do not extol it on this account, nor do we judge it to
               deserve a partial anathema. But, because it calls the Son and the Holy Spirit
               creatures, and degrades them to a servile position, on this account it is utterly
               repudiated by the orthodox doctors of the Church. This same trick we find practised
               by the other heresies also. By displaying a certain part of the sound faith as a
               decoy and mixing with this the vanity of their <pb n="7"/> own profane words they
               thus appear plausible to those that are more innocent and simple; but we do not, on
               account of the sound part, hold back and shrink from repudiating them, but we
               anathematize them with all our power." When the good and excellent John had heard
               these things, he betook himself to another topic. He asked me whether Epiphanius the
               bishop," who is among the saints, performed our ordinations fitly and in accordance
               with the canon. But I said, "Very well and most properly," and "after the pattern of
               the doctors and stablishers of the word of the orthodox faith. For he in his boyhood
               was brought up in monasteries, and practised a virginity modelled on the angelic and
               unembodied life, being a citizen of Perga: a man of no ignoble city, as it is
               written, yes, and a man of noble birth also, if these things are not small to the
               citizens of Jerusalem above. Having been advanced to the bishopric of Magydum (this
               also is a city in Pamphylia) at the time of the Encyclical which repudiated the
               impiety that was confirmed at Chalcedon, under which Timothy, who was sent into exile
               for piety's sake, returned to Alexander's city, and received back the presidency of
               the flock of Mark the Evangelist, which before was unrighteously tended by wolves and
               torn, when he saw that the bishops had changed, and that they had overthrown the
               Encyclical by a contrary <pb n="8"/> document, and had gone back to the Synod of
               Chalcedon and its hateful doctrines, he left his throne and Pamphylia, the land of
               his fathers, and the blessed man came as a fugitive to Alexander's city, and embraced
               communion with the saintly Timothy, the champion of the right faith, having taken
               joyfully upon him the spoiling of his goods, and knowing that he had in heaven a
               better and enduring inheritance, as the wise Paul says. But, when Timothy of holy
               memory had finished his course and kept his faith? and departed to God, the zealots
               of the orthodox faith were again persecuted in Alexander's city, and the correct word
               was perturbed by certain men's mixture. Then therefore the blessed Epiphanius
               withdrew to Palestine, the stranger on the earth, who did not know any city of his
               own, or rather knew that only as his own in which God over all is purely worshipped.
               And, having associated with Peter of Iberia of holy memory, the God-clad man, who was
               bishop of one of the cities in Palestine, and with the other holy fathers and
               orthodox peoples, he was persuaded by them and ordained priests, not going beyond the
               meaning of the sacred canons (far be it!) The canon that forbids a bishop to perform
               an ordination in provinces or parishes which do not belong to him comes into play in
               cases where he forces himself upon other men's countries in a disorderly fashion and
               without an invita<pb n="9"/>tion from anyone, not when he is persuaded to ordain by
               the bishop of the country or city and by the orthodox clergymen, especially in time
               of persecution. We may find such instances also if we study church histories. In the
               times of the Arians, when the servants of piety were persecuted and suffered every
               kind of evil, Eusebius the bishop of Samosata (this is one of the cities of
               Mesopotamia) went about the cities and deserts and villages, and travelled to
               countries outside the boundaries, wearing a soldier's dress and having his head
               covered by a hood, and applied his sacred hand and confirmed priests for places that
               were in need; who also put on a crown of martyrdom, having his head crushed by a
               stone by the heterodox, and migrated in saintly fashion to Jesus who longed for him,
               and was admitted to the heavenly mansions. These things are clearly stated by
               Theodoret in his church history. The great light of the Cappadocians also, or rather
               of the whole world, Basil the bishop, the pillar of the church, the 'sure foundation'
               (for these words of the apostle fit him more than any man, as fine raiment a bride),
               was raised to the throne of the bishopric, receiving ordination to the episcopacy, by
               bishops outside the boundaries. This Gregory the Theologian says in the funeral
               discourse on Basil himself, writing thus: 'He is raised to the high throne of the
               bishopric, not without toil nor without envy and contention on <pb n="10"/> the part
               of the prelates of the country, and of the worst men of the city who ranged
               themselves with these; however, the Holy Spirit was bound to conquer: yes, and it
               does conquer, gaining an easy victory. For from outside the boundaries it stirs up
               men to anoint, men distinguished and zealous in the matter of piety.' But, if Basil,
               the teacher of orthodoxy and rule and law of all church discipline, was anointed and
               received ordination (for this is the anointing of a high-priest) from those outside
               the boundaries, because the people of the country or province were jealous of him, on
               account of the Arian heresy or for other human reasons, which is a very small thing,
               how can we say that the ordinations that were performed among us by a man outside the
               boundaries, when the transgression of Chalcedon and the Nestorian heresy bare rule
               and prevailed, are not to be approved? and we have such great and wonderful instances
               of holy men and such as these, whose zeal is resembled by ours. But what shall we for
               our part say of the ordinations that are now performed in the churches? What canon
               respecting these is not trampled upon? Are not high-priesthoods now everywhere for
               sale, as we see in the case of civil governorship of cities (the other things I pass
               over, lest by falling into evil speaking or backbiting and saying things suited to
               other men I be thought to be choosing for myself matters that do not concern me)?"
               While I was saying these things, the <pb n="11"/> gentle John covered his face. But
               since perhaps, even after he has returned to you, he will again circulate the same
               suggestions (for this. is the habit of those who cause confusion), I have thought it
               right to make known to your sanctity the details of our honest and lawful discussion
               of this matter in this royal city. As to the state of our affairs, I think the
               religious presbyter Peter has once already given you information by letter upon each
               several point. Still it is a matter for your saintly prayers that the Lord, as is
               said in the Psalms, after we have "passed through fire and water" may 'bring us out
               into a place of refreshment." But you as watchful shepherds and strict disciples of
               the chief shepherd Jesus, who brought us up with Him from among the dead by the blood
               of the everlasting covenant, "stand fast in the faith, quit you like men, and be
               strong. Let all your things be done with" orthodoxy or the right opinions. For you
               have "chosen the good part, which shall not be taken away from" you. And we believe
               that the whole lump also will coalesce with your holy first fruit and be kneaded: for
               through your prayers we have in all our troubles gained experience of the help of
               God, and the comfort of hopes of success has not departed from us. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
            <note resp="#compiler">Letters like this, of the same tenour, were written to the
               patricians also, and to Oecumenius.</note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
