<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To the Archimandrite of the Monastery of
               Bassus</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">47-52</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.11">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the archimandrite of the monastery of
               Bassus.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               345th letter.</head>
            <p> The letter of your love of God which has just been brought to me I have taken into
               my hands, and received as yours. For I rejoice and exult when I read your name even
               on the mere outside address, and I am brought to a more lively memory of your holy
               monastery, and draw away my thoughts from the worry of affairs, and in this way am
               refreshed and comforted. But, when the things written met my eye, I was astonished,
               and wondered how it could have come into your mind to make a profitless and
               impossible request. The devout Cosmas, who has just died, I instituted bishop of the
               city of the Apamenes, because I trusted to the report of others concerning him and
               their partiality on his behalf. For I confess to your holiness <pb n="48"/> that I
               never had any confidence in him. Accordingly during all the time previous to my
               coming to this city of Antiochus it can in no case be shown that I addressed a letter
               to him; but it was the religious presbyter Theodore who used to write to him. But for
               what reason I would not consent to write to him it is not proper to the present time
               to say. However, as I said, J instituted him bishop, thus adding yet another to my
               sins. For what blasphemous utterances he vomited forth, and what darts he hurled
               against heaven God who heard knows. In plain language, not to make a long story,
               after many roundabout methods and entreaties on my part, and tears unsuited to the
               Holy Spirit, after alleging one reason and another, and at last bringing in his
               bodily infirmity also, he resigned the bishopric. Thenceforward the whole position
               was an insoluble difficulty to us, and full of doubt. For it was not only on account
               of the mistake made in his case and the words blasphemously put forward by him that
               there was cause for weeping, but also owing to the question in what way the affairs
               of the Apamenes would have to be administered: for in such a state of confusion all
               counsel was helpless. The God-loving bishops who in accordance with the statutes of
               the church were residing at that time in the city of the Antiochenes, being present,
               exhorted me to receive him as wishing to resign. And, since it was impossible for one
               church to be united to two men at the same time, he drew up petitions of resignation,
               saying of himself that he was no bishop and no clergy<pb n="49"/>man, nor did he hold
               any other degree in the ministry. And, after this had taken place, the God-loving
               bishop Peter was thereupon instituted. How then is it possible to undo, as you ask, a
               thing that was carried out with so much caution and without anger? Assuredly, if the
               transaction which renders Cosmas not a bishop is not maintained, it results that the
               God-loving Peter was uncanonically instituted, and was given to a church that had
               already received a bishop. Accordingly it is plain that the resignation of the
               often-mentioned Cosmas tends to establish the ordination of the God-loving bishop
               Peter. But I for my part am wondering who advised your sanctity to ask this. Does
               anyone intend to clothe the dead man in that of which in accordance with the
               ordinances of the Holy Spirit that cannot be rejected he voluntarily stripped
               himself? or does anyone wish to mention him as a bishop? What therefore the wisdom of
               such a request is am unable to understand. And what a time was it for a man’s
               resignation to be recalled after his decease! Again, as to the fact that I went out
               to the devout Cosmas after he had fallen ill, I wish the sequence of events not to be
               unknown to your sanctity. Some of the zealous brethren came up to me and begged me to
               go to him, on the ground that he himself was asking for this. But I said, "This
               cannot be. With a man who is not in communion with the holy church, I do not consider
               that I myself have any communion." And, though those who made the entreaty
               persevered, I would not consent: and I was so firm that for three whole days they
               urged <pb n="50"/> the point, and J did not yield. But at last one of those who were
               with us, the religious deacon father Elijah, began to say that perhaps he wished to
               repent, and to receive the oblation from my sinful hands. When this was said, I
               considered that I should bring myself under the judgment of God, if I did not on this
               consideration consent to the request itself: and in this hope I went to visit the
               afore-mentioned man. However, knowing as I did his unyielding character, said to
               those who were with me: "Believe me when I say that I am going out against my will
               and without any confidence." And, when I had gone, I made a prayer in the expectation
               that he would repent: but to give him a greeting or to ask a greeting from him I
               would not consent, far be it! For with what reason could I have given a greeting of
               peace to a man who refused the mystical peace before the holy altars and communion
               with us? Woe is me if I give a bodily greeting to any man when my soul does not agree
               to the greeting. When therefore we had sat down and none of the things that were
               expected was said by him, but, though he could not articulate, he kept urging and
               inviting us to enter upon a long conversation, while I for my part considered it a
               sin for us to enter upon a contentious and profitless conversation while the man was
               on the point of giving up the ghost, I rose, and prayed to God in private to forgive
               me the inconsiderate visit. To a man who was so disposed I <pb n="51"/> ought not to
               have gone out at all. Even when he was dead and many thought I should go there, I did
               not go; considering that "everything that is not of faith is sin," according to the
               words of the Apostle. For I for my part consider a man who separated himself without
               reason from our orthodox communion an enemy not a brother, even if he is deceived by
               the devil, who "is transformed into an angel of light," by considerations that are
               rather upon the right side. For hear the Lord say, "He that is not with me is against
               me: and he that gathereth not with me scattereth." Indeed by the prayers of the
               saints and of your holiness, when church histories and the labours of the holy
               fathers from the coming of the great God and our Saviour Jesus Christ down to this
               time come before me, I find that this present condition of the holy churches in the
               East and in Egypt is purer than the condition in former times, when the facts are
               examined side by side. They therefore that trouble the simple "shall themselves bear
               the judgment whosoever" they are, and shall themselves "give account in the day of
               judgment, when "he shall come who knoweth the hidden things of darkness and revealeth
               the counsels of the hearts." As for me, may have no part with such men, either in
               this world or in that which is to come! For, shunning as I do harshness of speech, do
               not wish to declare in detail what is the judgment <pb n="52"/> of those who turn
               aside. Wherefore also I am urgent in entreating every one of those who have been
               involved in the error not to continue in the plausible strangulation of this
               righteousness, and hold aloof from the life-giving communion of the holy mysteries.
               And so forth. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
