<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3038">To Entrechius, Bishop of Anazarba</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">53-56</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.13">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Entrechius, bishop of Anazarba.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               397th, 398th letter.</head>
            <p> I do not know whether should lay the blame of the events that are happening upon my
               sins, or upon the operation of an evil demon. Though there is nothing else that I
               have had so much at heart or for 'which I have prayed so much as that every Christian
               should conduct himself blamelessly, but especially those who are high-priests, giving
               no cause for reproach or blame against themselves, but being "in everything a pattern
               of good works, in gravity and in holiness," as the Apostle says, "in order that he
               that is of the contrary part may be ashamed, having no evil thing to say of us, I see
               that not once only but twice also am worried about the same matters. Indeed, though
               some of the devout clergymen of the holy church of Flavias had presented to us
               certain accusations upon <pb n="54"/> certain subjects against their God-loving
               bishop, and we managed the affair ourselves, and brought things that else would have
               been troublesome to a peaceful typos or conclusion and so settled them, now again old
               men bowed down with age have risen up to make more serious charges, men who, if one
               may so say, struggle against life itself, and live tn utter poverty and need: if one
               were to call them a pitiable sight, the expression would not be amiss. The statements
               made by them are many and various. Still for my part, again following the same
               practice, I wished to stop their accusation if it were possible: but, as they went on
               saying the same things, I proposed to commit the hearing of the case to your
               holiness. But, since they objected, and said that their life would be no life for
               them, if the religious Procopius their bishop did not come here, I have adopted a
               middle course (I do not think that others either will think the coming to us an easy
               thing) and resolved to send the religious Theodosius a presbyter of our apostolic see
               that he may examine the facts in conjunction with your love of God, and a decision
               consonant to the canons may be given by you, and: a conclusion reached upon each of
               the subjects with the greatest possible accuracy. But at the same time we have
               resolved to say this much, that the said religious bishop Procopius should not, after
               the first warning, have received a gift at ordinations on the pretext of making a
               profit for the church, as he <pb n="55"/> used to say, and again been detected in the
               same practices, as those who make the accusation against him say: nor should he have
               named Lampetius at the divine sacrifice, a man who was infected with the heresy of
               Adelphius, and for this reason was condemned at Commanus in Armenia, as the minutes
               of the records of that synod also show. Indeed, to pass over old matters, it is easy
               for your love of God to learn what canonical discussion the abominable flock of the
               Adelphians received in Second Cappadocia, seeing that the saintly Soteric bishop of
               the city of the men of Czsarea and the holy bishops who sat with him, from Cappadocia
               and from Pontus and from Galatia, then put forth a decision worthy of the priesthood
               against it. Of this same heresy the outward token is greed and immodesty and a mad
               desire of vain glory, owing to which they pride themselves in attracting admiration
               and receiving in secret the evil spirit: and, what is most important, the fact that,
               infected as they are with extreme godlessness, and wearing as they do a deceitful
               mask of hypocrisy in all things, they put forward this deception also, that their
               heresy is not a heresy: for they count up all the heretics in order and anathematize
               them, but Adelphius they honour by silence. The celebrated freedom from passions of
               which they boast they do not display at all: and concerning matters on which charges
               are made against them they give no satisfaction, but from <pb n="56"/> matters on
               which they are not accused they gather the reputation of not being godless. It lies
               therefore with your love of God in conjunction with the religious Theodosius the
               presbyter of our apostolic see to see that the whole matter is as I have said
               carefully examined, and to make known the result of the examination to us also, in
               order that on all sides the appearance of the church may be preserved blameless. And
               another thing seems to me to be urgently demanded by piety, I mean that these unhappy
               men be not vexed by a long and useless session, who from necessity, as I believe,
               have made the accusation; and that they should not support themselves at their own
               expense, but that they should receive double the necessary daily sustenance from the
               holy church of which they are members. Another matter too you must set right without
               dispute before the trial itself, a thing which appeared to me absolutely incredible
               and still even now appears so: I mean that the said men themselves should be enrolled
               in the sacred number of the clergy, their names having been expunged, as they say,
               for this reason and no other, because they were able to have recourse to the
               apostolic throne on account of the things which they suffered and the wounds that
               have been inflicted on them. That this, if it is true, surpassing as it does all
               presumptuous audacity, needs canonical punishment, I leave to your love of God to
               reflect. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
