<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3040">To Antoninus, Bishop of Berrhoea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">57-59</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.14">
            <pb n="57"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Antoninus, bishop of Berrhoea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the 65th
               letter.</head>
            <p> We were glad to see even the illustrious tribune Antiochus inasmuch as he came from
               you, and we encouraged him to converse constantly with us, and to ask for everything
               that is in our power, and is for the spiritual assistance of your love of God. And we
               praised him to the God-loving bishop Thomas, and, although we are sinful and vile, we
               repaid him by prayers. We have come to believe that the man who made the happy
               mistake in the address of the letters did not fall into the error without some divine
               providence. For this showed clearly that the two of us are wrapped up in one another,
               being joined together by the love that is in Christ, and that we have all things
               common according to the commandment, and have nothing of our own. Know however that
               the letter which properly belonged to you but was addressed to us we have not yet
               received. As to the ordination at Chalcis (I call the truth to bear witness to my
               words) no letter has come to us, or any information or indication. But, if you have
               in a philosophic manner been brought to a state of exasperation on account of the
               things that have happened among you, there is no cause for wonder: since this also is
               proper to the orderliness of your habits and to your discretion, which allots all <pb
                  n="58"/> things to the times suited for them. But, since we know that your
               holiness delights in words of admonition, and that you are eager to amass all things
               that conduce to the salvation of the soul and the acquisition of divine wisdom (for
               it is written, "The ear that heareth the reproof of life shall dwell among the wise,"
               and, "He that keepeth reproof loveth his soul"), we say with boldness the things
               that seem to us to be right. You also were not ignorant that those who managed Simeon
               whose soul is at rest (for he did not rule himself but was ruled by others) performed
               no sacred or ecclesiastical action except for money or under the influence of
               passion. For, if one may so speak, they were not known for virtue to any one of all
               the men who live in the East. To men such as these therefore you should never have
               lent your undefiled and sacred right hand, when they were making a division and
               presenting men for the sacred order of priests, especially when the ordination,
               performed as it was just before death, contained in itself a great fraud. For how was
               it possible that a man who in time of health never did anything sound in such matters
               should in time of disease be in any but a diseased condition for examining the
               question of propriety? For that he was awake when he gave you permission neither do I
               dispute: I consider your testimony more trustworthy than all oaths and every ground
               of confidence. Still, since you thirst to hear things that <pb n="59"/> profit, there
               is a further point which I will not omit, that it would have been a thing in accord
               and very consonant with the devoutness of the rest of your life to tremble and
               hesitate to undertake ordinations that belong to others, and by actual deeds to show
               that it is with order and in all fear and only from actual necessity that you
               minister and serve even in those that belong to yourself. As to the question whether
               the ordination performed on the said persons ought to hold good or not, we believe
               that, after we have learned the whole character of the action and of the persons, we
               shall give a decision that agrees with the judgments of God, and shall urge that this
               hold good: not because we do not think the fruit of your blameless hand perfect (this
               is beyond doubt), but because we are examining the question whether those who
               received the grace are worthy or not. In any case we think your love of God will be
               contented, Since you do not even desire to be contented with things other than those
               with which God is contented. If our wretched discourses be copied out, we will send
               them to you. For we have ordered them to be copied out, though we have not in plain
               fact even a man to copy. Before this present letter was closed, the God-loving
               Isidore bishop of the men of Chalcis arrived in our city: and this has been added to
               the things written, because we honour the truth before all things. And now it will be
               our endeavour to learn from him also what his disposition is with regard to the same
               aforesaid ordination. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
