<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Antoninus, Bishop of Berrhoea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">61-63</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.16">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the same Antoninus, bishop of
               Berrhoea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               101st letter.</head>
            <p> As for the accusation in the matter of the silence after the feast of salvation,
               which you attack as if it had been a violation of justice, I shall be acquitted by
               the experience of fact. For indeed before the charge itself was made at all I had
               already sent a letter to your sanctity by John the eloquent scholastic. Nevertheless
               you must know that the greeting which is given at the festival of the saving
               Resurrection should always begin by a letter from you, as is the established rule
               with regard to the other God-loving bishops also. How is it then that, when you had
               not yet cast the <pb n="62"/> seed, you were thinking about the things that spring
               from that? With a clever jest at our poverty or our need you said that the devout
               Mark came to us in order to give presents, not in order to receive anything, and
               therefore we thanked your sacred soul in this matter also, and readily showed towards
               him too all the duties of love without expense, making the intercourse with him to
               consist of a cheerful face, a serene aspect, and gentle speech, and repaying the
               presents brought by him with torches and spices. Also on the subject'? of the estates
               that are near the hamlet called Beth Remsha but of right belong to your holy church,
               we are exerting all our ability, and will cause measures to be taken that will accord
               with justice and also satisfy you. As to the Jews, as soon as I received your letter
               and found a convenient time, I thought good to prescribe a course to you in a few
               words. You must apply the distinction made by the apostolic laws of the wise Paul,
               who in speaking of matters relating to us cries, "Avenge not yourselves, my beloved,
               but give place unto wrath," and "'Mine is vengeance and will repay,' saith the Lord,"
               but in speaking of presumptuous deeds against God says, "If a man despise Moses' law,
               he dieth without mercy at the mouth of two or three witnesses; of how much sorer
               punishment think ye that he will be worthy. who hath trampled on the Son of God, and
               hath counted the blood of the covenant whereby he was sanctified a <pb n="63"/>
               common thing, and hath done despite unto the Spirit of grace?" All who took part in
               the sin should, in my opinion, be subjected to a penalty, in order that even in
               future time the action taken may be a lawful example to those who dare to do the same
               things. Knowing therefore that this is our mind on this matter, carry out what ought
               to be done with the help of God, even though hereafter we appear to write something
               that goes farther in the way of concession or is more ambiguous, avoiding however the
               appearance of contradicting ourselves. This I say on account of certain men who show,
               as they think, philosophy and clemency in the case of presumptuous deeds done against
               Christ. But I bring my words back like some ship to the prelude or beginning of the
               letter, and again pray on behalf of your love of God with a disposition that is at
               the same time fervent and humble, one that exacts from us the debts of love and stirs
               our coldness to spiritual affection. For who is there, even though he be a man of no
               feeling, who would not be put to shame by such modest words as are written by you? </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
