<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Misael the Chamberlain</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">63-66</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.17">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Misael the chamberlain.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               103rd Letter.</head>
            <p> For my part, when I was raised to this bishopric, unworthily indeed, but still by
               the judgment or per<pb n="64"/>mission of God, I intended to manage my affairs in a
               spiritual manner, and I had regard to the commandments of the gospel and the
               apostolic statutes and commands. And in the matter of ordinations I thought of
               nothing but the awful text, the cause of great fear, that says, "Lay a hand suddenly
               on no man; neither be partaker of other men's sins; keep thyself in purity:" and as
               to interest or the avaricious system of loans it was my desire not to know even the
               very name of them. For I listened to the singing prophet, who at one time says, "He
               giveth not his money upon interest," and at another time again cries, "Interest and
               guile have not departed from her streets," things which, if one may so say, are known
               even to those who are not versed in the sacred writings. But, when I had had
               experience of the distressful state of affairs, and had seen in what a pitiable and
               wretched condition the fortunes of our holy church were, and that a great load of
               debts and of interest was hanging over it and threatening to overwhelm it, I forgot
               the spiritual laws: and it now seems to me a great thing to find men to lend; and
               meanwhile I make use of the term 'interest' as if it were some lawful name. But, as
               to ordinations, I no longer stand in awe of the strictness of the divine laws, nor
               will I in future allege this in excuse to those who beg or seek to ask for these:
               but, when I see the poverty on all sides, and that every year we are obliged to have
               some kind of <pb n="65"/> collection in order to distribute among the devout
               clergymen whom we have the money for their support, I am afraid of the
               <foreign>oeconomi</foreign> or stewards on account of the scantiness of our
               resources, and I publish the need up and down: though I should have alleged the
               strictness of the spiritual commandments. For those who worry me about this are very
               many: and each of them looks at his own request only, and does not know how many
               there are who desire to obtain the same things. And, as soon as one of them has been
               disappointed of his request or desire, he immediately becomes an enemy: there is no
               middle position. And hence springs implacable war: so that I should now, if it were
               possible, revolt even against this vain life itself. For all these men do not allow
               us to choose the good, and to carry out with circumspection the things that we wish,
               and content those who like you often give such commands in a pious spirit. Hence I
               have been compelled to cause annoyance to the glorious sacellar Eleutherius also, who
               has often thought fit to write to me about a certain person, sometimes personally,
               sometimes through those who manage my <foreign>apokriseis</foreign>. For I see that
               these presumptuous dogs seek a thing of this kind as if it were some quarry: so that,
               if they found a means of beginning, they would bark at me: while they do not consider
               the need that encompasses us, nor do they wait for the help of God, who Himself alone
               is able to heal our church that is groaning under many wounds, and to change need
               into abundance. For it is He who says by the prophet, "Behold! it is <pb n="66"/> I
               who bring it healing and cure and I will cure it." Seeing that you know these things,
               you who are able to share our distress and are in character a lover of God, I beg you
               to offer a defence on our behalf based upon the facts themselves to those who are
               concerning themselves about anything of this kind. Especially satisfy the aforesaid
               glorious sacellar the lord Eleutherius, and inform his excellency that what is being
               done is not due to haughtiness, but to necessity, and to distress. Out of shame I
               have never dared to communicate with him by letter on this subject: but through your
               mediation I have now made my defence to him. Nevertheless I will to the best of my
               power use any convenient opportunity, and will perform as far as possible what he has
               commanded: </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
