<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3046">To Solon, Bishop of Seleucia in
               Isauria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">67-70</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.19">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Solon, bishop of Seleucia in
               Isauria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               149th letter.</head>
            <p> The constant evil things that are being done in close succession and in various ways
               in Isauria counsel us to silence. But still, when we turn over in our mind the
               judgments of God, we are again distressed, and cannot keep within us the cause of the
               distress, and we are brought round to the necessity of speaking. We have been in the
               same state as Jeremiah, who said, "I said, 'I will not name the name of the Lord nor
               speak in his name'"; and afterwards he was confounded and broke through the restraint
               that was <pb n="68"/> upon his mind, and he changed his mind and said, "And it became
               in my heart as fire burning and blazing and flaming in my bones, and I am dissolved
               on all sides and cannot endure." What indeed am I to do? Last year I compelled the
               God-loving bishop Paul of Olba to return to the flock which it has fallen to his lot
               to feed; and now again I see him being disturbed in the same way by certain men who
               are not rightly disposed, and in old age and bodily weakness visiting now one country
               now another and wandering about: and, although the man acquiesces in our counsel, he:
               carries out none of the things that we determined to be right. Now the things that we
               so determined are these, points which upon their coming a short time ago the party of
               the God-loving bishop Epiphanius and Symbatius also promised in common to observe
               with all their might and to their best endeavour, I mean that each should remove from
               the sacred tablets the names of those who signed the impious deeds of Chalcedon, but,
               as to the others, should remain silent and wait for a fitting season for progress to
               excellence. For there is no objection to ascent, as Gregory the Theologian also
               somewhere says." But, as the old man, I mean the God-loving bishop Paul whom I
               mentioned before, is of a more than ordinarily simple disposition, I do not know how
               it is that you have been frightening him like a child with the signatures of
               documents, and <pb n="69"/> have thus thrown him again into perturbation, when you
               should have treated each man according to his own condition and character, seeing
               that satisfactory professions have been made in common, and there is no doubt about
               them. So long therefore as the man remains of the same mind, receive him readily and
               honour him, on account of his venerable old age. Again as to the dispute that he had
               with the God-loving bishop Hilarian about a monastery, when we heard of it, we should
               perhaps have given a proper solution and decision, had it not been that he flew to
               the royal city, as we have heard, separating himself from communion with you, on
               account of the presumptuous and illegal deed of Callistus. For he charges him with
               interpolating or forging or garbling the letter that was sent by him?' (I do not know
               what expression to use on account of the many methods of committing the crime). For,
               on comparing the signature of the letter that was produced with the other signatures
               of the aforesaid God-loving bishop Hilarian that are preserved here in synodal
               documents, we found them to be as far removed and as different from one another as
               sheep differ in appearance from elephants. And, to say nothing of the strictness of
               the canons, it is manifest to everyone that the laws of the Romans also, which
               contain excellent enactments upon these matters, fix beheading as the punishment: and
               this is an offence against public law. We wish therefore that <pb n="70"/> the man
               who has acted so impiously in this affair should for the present abstain from all
               sacred ministration: and, as soon as he comes back, we will submit the matter to
               examination; since even in things that are thought to be acknowledged we like
               examination: and then we will pronounce for the facts of which the truth is
               established, placing before everything the just judgments of the balance-scales of
               God, and trembling lest by sparing others we make ourselves liable to these. For we
               are not ignorant what punishments Eli the priest received because, when his sons
               outraged the divine sacrifice, he only reproved them as a father and did not as an
               instructor and a ruler punish them according to the law. We have heard that the
               clergymen in the same monastery, while under inhibition from the God-loving bishop
               Paul, made light of his inhibition, and took part in the ministration with the
               God-loving bishop Hilarian. Therefore we have determined it to be right that they
               also hold aloof for the present from the sacred ministration, until he comes and a
               thorough investigation of the matter is held. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
