<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3012">To Solon, Bishop of Seleucia in Isauria</title>
            
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
               Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L.
                  Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX,
                  USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/>
            <!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m"> The Sixth Book of the Select Letters
                     of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of
                        Antioch</persName> in the Syriac Version of <persName
                        ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">12-16</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"
            /><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.2">
            <pb n="12"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Solon, bishop and metropolitan.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               105th, 106th letter.</head>
            <p> If anyone who knows how to discern spiritually the dispensations of the Lord, who
               does all things with wisdom, will recall to mind your struggles on behalf of the
               orthodox faith— <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> Henceforth clothe
               yourself in the immaterial dress of the priesthood, and stand firm. Instead of the
               ephod take upon your shoulders the Lord's cross; and instead of the tunic woven of
               fine linen and blue stuff put on the many-coloured tunic of virtues; and strengthen
               yourself by the struggles of the martyrs which extended to blood. But assuredly the
               honourable in virginity and first of female martyrs, and skilled maker of these
               things, I mean the holy Thecla, will clothe you in such raiment to do honour to her
               vote concerning you. But the crown of the orthodox faith, and purity and good
               character, and sincerity and vehemence of preaching, by which others also will be
               stirred up to the same zeal, will be to you the mitre and the crown of gold and the
               fair-sounding bells. And you are girt with a girdle and a breastpiece, a solitary and
               unwedded walk in life. Wherefore also Christ shall lie upon your breast, the Word of
               God, who took flesh for us, who was typified beforehand by the robe and knowledge and
               truth." When therefore things are thus <pb n="13"/> with you, who will dare to find
               fault with the innovation in the matter of your institution, when so many bishops
               with one accord canonically performed the ordination? That a patriarch or a
               metropolitan or the synod of the province should according to custom ordain such and
               such a man is not a matter of the strictness of the canons, but rather of church
               discipline. But this discipline we see to have been often neglected in times of
               persecution. Take the holy Basil. Because the bishops of the province were adversely
               disposed towards him, partly from envy, partly because they were attached to the
               madness of Arius, Gregory the Theologian says that he was ordained by bishops outside
               the boundaries, writing thus in the funeral discourse on him: [Here follows the
               citation given above, p. 9]. However, Flavian may be caught by his own wings. If he
               himself, and that when accused of heresy, formerly ordained someone in
               Germanicupolis, and snatched away an ordination that belonged to the metropolitan,
               let him not be annoyed when he has been treated in the same way, when on our side we
               have an advocate in defence of a similar act in the orthodox faith; and what can a
               man think could be a better advocate than this? This has the approval of the holy
               Gregory the Theologian also when he writes in this manner in the first of the
               conciliatory discourses, I mean that on the union of the monks, when certain men,
               perhaps like these, were thought to have intro<pb n="14"/>duced an innovation
               contrary to the law of the Church: 'For for our part we received the heads also who
               were given to the severed part with joy, inasmuch as they introduced an innovation on
               behalf of piety and to help the right teaching which was in distress, and we did not
               turn away our faces as from enemies, but welcomed them as our brothers, who for a
               short time were at discord respecting the paternal inheritance, in a brotherly but
               not a wicked manner. And we did not praise them on account of the enmity: but we
               received them on account of the zeal. For separation for piety's sake is better than
               vicious concord. And for this reason we made the loss our gain, silently removing by
               love the supposition that there was against us: and to this extent we changed the
               order of things, that the gift should not follow the election, but the election the
               gift; and we made use of other men's hands in this matter, having been a little
               anticipated by the Spirit." From the citation it is possible to discern clearly that
               the innovation which was thought to have been introduced at that time was one similar
               to the present position, and that, while the election and the right of ordaining
               belonged to one set of men, others ordained, especially from his expression, "and we
               made use of other men's hands in this matter"; and above again, "who for a short time
               were at discord respecting the paternal inheritance." But he shows that those who had
               the right to elect and ordain, one among whom in <pb n="15"/> particular was the holy
               Gregory himself, concurred in the election with those who on account of zeal for the
               orthodox faith had once made an innovation, by uniting with those who separated and
               made the innovation, and accepting what had been done by them, in that they said,
               "and for this reason we made the loss our gain, silently removing by love the
               supposition that: there was against us; and to this extent we changed the order of
               things, that. the gift should not follow the election, but the election the gift." </p>
            <p> If Gregory the Theologian, and that being orthodox, or rather a guide and teacher of
               orthodoxy, bore with and endured those who seceded from him out of superfluous zeal,
               and accepted the things done by them by way of innovation, let Flavian, who is
               infected with heresy, either change his evil belief under teaching, and rejoice with
               us in the things done by us; or if he remains such as he is let him justly suffer
               annoyance, and put up with it, enwrapped as he is in the bonds of impiety. But, since
               there was also contained in your letter the question on what conditions it is right
               to adopt a union with those of the same opinions, it is necessary to say this much.
               It is right to unite with those of the same opinions, when they are of the same
               opinions in everything. Putting aside the complete union of the holy churches, since
               that needs a lawful concession on certain points, the man who privately wishes to be
               united with you must in everything seek the same ends; as Constantine also of
               God-loving memory proclaimed to the people before the church; <pb n="16"/> the
               mention of the Henotikon only being passed over as superfluous: for, if it does not
               touch the stumbling-blocks that sprang up at Chalcedon and separated the churches,
               what is the use of mentioning it? To the pious king this was necessary for the
               general union of the churches, since he was desirous of showing that the king who
               preceded him also had before him the object of bringing into union those who
               separated on account of the synod at Chalcedon, and that he is not now the first to
               introduce this question into the churches, as if making an innovation. We for our
               part therefore have written these things out of our poverty, because you bade us do
               this also, giving us an example of a modest or humble disposition. But you will of
               yourself add things greater and better than these, inasmuch as you have already
               received from the Spirit together with the pastorate ability also to feed the flock
               with understanding. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
