<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3048">In the Name of a Synod to the Suffragans of Apamea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">70-73</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.20">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">A letter of summons in the name of a synod to the
               bishops under the metropolis of Apamea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               187th letter.</head>
            <p> Having been summoned by the grace of God and by the behest of our pious king, we
               assembled before <pb n="71"/> the evangelical throne of the great Christ-loving city
               of Antiochus for the purpose of carrying into act whatever seemed good to his
               serenity's God-loving sovereignty: and one among those who assembled with us was
               Peter the saintly bishop of the illustrious metropolis of the Apamenes; and, being
               moved by an affectionate disposition, we were induced to ask his love of God how it
               was that not one of you was with him, as was in fact the case with the other bishops
               of the resplendent metropolitan cities. But he said that he wondered whether it was
               in ignorance of what had happened that we were putting such a question. He was
               sighing, but still he related how you separated yourselves from the common communion
               of us all (for it was not from his), and that he left no method of inviting you to
               concord untried. And, having included a few of the things that were done as he said
               in a petition, he presented it to the saintly patriarch of the God-loving bishops of
               the East, asking his beatitude to take canonical steps against the offences committed
               against him by you, or rather against the common union of the holy churches. For we
               were in fact all met together in accordance with fair adornment and ecclesiastical
               order. And, when we had heard the petition, the serious character of the things that
               have been done called for a decision suited to the circumstances to be put forth: for
               the above-mentioned <pb n="72"/> God-loving bishop of the metropolis of the Apamenes
               made certain of the charges themselves almost stand before every man's eyes without
               needing testimony from without. But we, considering that we are ministers of peace,
               and that, as we are one body, it is our duty to travel along every path that does not
               tend towards schism, but summons those who have fallen away to sin to repent,
               believed it to be right that we should summon you canonically, and should urge you to
               make a defence for the sins that have been committed, and should give time for
               repentance, and to say farewell to thoughts that lead to division, and with fitness
               to cry out to you also the words of the prophet which say, "Stand upon the ways and
               see and ask for the paths of the Lord that have been from everlasting, and see which
               is the good way and walk therein, and ye shall find holiness for your souls." For a
               man to sin is human. But after he has once sinned not to listen to the admonition of
               friends, who summon him to them in a manner befitting priests, gives occasion for the
               apostolic distinction that says, "Behold therefore the mildness and severity of God,
               on them which fell severity, but on thee the mildness of God, if thou continue in
               mildness: and if not then shalt thou also be cut off." For it is in fact not obscure,
               especially to those to whose lot it has fallen to feed churches, that the authority
               of the holy canons cannot remain a dead letter in such things, seeing that <pb n="73"
               /> "the catholic and apostolic church requires blamelessness." </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
