<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3049">To the Master of the Offices</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">73-75</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.21">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the Master of the Offices.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               189th letter.</head>
            <p> The illustrious Rufinus, the well-tried servant of your high eminence, when he
               brought to our meanness your revered and pious letter, which summoned us to the city
               of the men of Heraclea, was unable to receive our mean answer, because he was
               detained by a disease of the eyes; which answer was a short time ago brought to your
               glory by the resplendent Leontius, who is also one of your slaves. But, now that he
               is about to go up to the royal city, in payment of my debt I greet your highness. And
               I report and announce to you that the God-loving bishops residing in this city
               thought it a right thing to warn those who were bishops in Second Syria, of Epiphania
               I mean and of Arethusa and of Rhaphania, by a letter of summons, and summon them to
               them, in order that they might be detached from the disorderliness of those who are
               heads of the monasteries in those parts, and have unreasonably broken away from
               communion with us, and that they might either convince the others or be willing to
               yield to what is right. And some of those who rejoice in schisms and divisions, <pb
                  n="74"/> and have often conspired and plotted against my mean self also, and do
               not escape the knowledge of anyone, though they themselves desire to do so, persuaded
               them not only to pay no attention to their summonses, but even to compose an
               insulting and unlawful document against the holy synod of God-loving bishops, a
               document that contains blasphemous expressions against God and against the dress of
               the priesthood. These things the afore-mentioned saintly bishops discussed with the
               sacred and venerable book of the gospels laid before them, as well as the other sins
               committed by them at different times, and they found them to be madly excited (?)
               against the holy canons and church discipline and against our pious king, as the
               transactions in their case in fact show; and they laid them under sentence of
               deprivation: knowing clearly that, if such offences were to be left without reproof,
               the ordinances of the Spirit would be trampled upon, and any man who is a hearer
               would rise in opposition to those to whose lot it has fallen to be heads of churches:
               and, as in the case censured by the divine Paul, disorder would prevail, and the foot
               would say, "Because I am not the hand I am not of the body," and the ear, "Because I
               am not the eye I am not of the body," and each of the limbs would renounce its proper
               place. For there is a canon which says thus; "Bishops who are summoned to a synod
               should not treat the summons with contempt, <pb n="75"/> but should go and teach or
               be taught for the purpose of reforming the church and the rest. But, if they treat it
               with contempt, such a man will be bringing an accusation against himself, unless
               perhaps he stay away on account of illness." But these gentle persons under.
               consideration not only set this statute at naught, but also insulted with unlawful
               expressions the God-loving bishops who are assembled in the great city of Antiochus
               which after God is yours. They thought fit to call them "no bishops at all," and in
               unmeasured arrogance they uttered yet other fatuous words which I shrink even from
               taking upon my tongue. It rests therefore with your excellency not by negligence to
               allow us to be trampled upon by such men, and be calumniated by men who are seeking
               their own interests, but to report the truth to the pious Christ-loving ears of our
               pious king, and extend to us sinners, who pray for your salvation, the just help that
               you extend to all who suffer wrong. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
