<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3050">To the Fathers</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">75-80</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.22">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the fathers.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the 23st
               letter.</head>
            <p> Since all the holy fathers, if we may so say, have written us many various letters,
               we considered it necessary to write in a common epistle to you what we have to say
               concerning the common state, and to stir you all up to one harmonious petition and
               earnest <pb n="76"/> prayer. But the matters which ought to be conveyed in writing to
               your sanctities in particular are these. You did not do well or worthily of
               yourselves in not sending the devout deacon Stephen. The proof that he was confined
               to bed, by which you tried to prove his infirmity, we as a mean and sinful man will
               perhaps accept: but I have no means of saying whether Christ has also accepted it.
               For he is in fact even now still the same who ordered the man who was paralyzed and
               had for the greater part of his life been confined to bed to take up his bed and
               walk. However we will say with Paul, "All forsook me." And we will readily add, "May
               it not be laid to their charge." But it is a matter for your prayers that the other
               thing also which he says may be granted us, "The Lord stood by me and strengthened
               me." For to say the words which follow these is too great a thing for me, I mean, "In
               order that by me the preaching might be completed and all the peoples might hear."
               But, since we have in fact come to mention that matter, we will say a few words about
               it also; since, when writing a common epistle to all of you, we forgot it owing to
               the multitude of subjects of discussion. Musonius, the uninstructed and presumptuous
               man, who takes no account of the judgments of God, after disturbing and upsetting
               Isauria has gone as we have learned to Alexandria. For, being infected with two very
               serious diseases, <pb n="77"/> with avarice I mean and with pride, he wished to be a
               legislator for the men of the whole province. And he despised like a carnal man the
               smallness of his city (for to spiritual men the privileges of the priesthood are
               matters that cannot be balanced, and are not weighed by the size of the cities, but
               judged by the dignity of the sacred office), and, making the God-loving Solon bishop
               of his metropolis, a man unversed in affairs and otherwise peacefully disposed, his
               ally, he caused constant disturbances, requiring from each of the bishops
               <foreign>homologiai</foreign> or professions in writing concerning principles
               approved by him. He even went so far as to draw up a minute? in which it is stated
               that all the names of those who ministered in any capacity whatever, presbyters and
               deacons and monks and laymen, ought to be expunged from the sacred tablets: so that
               everyone thereupon shrank from this burdensome and endless statute, and thenceforward
               they talked to one another and said, "We are progressing by degrees; we shall also be
               required to be re-baptized and re-ordained as it is said." And all in the province,
               being goaded by this idea as by some sting, rose against their bishops, and they
               upset things that had been rightly done before: insomuch as to name all who had been
               left out, and associate in. communion with those who hold the opposite opinions: and,
               to put it plainly, to go over to the opposite party, and drive the bishops out of
               their own churches. <pb n="78"/> While these things were going on, the gallant
               Musonius was sitting inside his house; for, though he is bishop of another city, he
               registers his fathers' house at Olba; and he resides for the most part either there
               or in the metropolis of the men of Seleucia; and he only creates disturbances and in
               tyrannical fashion lays down heavy and unendurable laws. This man we have now already
               for three years borne with ll meekness, though we often whispered of his madness, and
               many times we reconciled him when he was lightly breaking away and turning backwards.
               Wherefore also, when the bishops were assembled here, the same Musonius accused some
               of them of behaving in an undiscriminating or unlawful manner. And, when these also
               turned round upon him and accused him in their turn of lending his money on interest
               contrary to the canons, he was convicted, and was silenced. And, whereas he ought to
               have repented of this, with great shamelessness he proclaimed the sin a virtue,
               saying that his church possessed nothing, and lamenting about poverty and need: in
               consequence of which we ourselves assigned to him from here a sum of twelve darics a
               year." Having received this he went away, after communicating with us and making a
               promise to the bishop of his metropolis to go up also to the cities of Isauria that
               had gone astray, and to undertake labour for a good end. And, when he reached the
               province," he again lay hid (?) in his usual <pb n="79"/> haunts, and did not stir
               his foot anywhere, and never once opened his presumptuous mouth that has no door as
               the proverb says, and is learned only in arousing uncanonical contentions. Thinking
               this an occasion that provided him with a means of amassing base gains, he composed a
               letter to the devout presbyter Longinus who is with us, fishing for yet another sum
               of gold, and a contribution of sacred property. And, failing in this, he turned to
               men in Alexandria who are infected with an uncanonical disease like his and a madness
               of no ordinary kind: who themselves received him as a priest, like Micah whose story
               is recorded in the Tribes, him I mean of the hill-country of Ephraim: who, having
               made a molten image out of his mother's silver and set this up as a god, found a
               young man, a Levite, and, filling his hand, took this man as a priest, saying to him,
               "Abide with me and be unto me a father and a priest, and I will give thee ten pieces
               of silver by the day, and a pair of garments, and the necessaries of thy life."
               Whence also we believe that both Musonius and those who shall receive him or have
               received him will suffer the same end as those who oppose the judgments of the Holy
               Spirit and pervert the right ways of the Lord. But, to establish what has been said,
               we have thought good to quote also out of his fatuity some words taken <pb n="80"/>
               from his actual letter that he wrote to the religious presbyter Longinus, words which
               prove the passions that lurk in him. They are as follows: "But you remember that I
               said to you, 'The patriarch ought to have sent something to our church as treasures.
               By this means the men themselves also become more enthusiastic. In this way Flavian
               also acted to the bishop of Germanicupolis, when he gave both robes and treasures to
               the unholy Bisula, and he drew the inhabitants of his country to him.'" And again:
               "For, although we do not ourselves know it, we ought to take an example from the
               adversaries, how they show all energy and watchfulness in making presents to those
               who are in opposition to them and endeavouring to bring them over to them by a gift.
               For you are not unaware that nothing persuades unlearned persons so effectually as a
               present and a gift." You see how, involved as he is in the passion of avarice, he
               puts forward the specious name of the church and the simpleness of unlearned persons,
               decorating the passion with mild words as with colours. I have also many other
               letters of his that he wrote to me, from which it is clearly apparent how I sought to
               change his haughtiness by mildness, and after many toils and labours did no good. And
               at last, becoming weary, I handed him over to the judgments of God, because he
               wrought such disturbance, and gave to those who were standing in the right way turbid
               upheaval to drink. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
