<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Solon, Bishop of Seleucia in
               Isauria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">81-83</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.23">
            <pb n="81"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Solon, bishop of Seleucia in
               Isauria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               270th letter.</head>
            <p> Your sanctity has acted rightly and has shown a disposition consonant to the divine
               canons in thinking it right to ask me about Musonius and Paul. But, seeing that they
               have left their own flock, and played the part of hirelings and not of shepherds,
               whatever else can one say except that it is necessary that these men should be
               stripped of all priestly authority, and that they should be cut off from the number
               of the shepherds? We know that our Saviour also says these words in the Gospel: "He
               that is an hireling and is not the shepherd, whose own the sheep are not, when he
               hath seen the wolf coming, leaveth the sheep and fleeth, And the wolf catcheth the
               sheep, and scattereth them. But the hireling fleeth because he is an hireling, and
               careth not for the sheep." You therefore, in order that you may not be found liable
               to the very same punishments, are bound quickly to appoint shepherds for the rational
               sheep: for those that are at Meloe immediately and without delay, since, as I said,
               Musonius took to flight like a hireling, and made this excuse for his absence as you
               write (and we have heard others also who know state the same), though the canons do
               not allow a man to absent him<pb n="82"/>self from his flock on his own authority and
               without the consent of patriarchs or metropolitans: but for those at Olba after the
               winter season has passed, since it was for another reason that Paul set out for the
               royal city, and it has not yet been made manifest to what city or country he went
               when he returned thence. But it is known to everyone that, when the deprivation of
               men who have utterly neglected their own cities is lawfully effected and in
               accordance with the precepts of the holy canons, others are appointed in the places
               of those who have been deprived. But, if you resolve to ask our pious king about
               this, I mean whether the God-loving bishops in Isauria ought to assemble and discuss
               the matter, and to compose a clear epistle and to report to his hearing that the men
               who have departed have fled to those who are eager to support their schism, you will
               be doing very rightly, and, as far as one can guess, not contrary to the intention of
               his God-loving sovereignty. In my judgment this is a necessary and very advantageous
               step, and one which may show his piety that we avoid the rocks on all sides, and keep
               to the royal road and to the unity of the holy churches. While writing these things
               we weep and groan, and do not rejoice at our brothers' fall, and we consider how,
               while Musonius was extending his eyebrows upwards and puffing out his cheeks, and
               devoting his attention only to judging others, we were unaware of the fact that he
               was feeding his belly, and <pb n="83"/> that he was inflamed with the passion of
               avarice. We have also letters of his which lay bare his passions that are so
               shameful. As to the question I have thought it best to refer to the magnificent
               Oecumenius, since have great confidence in your perfection, and because you love the
               man just as we do. Moreover by referring the matter to a man who has already
               discussed this with us we shall escape the necessity of using many words; for we have
               no leisure, and we are not even able to take recreation owing to the multitude of
               subjects of concern. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
