<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Theotecnus the
               <foreign>Archiatros</foreign></title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">83-85</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.24">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Theotecnus the
               <foreign>archiatros</foreign> or chief physician</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               293rd letter.</head>
            <p> The things that have been indicated or announced to us from the royal city are many
               and various. But the sum of them is this. The bishops who assembled there have
               separated without coming to an agreement, since the majority of them or, if one may
               so say, all except the Romans, were found to be orthodox, but were obliged to
               associate themselves with the state of affairs? prevailing in the royal city, the
               saintly bishops Eleusinius and Proclus having for the time run away. Some said that
               the object of their endeavours was not to accept the impious. synod that assembled at
               <pb n="84"/> Chalcedon in respect of the definition of faith but "in respect of
               the rejection of Eutyches and of his doctrines." But that this endeavour or trick is
               the action of heretics your Christ-loving eloquence also is not unaware. But there is
               yet another thing which it is right that you should know: that is that our pious king
               and the glorious Master of the Offices wrote to my meanness by Leontius the
               illustrious magistrian who is called Tapitoleon to ask that the deprivation of those
               no-bishops and wicked men in Second Syria might be annulled. And I wrote in answer to
               this, "Since this is your pleasure, if they lawfully repent, the intention of the
               canons receives them, provided all the bishops who deposed them assemble together and
               canonically receive them." It is enough to say this much as in a letter and in a few
               words. For forbear to say that a certain defence-of the definition of the men who
               assembled at Chalcedon was also contained in the pious letter: against which again we
               further argued without any harsh speech, advancing the words of truth in opposition
               to the plausible pretexts there put together. Regarding the name of Nestorius, which
               has been included among the commemorations of the martyrs in the metropolis of the
               Tarsians, and has rightly scandalized you, we have written to the God-loving bishop
               Dionysius such things as are fitting and proper, and our words have no doubt come to
               the knowledge of your God-loving <pb n="85"/> intelligence. The present of a shoe
               woven of wool have received, and as a sinner I have prayed that a reward for it may
               be given you from above, you who do well in mingling spiritual healing with material.
               For the gift is material; but the fact of the affectionate thought is spiritual, and
               therefore a thing that contains in it comfort for soul and body. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
