<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To the Devout Monks of the Blessed Lord
               Isaac</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">90-92</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.29">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the devout monks of the blessed lord
               Isaac.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 5th book the 97th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The trial concerning the affair of the magnificent Antipater has by your prayers
               passed away: and in accordance with the mercy granted us from above we have been
               delivered from this: the magistrates having given this one order only, that the said
               Antipater shall not be permitted to remove anything from the room in which he put his
               baggage, since you are ready to give satisfaction on this point also. But now I am
               writing <pb n="91"/> to your love of God about a matter which is for the common
               benefit, and tends to the advancement of the right faith and the preservation and
               extension of the holy churches of God in the East. The men of the camp of Anasartha
               by their <foreign>psephismata</foreign> proposed various persons in order that a
               bishop might be ordained for them; and I for my part determined that we would ordain
               the religious father Stephen, who is adorned with character and with faith, and, if
               one may so say, with all excellencies of virtues, bishop for the aforesaid camp: not
               because we wish to honour the man, for I know that he shrinks from this, having more
               regard for his own profit; but, just as I paid no attention to this but complied with
               the judgments of God, in the same way beg your holinesses also and him not to resist
               the grace of the Spirit which calls him. For the whole force of Christianity tends to
               this, that we should not have regard and respect to our own interests but to those of
               others. Moreover, it is also utterly unreasonable that, while we are displaying such
               contests on behalf of the orthodox faith, we should entrust the presidency of the
               holy churches to reprobate persons, men too who (which I pray may not happen), when
               tribulation or persecution has come, as the holy Gospel says, are converted to
               impiety. Do your diligence therefore to obey this letter, and to send him whether he
               wishes or not: and be assuredly convinced of this, <pb n="92"/> that, if another man,
               who is reprobate, be instituted owing to his delay, you will be responsible for the
               loss. Do not pass him over and wish to send me someone else from your holy cloister
               in his stead: for I will not consent even to look at anyone else. I have chosen the
               religious father Stephen as being one of those mentioned in the
               <foreign>psephismata</foreign> by those who came from the aforesaid camp?!: and
               for us to introduce someone else not included in the <foreign>psephismata</foreign>
               is impossible. I add also that neither have I myself confidence?" in anyone else.
               This much we have written out of love. But, although we are a sinner, we have
               received, as you also with one accord confess, authority from Christ, who is God over
               all, to bind and loose: wherefore I wish you to know that, if you do not obey the
               words written above, you will be placed under a ban of excommunication; especially
               the devout Stephen himself, if he dare to resist this proposal. My reason for adding
               this after the completion of the letter is to show that it is from necessity that I
               come to adopt a decisive course of action. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
