<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Solon</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">16-23</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.3">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the same Solon, bishop and metropolitan
               of Seleucia in Isauria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 2nd book the 24th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The letter of your religiousness was enough to bring even those who are not easily
               roused to wrath into a state of anger and indignation. But for our. part, because we
               are accustomed to endure such things philosophically, especially when they are done
               and <pb n="17"/> said by honoured and beloved men like you, we have thought it right
               in this instance also not to strive with contentious words, but rather, as far as
               possible, in consonance with the actual truth to write such things as are in accord
               with the judgments of God, and to show that we are free from all cause of blame on
               your part. Callistus was not dragged before us by anyone upon any new charges being
               made against him by you. Then he would have had ground for complaint, inasmuch as
               discipline would, as you say, have been violated, and a judgment and cause that
               belonged to the holy throne of the metropolitan would have been forcibly removed
               before examination or pardon by being called up, as one may say, to the exaltation
               and height of the patriarchal and apostolic throne. But, if the matters upon which
               the party of Hilarian and Musonius made charges against Callistus were examined and
               investigated while your holiness was in this great city, how comes it that the
               transaction does not lie beyond the reach of your objections? Nay, how can you avoid
               praising us if you again recall to your memory how I turned benevolent ears to such
               faults, and to the bitter attacks of the accusers, and that with much wise moderation
               we tempered the vehemence of those men, and the gravity of the accusations in which
               he was involved; and that after this we further in some sort sent a request, which
               otherwise would not have beseemed us, to each of the bishops, asking them, <pb n="18"
               /> inasmuch as he had repented, to vote unanimously for the forgiveness which was to
               be granted him; and, upon our showing such solicitude, he received letters from each
               of the bishops, and we received these with joy, and immediately the things written
               were read, and the decree of pardon followed? But, as for the matter which is now
               thought by Hilarian to be connected with the same subject, how will it be suited for
               the hearing of your love of God, and that when the sin was directed against me, I
               mean that of the forged letter? For I do not know if anyone else among men, or an
               angel from heaven, will come and disprove its spuriousness, seeing that its prejudice
               is so manifest, and that Hilarian's handwriting also, when compared with his other
               signatures, utters, so to speak, a voice and proclaims the fiction. Therefore look
               into these things with carefulness and sincere God-loving thought, and consider
               whether you are not making a preposterous request, viz., that the patriarch should
               receive judgment from your love of God in a case of insults or sins that were
               directed against him, and that in the words sung by everyone you may turn things
               upside down; and whether we ourselves have not now the right to use your words, "I am
               insulted and contemned." I forbear to mention that, even after the conviction from
               the letter, Paul, the God-loving bishop of the city of the Olbians, came here, and
               bore witness and said that Hilarian said in the presence of his love of God that <pb
                  n="19"/> with Musonius' assent he wrote that the diaconate ought to be restored to
               Callistus, but that he should not in addition be archdeacon also, and hold the first
               place." But what is the modest defence to these things, which is given even by your
               sanctity (for this is the wonderful thing)? "Callistus is not subject to reproof for
               saying of himself that he does not communicate with us in the matter of the mention
               of Peter and Palladius, who are by a violation of strict accuracy named in the sacred
               tablets, and in the matter of communion with the God-loving bishop of the city of the
               Hierapolitans, Philoxenus, who names a man who signed the things unlawfully done at
               Chalcedon." May the all-holy soul of Constantine hear these words, against whom that
               wicked man armed himself, both by writing to those on the other side and by creeping
               into the archive-house, and arming and inciting the governor of the province to do
               everything that could bow down his venerable old age and subvert the orthodox faith!
               For so much did he infuriate him, I mean the governor of Isauria at that time, that
               death alone put a stop to his fury against piety. May Solon also, who succeeded to
               Constantine's see, hear these words! and let him hold Callistus as a teacher of zeal
               for strict accuracy, because after intolerable impieties he has of his own accord
               come forth as an unlawful champion on behalf of the laws of the church, one who
               sprang suddenly from the ground <pb n="20"/> like the giants fabled in legends.
               However let Callistus stand upon this peak, there is no objection, and let Solon go
               up with him. Only let them stay in this citadel, and not immediately come down and
               say, 'All the cities of Isauria have also introduced into the sacred tablets the
               names of those who unlawfully signed at Chalcedon"; for it is time for me also to say
               what the well-disposed robber, who was crucified with our Lord and Saviour Christ,
               said to the blasphemous robber, "Dost not even thou fear God, seeing thou art in the
               same judgment?" These things we for our part say out of an abundant choice. But
               anyone who makes a careful investigation will find that your love of God has not
               maintained the order of things which you took over from Constantine the metropolitan
               who is among the saints, but that your feathers have gradually fallen off after the
               manner of a bird, while our meanness has carried out a gradual progress, and has in
               no way fallen short of the beginning previously made. Indeed every one of those who
               were ordained by us, whether he incurred dangers or was free from danger, removed the
               names under suspicion. For neither is the statement made by your religiousness true,
               I mean that the God-loving Mammian bishop of the city of the Damascenes mentions the
               name of one who signed. Immediately upon his setting foot in the city. and
               sacrificing the first sacrifice and at the same time with it he offered to God the
               legal omission of his <pb n="21"/> name. But the omission of the mention of such men
               as Peter and Palladius we for our part have for the present not promised to any man.
               The things that must be yielded to junctions or general unions of God's holy churches
               are both regulated and defined, and we never stretch ourselves to things outside the
               bounds of moderation, "being vainly puffed up," as the apostle says, and wandering
               outside the royal road. If we had in the beginning yielded this difficulty in these
               other names to you who did this, but had stopped at this one only, that of those who
               signed as you say several times, how could I on my own authority have laid either
               upon myself-or upon those who have in no way attained to this strictness "heavy
               burdens and grievous to be borne," according to the Gospel saying, which injure the
               right teaching of the faith and upset everything owing to the stress and difficulty
               of the present time? The things done in the case of Callistus are therefore as stated
               above. But your love of God ought also to reflect upon the accusations that Musonius
               and Hilarian brought in the case of the devout Eustace, and how we for our part dealt
               with the affair in a proper way and in a seemly fashion; and to see with your eyes
               how honourable is the place that you hold before us, though you show an appearance of
               forgetting. Indeed I know clearly that in the matters in which it is my duty to
               trouble my mind: have not relaxed at all But, if any man seeks to be burdened <pb
                  n="22"/> by God's laws, "we have no such custom, neither the churches of God." But
               may the Lord be witness. for me of my words and of the feelings of my heart, that I
               am still even now praying that Callistus may be found upon manifest proofs to be
               innocent of the charges made against him, as the previous proceedings also and the
               various measures taken by me in his case showed! But, if he shall neglect the right
               road of defence and take refuge in an accuracy of names that does not exist, and in
               the fact that he does not communicate with us, it is time for me to say to him
               appropriately the words of Jeremiah, "'If thou whiten thyself with natron and take
               thee much soap, thy sins have scarred thee before me' saith the Lord." But neither
               will the religious Hilarian escape from the strict execution of the canons, if he be
               proved to be lying. A certain term of days has been fixed for him, and this has been
               set down in writing; and, if he fail to appear and make no defence to the accusation
               against him, Callistus will be released from the interdict, and the position of a man
               under a charge will rightly pass to him, as disturbing the discipline of the Church.
               <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> But you must believe that,
               after I had given the letter to the devout Stephen, something that had been omitted
               came into my mind, I mean, to tell you the time within which the religious bishop
               Hilarian is to come, or else the things stated in the letter about Callistus and
               about him will be carried <pb n="23"/> out. The time is reckoned from to-day, and
               extends to the end of the month of September. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
