<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To the Clergy of the Metropolis of
               Apamea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">92-96</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.30">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the clergy of the metropolis of
               Apamea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">from those during episcopacy, from the 5th book the
               135th letter.</head>
            <p> Your love of God, marked out as you are by the orders of the holy clergy of the
               church, and addressing a <pb n="93"/> bishop, and upon a spiritual subject, ought not
               to have cited the rhetor of Greece in the preludes or beginnings of your admirable
               letter. In due time Elijah the Tishbite, urged by the same zeal, will now say to you
               also, "Is it because there is not a prophet in Israel that ye go to inquire of the
               fly-Baal, the abomination of the gods of Ekron?" Fitly also will the book of Proverbs
               reprove you which says, "Drink waters out of thy vessels and out of the spring of thy
               wells." You did not make search in order to draw from the divine scripture a saying
               that would prove the swiftness and weakness of human life. For the prophet David
               says, "Our days pass away like a shadow." And the divine Job, while playing the
               philosopher during the grievous trial caused by his suffering, said, "For we are of
               yesterday, and we know not": and again, "My life was swifter than a runner." We are
               not unaware that the wise Paul also often quoted the words of poets in speaking to
               certain persons. But the character of the hearers, who had not been instructed out of
               the God-inspired words, in itself made the use of testimony from these seemly in his
               case. The divine scripture should therefore have been enough for you, and you should
               not have started by making the beginning spurious and false. We therefore (for we
               must now return to that which is more useful and more urgent) have been grieved at
               the decease of Isaac of religious <pb n="94"/> memory, your bishop; and we have been
               distressed because he left the present life before he had maintained a contest on
               behalf of the doctrines of orthodoxy, which he proclaimed in writing and otherwise in
               this great Christ-loving city. However we submit to God, the orderer of such deep
               judgments. But the duty that remains for us is this; not to be negligent and leave
               your holy church without a shepherd during the days that are so venerated of the
               saving Passion and of the Resurrection of Christ. Make haste therefore and draw up
               quickly a <foreign>psephismata</foreign> in favour of three men of favourable repute
               and well known for virtue and, as it is written, "powerful men and religious, men
               that are just and hate pride." But the powerful man is defined by the divine law as
               the man who through his life and conduct has power over the passions of the flesh,
               and possesses accurate and well-tried faith, which is greater than everything and is
               the foundation of our salvation. For the man who is to stand at the head of rational
               souls must have power in him, and is "able to comfort by sound teaching and to refute
               the gainsayers," as the Apostle, who had Christ speaking in him, handed down to us.
               This besides pleasing God will also gladden our pious king, seeing that he is much
               concerned for the apostolic faith, and has been brought up in such doctrines from his
               boyhood: who also in some sort did not praise our meanness for having delayed until
               to-day to institute shepherds for the cities <pb n="95"/> that are in need, who shall
               feed them with understanding. Do not therefore look to worldly authorities, or under
               the influence of fleshly considerations put forth your vote in favour of certain men
               who live in a worldly atmosphere and need much purification, and ought not to be
               entrusted with the purification of the people and to offer the bloodless and rational
               sacrifice on behalf of the faults of whole congregations and as an expiation: for I
               hear that certain men among you dare to do such things, thinking to make a mockery of
               things that are divine and not subjects for mockery. Let no one think that I shall
               acquiesce in a vote in favour of such men, no not if I be very mad. It does not suit
               me because of the inconsiderate action of certain persons to "partake in other men's
               sins," as it is written, or for no purpose to be sent to the eternal fire. When
               therefore you have duly drawn up a <foreign>psephisma</foreign> in accordance with
               our counsels, or rather according as the sacred ordinances and laws provide, let
               there come according to custom devout men, men modest in their conduct and earnest in
               character, such as are fitted to approach the apostolic throne and receive its
               judgment. We learn that, while Isaac of saintly memory was breathing his last,
               certain persons, wishing to hide their own faults, by an evil action dared to remove
               from his office the man who was entrusted with the stewardship of the church
               property, and to put forward <pb n="96"/> others in his place, having unlawfully and
               contrary to custom taken the keys from him. Accordingly we have determined that the
               man who administered the stewardship before shall hold the same charge, and those who
               have now been introduced shall be turned out and remain somewhere at a distance, and
               that they shall not participate at all, lest by depriving him for a short time of his
               stewardship we seem to be giving him also some just reason for not giving an account
               for the whole of his administration in time past. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
