<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Simeon, Bishop of Chalcis</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">104-06</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.37">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Simeon, bishop of Chalcis.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 7th book the
               238th, 240th letter.</head>
            <p> The devout monk so-and-so came to us, sadly lamenting and saying that he had been
               separated by your love of God and forbidden to live in the monastery of the holy lord <choice>
                  <reg>ʿAkiba</reg>
                  <orig>'Akiba</orig>
               </choice>, where he had also been: educated from the beginning and practised
               philosophic modes of life. What moved you to this was, he said, because it was he who
               told us that the man who is <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> and also
               <foreign>periodeutes</foreign> of the village of <pb n="105"/> Thelhadin, who had
               previously been tried by us at a time when the saintly bishops were here, and
               themselves also joined us in the examination, had treated the canonical inhibition
               with contempt and presumed to take part in the sacred ministry. When I learned this,
               I judged it right to send and tell your love of God that, as God is witness, I did
               not even know the very name of this monk, nor was I acquainted with his personal
               appearance, until I learned it just now, when he made the complaint to me; nor was it
               he who disclosed a fact that was hidden: for it was already being whispered by
               everyone. Whence those of the house of the God-loving bishop Maron also had learned
               it before this came to the knowledge of my vileness, and they were distressed in
               themselves, and did not reveal it or tell it out: but they concealed the distress and
               kept it to themselves, as the truth is witness. It is therefore the duty of your love
               of God to release the man from his inhibition, seeing that it is without cause, and
               he gave no handle for blame against him. For the <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> or
               <foreign>periodeutes</foreign>, whom we just now mentioned, whether it is openly
               or secretly that he presumes to transgress the law by treating with contempt the
               inhibition from us, in the same way and without any difference rouses the wrath of
               God. For, though a man escape men's eyes, he cannot escape the eye that sees
               everything. Let such a man hear also from the singing prophet, "He that planted the
               ears, <pb n="106"/> doth He not hear? or He that created the eyes, doth He not
               perceive?" Let this therefore be a matter for inquiry, and for your consideration:
               for our part, bound as we are by respect for your venerable age, we commit everything
               to you: for know that, as you have undergone a contest on behalf of the orthodox
               faith, and have shown great concern on behalf of accuracy in this respect, so you
               will show similar concern in the case of the canons. But for the present please
               release from his inhibition the devout monk whom we have many times mentioned, who
               brings you this letter; since, to say the truth, he has not committed any of the sins
               with which you have charged him. As to the matters" that were the cause of the devout
               deacon Stephen coming to you, do your diligence to handle them as befits you and is
               reasonable, in order that none of the troubles which have been stirred up may remain
               without healing and without cure. This will bring you no small praise both in the
               sight of God and in the sight of men. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
