<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3072">To Simeon, Bishop of Chalcis</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">106-10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.38">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the same Simeon, bishop of
               Chalcis.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 7th book the
               267th, 269th letter.</head>
            <p> For my part I had no need of words and of assurance by letter as regards the various
               matters that have happened and been transacted with the tranquillity of <pb n="107"/>
               your love of God, since the facts, if one may so Say, utter a voice and plainly cry
               this out. But, because there is a time to speak, as there is also a time to keep
               silence, according to the saying of the wise Koheleth, I now wish to repeat again as
               in a summary the events that occurred before, and to say like the prophet, "I have
               kept silence, lest I should keep silence also for ever; I have refrained myself like
               a travailing woman." Your holiness probably, think, remembers that all through the
               summer the men from the village called Thelhadin were urging us, and that, though
               their request was refused by us once and twice (I do not hesitate to say even three
               times and many times), so that a chance might be given you of settling their affair
               by some wise method and God-pleasing plan, we effected nothing at all, but we were
               more pressingly and more violently urged by them, and we were now being abused even
               by the citizens themselves who saw that they were continually complaining to us and
               did not receive any answer; and thenceforward we had also to submit to murmurs of no
               ordinary kind. Whence also we exhorted the devout presbyter Ignatius, who happened to
               be here, to appease the men by some means and invite them to a peaceful frame of
               mind. At last, not to make a long story, we were compelled to resort to such an
               extreme measure as bringing the <foreign>periodeutes</foreign> himself here and
               having the details of the case examined before the <pb n="108"/> saintly bishops. How
               repulsive to the ears the counts of the accusations that were examined were I forbear
               to state, seeing that the gravity of these is known to those who examined them with
               us, and closed their ears when they were being examined and proved. But this I know
               clearly, that in the middle of the examination into these things the same
               <foreign>periodeutes</foreign> wanted to run away; and in the hearing of everyone
               and while he was standing up I said to him in clear and distinct tones, directing the
               words towards him, "If you dare to depart, you old man, before the investigation is
               ended, you will be excommunicate, and under deprivation." Upon hearing this he
               promised not to run away. And the next day, when his presence was required, though he
               was sitting in what is called the <foreign>psepheion</foreign>, and had been seen by
               certain men, he would not come: but he formed the plan of running away, and departed
               while in full health, thus offending against the reverence due to the apostolic see,
               and against the synod of saintly bishops. The saintly bishops Sergius and Marion, who
               are much devoted to your love of God, are trustworthy witnesses of these things.
               These things therefore having thus passed in order and been transacted, it is now
               your part, not mine, to say what punishment the man deserves who presumed to take
               part in priestly functions and down to yesterday to write letters as a
               <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> and to administer the affairs of the <pb n="109"
               /> district. When a man dares even to lie and swear, and to retain a thing in
               ignorance, and that after he has personally received the prohibition, what chance of
               forgiveness or indulgence can he have? Who is there even among men of very peaceful
               disposition whom he is not treating as a fool and rousing to an anger that is just
               and well-pleasing to God? For for a man to be jealous for the divine laws when they
               are transgressed is to offer a sacrifice to God, just as the opposite course, I mean
               to be silent on such occasions, is to rouse the wrath of Him who laid down such laws.
               And yet we for the sake of your holiness' tranquillity remained silent, as we ought
               not to have done under such circumstances: and, when at an earlier time those who
               came from the monastery of the holy lord <choice>
                  <reg>ʿAkiba</reg>
                  <orig>'Akiba</orig>
               </choice> were asking us about the same said <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> or
               <foreign>periodeutes</foreign>, we kept silence out of respect to you, because we
               were ashamed to expose the abominable character of the affair, of which even men of
               no distinction were not unaware. Quite recently again, when the religious presbyter
               father Cosmas came to us about this same matter, and: said that his conscience and
               that of the others was wounded, and that they ought not to communicate with a man who
               had trampled upon the strictness of the canons, and had reckoned the ban of
               excommunication as nothing, we were compelled to tell them the whole affair, and to
               place the facts proved by examination before their eyes and read them to them,
               fearing as we did the prophetic curse which lays under a miserable con<pb n="110"
               />demnation those who call bitter sweet or darkness light! After this again the
               letter of your love of God came, and we gathered together in our mind all the details
               of the same affair, and we summoned the said God-loving presbyter Cosmas to us, and
               we had some conversation with him concerning peace and concord; after which we
               thought it right for the sake of your holiness' tranquillity to relieve the
               above-mentioned presbyter from his punishment, and allow him communion: but only on
               condition of his remaining quiet and not approaching the office of
               <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> or <foreign>periodeutes</foreign> in any way,
               because, to speak in the words of scripture and in fitting language, some had been
               caused to stumble through him. But, while I was in the middle of writing these
               things, the company of the men of Thelhadin again assailed me, buzzing about my ears
               like bees: and they were again dismissed by us with insult and with many contumelies
               heaped upon them. It is therefore the duty of your sanctity to appoint such a
               <foreign>chorepiscopus</foreign> and <foreign>periodeutes</foreign> for them that
               God may be praised, and all occasion be cut off from those that wish to find
               occasion. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
