<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To the Clergy and Notables of
               Apamea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">110-12</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.39">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the clergy and notables of
               Apamea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 7th book the
               289th letter.</head>
            <p> The name and fact of concord is pleasing even in God's sight, for He himself said in
               the Gospel, "If <pb n="111"/> two of you shall agree on earth touching any matter
               whatsoever they shall ask, it shall be done for them by my Father which is in
               heaven"; and in the statute of piety also concerning the nomination of bishops it is
               ordained that a deliberate vote upon this must by all means be put forward by the
               common consent of the religious clergymen and of the eloquent and illustrious
               notables; a principle which our pious Christ-loving king also ratified. Wherefore we
               urge you again, as we have also already done, and that many times, to come to a
               united election of him to whom the bishopric of the illustrious metropolis of the
               Apamenes is to be entrusted. When you were divided, we, who were not under the
               influence of passion, were obliged ourselves to choose by a judgment that did not
               respect persons and to nominate for you the devout presbyter Cosmas, a man who was
               reputed to be fitted for this, according to the prevailing opinion of many respecting
               him. But, considering also the greatness of the thing, he would not consent. And
               therefore I have determined again to urge you, as I have said, to a united vote,
               since those whom some of you chose by name did not seem to us to be fit men: and to
               send this letter to you the religious clergymen, and to the eloquent and magnificent
               <foreign>ktetores</foreign> and to the men of repute at the same time, in order
               that I may be the first. to give you an example of concord by not writing to you
               separately, but as to <pb n="112"/> one church which is the body of the one and only
               and undivided Christ. You will agree, I know well, if, free from all prejudice and
               cavilling and favour, and from other such influences, you will put in your
               <foreign>psephisma</foreign> three men who are in the first place sound in the
               orthodox faith and show this by holding firmly to communion with us, and secondly are
               in character free from avarice, and will not approach the high-priesthood with
               unwashen feet, as it is said, but men who have been trained, if only to a moderate
               degree, in exercises of virtue, and able to rule, and who besides humility possess
               also a practised intelligence, in order that they may rather rule those that are
               under their authority, and not themselves be ruled by them, but also be men practised
               in divine doctrines. For he who stands at the head must also be a man "apt to teach,"
               and one who in character and speech shows himself "a pattern of good works," as the
               Apostle says. For we have in fact no other reason for using strict language about
               such things- except to avoid straying from what is right, and becoming liable to
               endless torment. For it is manifest that, although we are sinners, yet still in the
               nomination of bishops we in no point fall short of the principles about which many
               concern themselves. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
