<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3026">To Solon, Bishop of Seleucia in Isauria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">23-34</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.4">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the same Solon the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">from those during episcopacy, from the 2nd book the
               42nd, 50th letter.</head>
            <p> That there are limits even to long-suffering the sacred scripture clearly teaches
               us, in that it speaks thus in the person of God over all, "All the day I have spread
               out my hands unto a gainsaying and disobedient people": and again: "Thus saith the
               Lord, 'Have I become a wilderness to them of the house of Israel, or a desert land?
               Because my people said, "We will not be brought into subjection, and we will come no
               more unto thee."'" What therefore is one to say about Musonius, who was known to us
               for impudence and rustic denseness, and for love of money which is greater than all
               evil things, which Paul who had Christ speaking in him said is "the root of all
               evil?" Being excited by these same passions, he did not notice that he was blinded by
               beams and searching for other men's motes through love of fault-finding and not in
               order to guard the salvation of the brethren; insomuch as to upset the whole province
               as far as his power extends, disturbing both bishops and laity, and on his own
               authority adding burdens to burdens, and <pb n="24"/> not allowing them to arrive at
               excellence by gradual advance, but by his arrogance to cause those who were standing
               rightly to go over to the adversaries: insomuch that yet another prophecy is adapted
               for quoting against him which says, "My sheep fed upon the trampling of your feet,
               and drank the water that, was fouled by your feet; and ye thrust them with your sides
               and with your shoulders, and ye pushed them with your horns; everyone that was sick
               ye oppressed, till ye had driven them out, and my sheep were scattered upon every
               crossway"; and again, "That which was weak ye did not strengthen, and that which was
               sick ye did not heal, and that which was broken ye did not bind up, and that which
               was in evil plight ye did not comfort, and that which was wandering ye did not bring
               again, and that which was lost ye did not seek, and that which was sound ye subjected
               by force." Of all these things he has been guilty, and as far as in him lies he has
               made havoc of the province. To the orthodox he is burdensome and hostile, and is
               always kicking his neighbours and pushing them with his horns and gnashing his teeth,
               like unbroken asses or bulls or wild boars which feed in bestial fashion; but against
               the adversaries he has never dared to speak so much as a word, but sits inside his
               house and lives in fear; for such is the boldness which in face of those against whom
               it is right to be bold shrinks and draws back, but in committing illegal <pb n="25"/>
               deeds is precipitous and easily moved to action, and turns everything upside down.
               Finally, saying that he had become a man according to the saying of the prophet,
               because he loved strange men and went after them, he went away and found those who
               could satisfy his avarice and fill his hand. And he did not even think it wrong to
               exact interest: but, when the God-loving bishops were assembled here, he piteously
               alleged poverty and want, and openly confessed that for this reason he followed the
               avaricious practice of taking interest. And, though we gave him many admonitions, he
               did not even promise to withhold his hand from the unconsecrated means of gain for
               the future, and that though we ourselves gave him twelve gold pieces and promised to
               pay him that sum every year, and to relieve the needs of the church that had been
               entrusted to him; for this he used, so to speak, to bewail every day, going so far as
               to speak to one of our religious presbyters, whose name is Hesychius, in so many
               words thus, with the rusticity that is natural to him, "By God! what do you care, you
               who receive the stipend of the clergy of Antioch, while I possess nothing in my city,
               not so much as six denarii?" When I wrote to you before also, I quoted in the letter
               his abominable, unholy words, full of sacrilege, which he dared to write in an
               epistle to our religious presbyter Longinus; and they also are word for word as
               follows:—"But you remember that I said to you, <pb n="26"/> 'He ought to have sent
               something to our church as treasures. By this means not only do the men themselves
               become more enthusiastic, but the other cities also which are in error, as if they
               were jealous of us, would have come over and entered into accord with us. In this way
               Flavian also acted to the bishop of Germanicupolis, when he gave both robes and
               treasures to the unholy Bisula, and he drew the inhabitants of his country to him.'
               And your holiness also reported these words to the same holy patriarch, and you told
               me that you told him and he did not help you at all." What are we to say of a man who
               from such passions left his flock and would not submit to be poor with Christ, who,
               while as God He was rich, became poor of His own accord for our sake? This I say,
               because the money-lover called moderate means poverty, and because, now that he has
               reached this incurable depth of wickedness, it is absolutely necessary to strip him
               of the priestly functions, and to subject him to the punishment prescribed by the
               holy canons. For the seventeenth canon runs thus:—"Since many, while enrolled in the
               canon, by pursuing after covetousness and base gains have forgotten the divine text
               that says, 'He hath not put out his money upon interest,' and exact
               <foreign>hekatostai</foreign> or one per cent. when they lend, the holy synod has
               decided, that, if after this ordinance anyone be found receiving interest, contriving
               the matter by commerce or otherwise, and <pb n="27"/> exacting
               <foreign>hemioliai</foreign> or half the whole, or contriving anything else for
               the sake of filthy lucre, his deposition from the clergy shall follow, and that he
               shall be an alien to the canon." The hundred and seventh law also, laying down the
               same principles, says plainly as follows:—"Priests must not lend and receive
               interest, and what are called <foreign>hemioliai</foreign>." </p>
            <p> But as to Paul, who I would had never become bishop of the city of the Olbians, who
               because of a provocation that deserves to be treated with contempt left his flock,
               and was often admonished by me and calmed his savageness, and said that he would be
               calm and remain at peace and stay in his church, and "returned again to his vomit,"
               it is necessary for us to use the prophetic words and say, "We healed Babylon, and
               she was not healed. Let us leave her." Having a dispute with the religious Hilarian,
               bishop of Diocaesarea, about a certain monastery, an unhallowed and unseemly dispute,
               but still a dispute, he closed his ears to the apostolic statutes, and would not give
               them any admission, the statutes that say, "Behold! already ye are utterly in fault
               that ye go to law with one another; why do ye not rather take wrong? why do ye not
               rather suffer yourselves to be defrauded? but ye wrong and defraud and that your
               brethren; or know ye not that unrighteous persons shall not inherit the kingdom of
               God?"; and often, when he argued. in a childish and rustic manner about this, I
               persuaded <pb n="28"/> him and restored him to a proper state of mind. For he used
               always to swear and say that he had great faith in me, and that he revered my labours
               and struggles on behalf of the orthodox faith (I am even compelled to become a fool
               by quoting words in my own praise in order to show his disposition). And he would
               depart from our presence, as if he had been delivered from thoughts that wallow on
               the earth. But, being bound up in earthly things and infected with the perversity of
               strife, he would again abandon himself to the same contentiousness. And, being wholly
               swayed by anger, and swelling with contentious strifes, he would at one time go up to
               the royal city, and at another hasten to other countries. And at last, out of love of
               base gains, he went over to the schism of Musonius, the same Musonius who in his
               letter to the religious presbyter Longinus, which I mentioned a short time ago, with
               regard to the same Paul made, sentence for sentence and word for word; such
               statements as these: "But I will make yet another small addition to the letter. In
               everything I blame myself. I caused him to be made bishop of Olba, because thought
               that there was some good in him, since he displayed an appearance of undergoing a
               struggle for the faith. And it turned out contrary to my expectations. For he had a
               mad and wicked strife about a place which was subject to pay tribute to the lord
               Hilarian the bishop, while he wished to make this <pb n="29"/> subject to himself;
               and the afore-mentioned saintly bishop Hilarian bore with him as long as possible,
               but, not finding in him any advance towards settling the affair, at last appropriated
               the place to himself by setting up an altar there. For it was a monastery. But Paul
               went out of his mind and became like a demon and wrought every kind of disorder,
               reviling me also. He says he will come there to you. If this happens, write to me and
               I will come with the lord Hilarian also, and expose all his conduct. God forgive me
               and be merciful to me! he is not worthy to set foot even on the doorway of the church
               owing to the deeds done by him. I tremble and am afraid to repeat in the letter the
               facts regarding him, lest I pollute your ears which are benevolent and God-loving.
               May the holy God himself grant your holiness to me! For you are always our
               refreshment and consolation, whenever we remember your name." What mercy therefore
               can one admit in the case of men who are so foolish, and have unreasonably abandoned
               their flock on account of base and unhallowed passions, while the sacred canons do
               not give them any forgiveness, but the eighty-first canon plainly says: "If any
               presbyter or deacon or generally anyone of the sacred order should leave his own
               parish and pass to another, and afterwards, completely removing, try to live in
               another parish for a long time, he shall not minister any more; and especially if
               when his own bishop calls him and <pb n="30"/> admonishes him to return to his own
               parish he should not obey; and, if he should continue in the same disorderly conduct,
               his complete deposition from the ministry shall follow, so that he shall not again
               have a chance of returning to his place; but, if when his deposition takes place for
               this reason, another bishop should receive him, he also shall receive punishment from
               a general synod, as breaking the church laws." And moreover the purport of the
               eighty-seventh canon also is the same, and it says thus: "The bishops in each of the
               provinces must know that the bishop who stands at their head in the metropolis is
               himself entrusted with the care of the whole province, because those who have
               business meet in the metropolis from every place; wherefore it has seemed good that
               he shall also be the first in honour, and the other bishops shall do nothing outside
               the ordinary course without him, in accordance with the canon that has prevailed from
               the beginning from the time of the fathers, but only those things which belong to
               each man's province and to the districts under this; for each of the bishops has
               authority to administer his own parish, in proportion to the devoutness that has
               fallen to the lot of each, and to undertake the care of all the district that is
               under his city, in so far as to ordain presbyters and deacons, and to administer each
               matter with judgment or examination, but not to do anything outside the course, or
               even try to do so, without the <pb n="31"/> bishop of the metropolis. Neither shall
               he again do this without the consent of the other bishops." It is a long task to
               quote the things that are laid down in various places by the holy canons. However it
               is manifest from the citations made that, since Musonius and Paul have offended
               against the intention of all church discipline by leaving their country, they have
               made themselves aliens to the high-priestly office, since they have run counter to
               Him who said, "The good shepherd layeth down his life for his sheep: but he that is
               an hireling and is not the shepherd, and whose own the sheep are not, when he hath
               seen the wolf coming, leaveth the sheep and fleeth, and the wolf seizeth and
               scattereth them: but the hireling fleeth because he is an hireling, and careth not
               for the sheep." I had nearly omitted yet another fact which also affords a manifest
               proof of the madness and of the foolish impulses of Musonius. When he was making a
               charge against the devout archdeacon Callistus on the ground that he had bought the
               priestly order and status, thereby satisfying his wrathful inclination, and not
               actuated in any way by religious motives, he wrote to us to the effect that such a
               man as that ought to retire from the archidiaconate, but minister in the order of
               deacons. And he heard me quote, and with great justice, the passage of holy scripture
               that says, "May thine own mouth convict thee and not I!", and that also which was
               spoken by the divine Daniel to the <pb n="32"/> presumptuous elders, on one occasion,
               "Rightly hast thou also lied against thine head," and on another, "O thou that hast
               grown old in evil days, now have thy sins come near which thou usedst to commit
               aforetime, in judging unjust judgments, and in condemning the innocent, and in
               acquitting the guilty, when the Lord saith, 'The innocent and righteous thou shalt
               not slay.'" "For, if, as you say, he bought for money the grace that may not be
               bought, such a man ought to be removed not only from the archidiaconate, but also
               from the diaconate itself." What then is his ignorant and very rustic defence to
               this? "Callistus, while archdeacon, puts a stumbling-block in the others' way by
               carrying the holy gospel on his breast." "What does he say then, madman, to the
               ignorant person who is near him? Do you think that the cup of salvation of the divine
               blood has less virtue than the book of the holy gospels, and that the onlookers will
               not strike upon a greater stumbling-block, when a man who has bought the ministry
               carries this?" It seems to me that I am doing a superfluous thing in insisting on
               speaking words without eloquence to men who have contracted this unholy infection.
               These words your sanctity ought to speak to those who have remained sound, and to
               call to you the saintly bishops of your province, who confess the orthodox faith, and
               hold the same communion with us, but strip those men of the priesthood, inasmuch as
               they did not spare the rational <pb n="33"/> sheep, but reckoned the salvation of
               these secondary to their own passions, and left these as in a night in which is no
               brightness, and tried to submerge them so deeply in the turbid drink that they should
               not even have power to rise. However we believe that they will find such efforts
               vain. For by the mandate of the divine Spirit, and the lawful vote of the citizens
               through the mediation of your <choice>
                  <sic>sancity</sic>
                  <corr>sanctity</corr>
               </choice>, bishops and high-priest will be ordained for the cities who will feed
               their flocks with understanding. For he that speaks through Ezekiel says, "Behold! I
               will seek out my sheep, and will visit them. As the shepherd visiteth his flock on a
               day of storm and darkness when his sheep are scattered, so will I seek my sheep, and
               I will deliver them from every place wherein they have been scattered on the day of
               storm and darkness." Therefore visit these sheep with the help of God, and do not
               show negligence or give any occasion for delay, lest you bring yourself under the
               condemnation of these men, and draw upon your head the sentence hanging over them.
               For we may hear yet another sacred utterance of the prophet which says, "Cursed is he
               that shall do the works of the Lord negligently, and cursed is he that shall keep
               back his sword from blood." As there is a time for mercy, so also there is a time for
               cutting off: for we hear the same Spirit saying in Koheleth, "There is a time to
               plant, and a time to pluck up that which is planted: a time to kill, and a time to
               heal: a <pb n="34"/> time to break down and a time to build," and the other passages
               through which we understand how that it is with judgment that we must handle the
               divine words and fulfil the ministry of these. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
