<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3079">To Hypatius the Master of the
               Soldiers</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">113-15</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.40">
            <pb n="113"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Hypatius the Master of the
               Soldiers.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 7th book the
               458th, 465th letter.</head>
            <p> Your excellency's exalted letters I for my part receive with all affection and
               pleasure. Though you are so exalted and have so much glory, to which the Lord brought
               you, you encourage even humble men like me to inform you of things that are the
               truth, since you place nothing before this. Wherefore I also will truthfully inform
               your highness of the reason for which i have now composed this mean letter. It was
               not the devout presbyter Julian only who was accused by the holy church of the
               Tarsians of detaining property that belonged of right to it, but many others also
               with him; and in connexion with such accusations those who made the charge and those
               who were under the charge often wished to have recourse to the apostolic throne of
               the city that belongs to the Antiochenes and to you. And, since it is my habit not to
               cause trouble to anyone, but as far as possible to remove the complications arising
               from affairs, and not to inflict the burden of heavy expense upon men who are
               compelled to take so long a journey, and at such grievous cost to discuss the points
               on which they are in doubt, I determined that all the saintly bishops of First
               Cilicia should sit in conjunction with the eloquent <pb n="114"/> scholastics whom I
               certainly knew to be of good reputation, and who are well reported of both now and
               from their former life in Berytus, and discuss the details of the case of each of the
               persons who are said to be devouring church property. I also provided that two
               religious presbyters of the apostolic see, men versed in affairs and of minute
               experience in such matters, should be associated with them in the hearing of the said
               questions, with the book of the revered and holy gospels also laid in the midst. And
               after every point had been discussed in due order, and each of them had accepted the
               judgments given (how could they do otherwise?), the devout Julian only, being
               afflicted with covetousness, dared to treat the verdict? of the bishops with contempt
               contrary to the canons and the intention of the rightly-enacted laws, and to drag the
               hearing before a civil court, in so much as to incur indignation and the punishment
               prescribed by the canons. And upon his brother the God-loving Syrian, bishop of the
               city of Augusta, using many entreaties and promising to induce him to keep quiet his
               punishment was remitted, since I am in fact naturally inclined to the milder course.
               Indeed he tried by the use of deception to make the illustrious Heliodorus your
               curator also an accomplice in his plot by giving him false information: and upon your
               highness obtaining previous information of his proceedings all his plan was
               shattered. And now again, as if <pb n="115"/> dealing with a new matter he has set
               himself to entreat your highness, and to seem to be making a moderate request, that
               he may plead his cause before civil magistrates, after the examination and decision
               of the apostolic see and of the whole synod, the reversal of a decision of which is
               not permitted him by any authority, either by the holy canons or by the civil laws.
               Therefore by his words which are moderate and have a supplicatory appearance he is
               trying by means of his tricks to suppress things which have passed in order and been
               brought to a conclusion in this way. And his thoughts are, as one of the prophets
               said, "a pondering of iniquity, and his sin is hid." For how did he expect to get
               anything of this kind from you who are very just, seeing that everyone who has made
               havoc of the property of the church would have imitated his example, and reversed
               judgments rightly given, and transferred ecclesiastical causes to a magisterial
               tribunal, and that after judgment had been given and they had received an ending
               consonant to the laws and to the intention of the divine canons? Therefore I beg and
               entreat your excellency not to give him an opportunity of appealing to your
               friendship, and arming himself against the ordinances of the holy church, and
               destroying all discipline, of which you both are and ever will be a guardian and a
               protector, so long as you are preserved through your whole life. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
