<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3066">To Solon the Bishop</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">116-18</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.41">
            <pb n="116"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Solon the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 7th book the
               51st, 42nd letter.</head>
            <p> It is written somewhere in the legal writings that the divine Moses, after
               appointing judges over Israel, allowed them to judge unimportant causes (I must quote
               the actual expression of the God-inspired utterances): but a hard matter they were to
               report to him, and from him to receive the solution that God "the knower of secrets"
               (this also I take from another scripture) should reveal and signify to him. You also
               therefore as a giver and teacher of divine laws have followed this rule and reported
               to the apostolic see (not to my mean self who scarcely see even what is before my
               feet owing to the denseness of my understanding) a matter which seemed to be hard.
               Therefore your love of God must know that Maximus the presbyter, who has fallen into
               the snare of fornication, although he has shown fervent repentance, and for a period
               of five years has given himself up to such labours, cannot be restored and take his
               place in the sacred office: and it is a simple thing for us to obtain a solution of
               this question without trouble from the holy canons themselves. For indeed the
               God-loving bishops who met together at Neocaesarea made these distinct pronouncements
               in the ninth canon: "If a <pb n="117"/> presbyter be promoted after having previously
               sinned with his body, and confess that he sinned before ordination, he shall not.
               offer: but he shall retain the rest of his functions on account of his zeal in other
               respects." If then a man who before ordination has sinned with his body,
               <foreign>i.e.</foreign> has committed fornication (for this the Apostle also said,
               "Every sin is without the body, but he that committeth fornication sinneth against
               his own body"), is not permitted to offer, but to retain the rest of his functions on
               account of his zeal in other respects, how can it be doubted that he who has
               committed this same sin after ordination cannot offer the divine sacrifice, or
               consecrate the water of regeneration, or perform any such function? Let no man say,
               "What then is the advantage of repentance to a man who has committed fornication, if
               he is not after labours of continence to be restored to the sacred service?"
               Repentance brings about forgiveness and bestows communion in the bloodless sacrifice
               for the sake of purification and preservation upon those who wash away the sin by
               tears and the other forms of bodily mortification: but the service of the priesthood
               is the reward of a blameless character. The ninth canon of the three hundred and
               eighteen holy fathers also says thus, as you also know, "If men have without
               examination been promoted to be presbyters, and being. examined have confessed the
               sins committed by them, and after they have confessed <pb n="118"/> some men being
               moved in a manner contrary to the canon have laid a hand upon them, such men the
               canon does not accept: for the catholic church requires blamelessness." I forbear to
               say that you have adopted a very mild policy and one of exceeding leniency in the
               matter of Maximus, because the canon did not say anything plainly about a man who
               commits. fornication after ordination. You have openly permitted him (this was stated
               in your letter) to perform evening and morning prayers, and to sit on every occasion
               with the presbyters, a thing forbidden in the case of a man who has sinned before
               ordination and afterwards confessed; for this is clearly written down in the ninth
               canon of those who met together at Neocaesarea, which we mentioned a short time ago,
               which says that he should retain the rest of his functions on account of his zeal in
               other respects, but should not again go so far as to offer the rational sacrifice,
               and do things like this and of equal honour, Therefore, since you have the nature of
               what ought to be done from the canonical utterances themselves, do not allow anyone
               to take refuge in the unknown, and in the pretence of searching into the spirit of
               the holy canons. One seeks for the spirit in cases where nothing is defined in actual
               words and phrases. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
