<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3081">To the Archimandrite of the Monastery of
               the Holy Lord Simeon</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">120-23</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.43">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the archimandrite of the monastery of
               the holy lord Simeon.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 8th book the
               134th letter.</head>
            <p> Whereas Nonnus even before entering the holy Simeon's flock was often summoned to
               answer the charges and accusations that were being brought against him and did not
               obey, but, even when placed under an injunction by the God-loving
               <foreign>ekklesiekdikoi</foreign>, trampled upon this with similar impudence, like
               a man who had grown accustomed to treat holy things with contempt, and after
               repairing to me by night once only and in secret, as if doing things worthy of night
               and darkness, thought that he had thus done enough <pb n="121"/> to give satisfaction
               (?), and at last after receiving an explicit letter through your religiousness
               continued in the same shameless state, I for my part endured, and was not roused to
               just indignation: but after appointing him a limit of ten days I allowed him to have
               this doubled. And he behaved exactly as one who had not been summoned, alleging only
               pretexts founded upon sins, and answered through your religiousness that he asked
               that clergymen should not be present at his trial, because they are clergymen who
               have been injured by him, and from whom he used to receive the unhallowed and profane
               gains. For he did the same as those who have stolen or committed adultery, or
               perpetrated a murder, and say that those who have been outraged and injured by theft
               and those who have thus suffered by adultery and those who have suffered by murder
               ought not to be present at their trial. No wonder if, being guilty of such evil
               deeds, he belches forth such words. What will they say who 'hate judgment and pervert
               all right things, and build Zion with blood and Jerusalem with iniquity," as one of
               the prophets somewhere said? For how can one help saying that the hands are full of
               blood which have sold the gifts of the Holy Spirit, which he had no right to give to
               some men, or to take away from those who possess them? For this is the wonderful
               point about his sacrilege, that he used to hide himself as in some lurking place, I
               mean in hypocrisy, while hearing at <pb n="122"/> every ordination the anathemas and
               terrific curses that I pronounced against such unlawful gains, and to stop his ears
               "like the deaf asp that stoppeth her ears, which will not hearken to the voice of the
               charmer," as the singing prophet says. However, that I may not by using many words
               protract the letter unnecessarily, this is the second and third summons that I am
               addressing to him through your love of God, or, rather to speak more truly, a summons
               that has the force of the tenth and twentieth (for one may justly reckon them as
               equal in number to the days that have passed); since I wish even if late yet some
               time or other to induce him to make a defence, with the saintly bishops present
               according to the intention of the holy canons, and ready to conduct his trial, with
               the holy Gospels laid in the midst, and the terrific threat pronounced by them
               hanging over those who turn aside justice." But, if even after this letter he shall
               dare to delay, then after this the same divine statutes of church discipline shall
               pronounce judgment and the fitting verdict upon him. For we for our part in no way
               wished the circumstances of his case to remain unknown to the glorious notables also
               in Antiochus' city: but we even brought these as far as was possible to their
               knowledge; and we would have urged them and some of the learned rhetors to be judges
               of the cause, had it not been that we were hindered by reflecting upon the order of
               the holy canons, which command that ecclesi<pb n="123"/>astical cases shall be tried
               and decided by saintly bishops, and subject to penalties those who pass over these
               and turn to civil courts." And it was for this same reason that we sent the religious
               Eusebius the deacon also; for we cannot consent, after the lapse of so many days, to
               keep the saintly bishops here, when they ought to return to their own flock. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
