<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Eutychian, Governor of Apamea</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">123-25</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.44">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Eutychian, governor of Apamea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">from those during episcopacy, from the 8th book the
               190th letter.</head>
            <p> When I compare the reports that have recently come to my hearing with the words
               spoken by your magnificence when I was leaving the royal city and had reached this
               city of Antiochus, I still even now consider these untrustworthy and shrink from
               setting them down in so many words in this letter. I learn that, when one of those
               who have been deprived and stripped of the high-priestly office was celebrating (as
               he thinks) the unhallowed memory of martyrs and the initiatory festival and
               dedication of a certain house, you also went there and took part in a feast that thus
               contends against God. In order that you may not think that it is from a quarrelsome
               disposition that we have been led to use such hard words, or rather in order that you
               may know that what I have written <pb n="124"/> falls short of the real abomination,
               I will immediately quote to you the actual canon and law of the Spirit, and you will
               know clearly that for a man who is in servitude to the pious king and is the ruler of
               a people to do anything of the kind without consideration is not a thing free from
               danger. The canon or law that has been mentioned is as follows:—"If any bishop,
               after. he has been deprived by a synod, or a presbyter or deacon by his bishop, shall
               presume to perform any part of the ministry, be he a bishop according to the
               previously existing custom, or a presbyter or deacon, no hope of restoration even in
               another synod shall thenceforward be permitted him, nor shall he be permitted an
               opportunity of defence: but those also who communicate with him shall all be expelled
               from the church, and especially if they have presumed to communicate with the
               aforesaid persons after they have learned the verdict that has been put forth against
               them." Do you think even after reading this law that it is about small or
               contemptible matters that we are speaking; or that we do so out of concern for your
               soul and for your reputation? You must therefore abandon this discreditable state of
               mind, if indeed it really is a state of mind at all, and reflect upon the purpose of
               God and of our pious king, and of the glorious notables who are earnest upholders of
               the orthodox faith, and not set yourself in hostility to the saintly Peter bishop of
               your metropolis in any<pb n="125"/>thing, or rather not conceive any thought that is
               hostile and hateful to God, and to our triumphant, serene, Christ-loving king. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
