<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To the Clergymen of Antaradus</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">126-29</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.46">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the clergymen of Antaradus.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">from those during episcopacy, from the 8th book the
               264th, 265th letter.</head>
            <p> When I had read your devoutnesses' petitions concerning the necessity of a shepherd
               being nominated for you, in accordance with the precepts of the holy canons and the
               laws of the Spirit, and concerning the articles that belong of right to your holy
               church, but are unreasonably and unjustly detained by others, after giving due
               consideration to the whole matter I thought it right to refer the whole case to our
               serene Christ-loving king and his pious ears. For it is from him after God that we
               receive useful and satisfactory assistance in difficult affairs. Wherefore it is your
               duty at once to insert in a <foreign>psephisma</foreign> three men well-known for
               virtue and capable of being entrusted with a rational leadership of this kind, in
               order that we may choose the man who stands highest in these respects, and confer <pb
                  n="127"/> ordination upon him; or rather present him for the inspiration of the
               Spirit: for the choice and judgment and bestowal in such matters are from above:
               since in fact "every good bestowal and every perfect gift is from above, coming down
               from the Father of lights," as the sacred scripture somewhere says. Let this be both
               considered and performed in this way, and may it be brought to a good end by God!
               Whereas the devout deacon Stephen has just presented petitions to me and informed me
               that Leontius, who has lived an unhallowed life, but was improperly admitted to
               ordination as deacon, as if setting himself to act in accordance with his former
               life, contracted a second marriage after ordination, and after this was by the
               bishop's judgment struck out of the sacred tablets, and as an indulgence was allowed
               to minister again, but now wishes to retain deacon's rank and claims to be made head
               over the others, though he ought not to be ranked even among those that are under a
               head, how can we neglect the intimation that has been given us, and close our ears to
               such audacious deeds on his part? Even if it is the case that, while your holy church
               was without anyone to act as shepherd, the man who then held the post of archdeacon
               by a presumptuous action enrolled him in the order of deacons, this action is already
               in every way invalid. This man ought therefore to stand entirely outside the
               ministry, and to feel the sins that he has committed, and to congratulate himself
               that he does not gain <pb n="128"/> experience of some canonical punishment; not go
               on further to desire the headship that it is no way proper for him to hold. But the
               first position in the order of religious deacons shall be held by those who are
               summoned from among the members of the order. For the present this is the conclusion
               at which we have arrived: but, if Leontius thinks that he has any right founded upon
               the canons that may help him, let him inform the apostolic see of this; and the fact
               of the accusation will not do him any harm whatever, if he have truth on his side. If
               he was conscious of guilt even on one count only of those that were related to us, he
               ought, he ought indeed to have restricted himself to a modest and humble demeanour,
               and thought of Him who said by Jeremiah the prophet, "'Hear these things, foolish
               people and without understanding, which have eyes and see not, and have ears and hear
               not! or will ye not fear me,' saith the Lord, 'and will ye not tremble at my face,
               which have placed the sand as a bound for the sea, an everlasting decree, and it
               shall not pass it?'" However for our part we feared for his sake owing to the
               terrible nature of the reports, and were unable to remain silent in such
               circumstances. And, since the church ministry "requires blamelessness," we decided
               that he should cease to exercise this, in order that we might not seem even to
               ourselves by acquiescing in the sins that he committed and the deeds that he thought
               good to do, to be by our silence actually <pb n="129"/> approving the evil thing, and
               apply to ourselves the words spoken by God to the same prophet, "A wonder and a
               horror has happened upon the earth; the prophets prophesy falsehood, and the priests
               clapped their hands." But, since we are always desirous of arriving at the truth, and
               we know that the magnificent Christ-loving count John is very desirous of this, we
               have written to his magnificence to examine into the true state of the case, and
               notify our meanness of it. For in everything let truth and justice be respected;
               while at the same time the honour of the holy church is preserved, and the ministry
               has the reverence assigned to it which is its by right, especially by those to whom
               this ministry has been committed, through the benignance and ineffable grace of God. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
