<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Philoxenus Bishop of Hierapolis</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">130-32</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.48">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Philoxenus bishop of Hierapolis.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 10th book the
               295th letter.</head>
            <p> Hearing the divine writings which say, "Salvation cometh by much counsel," I wish
               yet now again to ask your sanctity even about a matter upon which we have often
               already counselled and deliberated. You <pb n="131"/> know that those who received
               ordination for payment and bought for themselves from Flavian the trafficker in all
               divine things the grace of the Spirit that is not to be bought, alleging ignorance of
               the strictness of the holy canons, begged you and the other bishops of the other
               resplendent metropolitan cities that they might obtain forgiveness on the ground of
               ignorance of the sin. And, though the same said men further brought us letters
               written in lenient terms from one and another set of persons, even so they did not
               obtain release from the interdicts. And some of them even went up to the royal city,
               and showed letters of this kind to those who conduct our
               <foreign>apokriseis</foreign> and to all those who are in power and deign to love
               our meanness, and caused them all, though certainly in a friendly manner, to charge
               me with cruelty. For all being moved to pity for them granted them forgiveness. And,
               when they returned thence, they did not desist from this course of action, since we
               even after this would not incline our ear to their entreaty and lamentation: but they
               went to the holy cloisters of the orthodox and moved the chiefs or rulers of the
               solitary and sacred orders to compassion. And they also, after weeping for the fall
               of certain persons, in an exactly similar manner and much more earnestly than the
               others, addressed supplications to us in writing with the object of procuring for
               them liberation from their evil plight. Being in some sort harassed and troubled by
               all the facts stated, I have taken the course of asking your holiness by this letter
               whether <pb n="132"/> these men ought to receive forgiveness at the feast of the
               Epiphany or if they ought not, let your love of God put yourself to a little trouble,
               and after the feast mentioned repair to this great Christ-loving city of Antiochus,
               and assist in a course of lenient mildness towards men who have sinned from
               ignorance, a course perhaps not wholly inconsistent with canonical strictness: for
               they say that the gift was concealed under the name of a present by those
               gain-hunters, and it deceived them. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
