<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To John and John Presbyters and
               Archimandrites and the Rest</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">132-40</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.49">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John and John presbyters and
               archimandrites and the rest.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 1st book the 55th,
               53rd letter.</head>
            <p> I am glad and rejoice greatly whenever I write an epistle to your holinesses, and,
               if one may so say, fancy myself speaking to you as if you were close by me.
               <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> For do not think of me that my
               concern for the church of the Alexandrines is different from my concern for that of
               the Antiochenes; I shall not be lying even though I say it is much greater. In fact
               both the party of the learned Hippocrates, to whom I referred a short time ago, and a
               very large number of other well-known and distinguished men, who have always
               concerned themselves about their own salvation and about the strict observance of the
               orthodox faith, and those who followed these, through the efforts and endeavours <pb
                  n="133"/> (to speak with God's permission) of my wretched miserable self joined
               the catholic and orthodox church in Egypt; men who as you know for a long time had
               not communicated but were satisfied by the minutes of the records? drawn up by the
               blessed Dioscorus who a short time ago departed to God, of which you no doubt have an
               <foreign>ison</foreign> or copy, and are not ignorant of the purport of the things
               contained in them: since, after the sacred old man had received the epistle written
               by my meanness, in answer to his synodical letter, with hands and feet, as the saying
               goes, and as far as was possible he complied with my advice and satisfied those who
               were separated; who often wrote to me in their letters (although it is in folly that
               I speak), "It is because we have confidence in your reputation that we have
               communicated." How then can neglect such men? or how can it be said that I must not
               both "in season and out of season" as the divine Apostle says search even into small
               matters, and cut away every cause of stumbling, and remove the stones and cast them
               out [of] the way that leads [...] or to satisfy so-and-so and so-and-so individually,
               so that all these and men like them were scandalized in that a door for vain speaking
               was being opened to the contentious. For neither are this time and that alike, nor
               yet can you on your part avoid doing everything in the capacity of my
               representatives. For, what you do, <pb n="134"/> that men will justly reckon to me;
               for all, both brothers and strangers, both friends and enemies, know clearly that I
               and you are one, as in fact we are. Accordingly, if any man owing to his imperfect
               intelligence needs to be directed by pilotage, being carried about like some ship by
               troubled thoughts, let him be so directed and controlled as not to rouse any storm or
               tempest against the great ships. Let not your sanctities think that this is the first
               time that I have been moved to this action. Even while I was living in Antiochus'
               city, I used to hear it said of the presbyter father Theodore of saintly memory that,
               when many came to Egypt and asked him whether they ought to communicate, he would
               answer and say plainly to them, "If you have been satisfied, communicate": and other
               things that are like this and resemble it, And I endured because it was a time of
               endurance, and because none of the bishops in the East heard anything of the kind,
               but the reports were confined to yourselves, and did no great harm. For a man who is
               doing anything in accordance with God's purpose never halts and hesitates in his
               action: but he stands firm and steadfast, and increases what he has begun; like the
               gift of the talents in the gospels. <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add>
               As to the devout and beloved brother Epimachus, you know how distinct the apostolic
               statute is through which I also was prevented from laying my hands upon this man,
               when he came to Antiochus' city, in order that he might conduct my
               <foreign>apokriseis</foreign> in the royal among cities, in conjunction <pb
                  n="135"/> with the presbyter Peter of blessed memory, my brother. And, being
               afraid of the strictness of the canon, I restrained my desire: and this though I
               loved the man, I mean the devout Epimachus, not out of human favour, but on account
               of his devout and modest conduct in the monastic. life, and his venerable age and
               old-fashioned mind. For I saw that the canon of the church everywhere "requires
               blamelessness"; and at the same time also I was in the habit of proclaiming to
               everyone in Antiochus' city, "No man who has been twice married or labours under any
               disqualification similar [to this] can [receive] ordination from me." [...] Therefore
               take the course of which our Lord shall satisfy you." Accordingly it would not have
               been right for us, when the thing has been made public, to advance him now to
               ordination, and let him be a blot in our ministry, as the very wise Paul says, us who
               endeavour with God's help to do everything as far as we can without cause for blame.
               For we cannot in fact say that the man by his monastic habit and the long life that
               he has passed in this is able to mitigate the strictness of the canon, seeing that it
               nowhere in actual words makes any such further provision about the twice-married, and
               seeing that "what is rare is not a law of the church," as the Theologian Gregory
               somewhere says. The ninth canon of the three hundred and <pb n="136"/> eighteen holy
               fathers also plainly says that presbyters who have been put forward without
               examination shall be set aside, even though it is after ordination that their sin
               which violates the canon is confessed. The twice-married have also a certain definite
               time provided in the same canons, during which they are excluded from communion,"
               because these men ought to devote themselves to fastings and prayers. Hence it is
               very plain that devout conduct after the second marriage is of assistance to them
               only in the way of penitence, and does not besides this also assist them in.
               obtaining admission to the clergy. We know also the letter written by the saintly
               archbishop and martyr Dioscorus concerning Irenaeus the twice-married, and the order
               of Theodosius of truly pious and God-loving memory concerning this man. These things
               then being so, it rests with you and with those who disputed with you to consider
               whether one can extend the application of the fifty-third canon and compel it to
               cover the case of a man who, having contracted a second marriage, is ordained without
               examination, and to come to an agreement with one another on this point and settle
               your dispute and doubt. The canon itself is as follows: "If a presbyter be promoted
               after having previously sinned with his body, and confess that he sinned before
               ordination, he shall not offer: but he shall retain the rest of his functions on
               account of his zeal in other respects, For in the case of other sins <pb n="137"/>
               many have said that they are remitted by the mere fact of the laying on of hands.
               But, if he do not himself confess, and it is not possible for him to be manifestly
               convicted, the discretion shall rest with himself." Consider therefore whether the
               devout Epimachus also ought to communicate in the prayers and other things only. But
               even this I say as an indulgence, not as a command. For the principles laid down by
               the canon do not refer to an open and notorious second marriage, but to other bodily
               sins that are secret. But for your part, since it is upon you that the burden of
               judgment is laid, choose the course that seems to you good: my feebleness cannot
               write about this: in fact for my part whatever have given if I have given anything I
               have given for your sakes as the representative of Christ. However it is with much
               sorrow and sighing that I have written this (I speak with God as witness), seeing
               that even to the devout Epimachus himself that which is thought an honour is being
               turned into a shame, and I too am being driven by the divine precepts to break out
               into grievous and bitter words. For what we are to say upon the point in question is
               laid down for us as a law by others. There is another thing that, as upon brief
               consideration appears to my meanness, would have been just and proper, I mean if you
               had asked me first and taken my advice, especially since it is now a kind of
               beginning of our state of banishment. You are not unaware that in <pb n="138"/> the
               case of the man of holy memory also, I mean Peter the bishop, even when he was not
               ordaining anyone, those who were ordaining took his advice. Timothy too, who bravely
               endured in the contests of piety, when he was at a distance and was living somewhere
               far away beyond the boundaries, used to regulate all these things by epistle, and
               they were carried into effect. However you may allege in defence that I was in hiding
               and that you did not even know where I am, and that you were in a hurry to satisfy
               your need, which it would not have been certainly possible to do when you wanted.
               Another matter, I confess, was very displeasing to me, I mean the fact that certain
               other men also who rejoice in two disciples only, and those boys, have presented
               those who are living with them for ordination, so that they are led astray from the
               very fact of living with them. Fora boy who is admitted to an honour which passes his
               measure exposes himself to shame, while he has for the time brought no small blame on
               the community. Your remark that the God-loving Isidore the bishop ought not on
               account of the persecution to have again laid his hand on those who were ordained
               deacons by me is lukewarm and cold: for these regulations apply to deacons enrolled
               in the churches: and to monasteries round about that parish. But to extend this to
               those who are in a province beyond the boundaries and are united with us in respect
               of the right faith it is not <pb n="139"/> a fitting season. In the same fashion also
               the practice of devout women living in their houses being ordained deaconesses is
               very usual and is diffused, if may so say, over the whole world. Again the fact that
               in previous times Palestine also was subject to the apostolic see of the city of the
               Antiochenes is in no doubt. However I and the God-loving bishop Isidore make up one
               person, and I myself say that his love of God performed the ordination on my behalf;
               therefore let all question and dispute cease. The quality of the person who ordained
               causes no detriment whatever, such that the ordination that has been performed should
               be thought to be uncanonical. But you, who are wise in the Lord, ought not to have
               dropped the religious presbyter Victor out of your consideration: seeing that he
               would often introduce some useful action before the event itself, or that after
               consenting to what you did he was thenceforward ashamed to go against his own
               consent; and seeing that many find it hard to endure neglect. But that he was your
               friend not only I but everyone is aware. I know, I know clearly that it was with
               judgment that you put forward your devout brothers: but the reason that you yielded
               to certain men who were putting forward boys was, as it seems, that you might not
               excite disturbance against you. These things I have written to you by <pb n="140"/>
               way of admonition, and privately. For indeed I know how to admonish such men as you,
               but to find fault with those who are so exalted in virtue I have not learned, far
               less to. rebuke them, as you write. I know my measure, even though the fact of the
               office and the spiritual honour that has been given me through the benignance of God
               tends to exaltation, a thing that to the unintelligent and foolish gives occasion for
               vanity and pride, but in those who do not deceive themselves and know that they are
               sinners implants endurance in contests and fear of the judgment, in which we shall
               give account even for honours that are so high, when the Judge shall give judgment,
               as is threatened in the prophets, against those that are "clothed in other men's
               apparel." </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
