<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Peter</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">34-38</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.5">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Peter, bishop of Apamea.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the 5th
               letter.</head>
            <p> When the letters of your love of God came before me, not that only which was written
               to me, but that also which was written to the religious presbyter Thomas, I thought
               it right not to judge words which were put forward, as you yourself also say, under a
               feeling of wrath and anger, but only to declare my mind as if God himself were
               listening, and to say to Him like Jeremiah, "The things which came forth from my lips
               are before Thy face." In the first place you bring a charge against us, which is not
               known to the canons, nor to the church laws or precepts. For what law of the
               God-inspired scripture, or precept of the holy fathers, encloses and confines the
               laity in cities and in countries, and prevents these from going to receive ordination
               from anyone willing to give it? And how is it that this new charge, which has
               hitherto escaped the notice of many, has found such a strict prosecutor in you alone?
               It <pb n="35"/> is time for the God-loving bishop Julian of the city of the Emesenes
               also to make the same accusation against us in the case of the devout deacon
               Irenaeus, because he registers his fathers' house at Emesa. The saintly Dionysius
               also, who has reached extreme old age, and is crowned with honourable white hairs,
               who is venerable for the length of his life, will perhaps more justly put forth a
               complaint against us, in the case of the religious deacon Anatolius. For in fact he
               too was previously thought to be a citizen of the city of the Tarsians. And I am sure
               that the purpose which we had as to the magnificent count Oecumenius is also not
               unknown to you. Have I therefore up to this day been interfering with all these
               shepherds of metropolitan sees and causing them annoyance, and been infected with
               such greed, and been coveting other men's property without it being known? or is it
               rather, as the truth is, because I have given no handle for a lawful charge against
               me, nor caused annoyance to anyone soever? As to the devout Leontius, it was not out
               of need as you think that we raised him to the honour of the presbyters' seat, but
               because we wished to honour the man. And this is not the first time (I speak with God
               himself as witness), but long before this was in my mind, even before your love of
               God was raised to the high-priesthood. We had in fact made the acquaintance of the
               man and he was known to us by letters, even while we were practising the philosophic
               life in Palestine. However, I did not even know that the said <pb n="36"/> Leontius
               himself is among those that are in such high esteem with you. Neither had you ever
               bestowed upon him such laudatory expressions as you now do in your letter, nor had we
               ever learned that the stability of the holy church of the Apamenes was shaken by him.
               However, if the man is of such a character, and is among your friends and counsellors
               as you say, even one letter from your love of God is enough to win him over: and if
               he desires to live in the city of the Apamenes we will in no way prevent him, nor
               will we detain his devoutness, even though it was thought that we needed him for
               something. But that we should commit the unholy and uncanonical action of driving him
               out against his will, and turn the honour into a shame, neither you nor any other
               intelligent man like you will judge to be right. If you wished to raise the man to
               the priesthood as you say, the time past would have suited you equally well for this
               purpose. I consider that the grace of ordination receives no difference in similitude
               from the fishing-net, which is thrown into the sea of the world or into worldly
               matter by the Spirit itself: and that it is one, though divided among the nets of
               many fishers; among whom are Peter and James and John and Andrew, and all who fed the
               churches after them. All did not catch the same persons, but one caught one, and
               another another: but the grace of the fisher was one, because the faith also is one,
               and the church under the whole heaven of those who hold the same things is one. That
               therefore which <pb n="37"/> was done in the case of the devout Leontius is the
               action of the Holy Spirit, not of us. For it "bloweth where it listeth," as is said
               by our God and Saviour. If therefore you also catch one of the Antiochenes in your
               net, we shall find no fault at all with your fishing, but we shall praise the Holy
               Spirit which distributes to each man individually its own grace, and does everything
               in an ineffable manner and as it lists. Indeed in this frame of mind we pray that
               John also, the eloquent scholastic, the son of Matronian of illustrious memory, and
               the eloquent and Christ-loving scholastic Sergius may be enrolled in the order of
               those who minister to the Lord, and that they may adorn the church and be adorned by
               it and praise Christ. This I remember to have told your love of God also many times.
               And it was and is in my mind to raise the eloquent scholastics Peter and Maximin also
               to the priestly order; and I do not know through what reasons, known as they are to
               the wisdom that passes understanding, I have not yet been able to carry out what I
               intended. But for this also I am waiting for sanction from above, and divine
               inspiration. However I shall not dispute whether they are to be drawn in by my hand
               or yours: but so far am I from being jealous of you in respect of the fishing, that I
               will even help you and catch hold of the net with you above. Every matter whatever
               that is not contrary to the canons surely urges us to give help and to act <pb n="38"
               /> in unison with one another. How is it anything but shameful that, while those who
               hunt birds reckon the air common property, and fishers, as I have said, the sea, we
               should dispute about things that lie not in our power but in God's? However, not to
               use many words and interfere with the moderate length of the letter (I think that
               even what has been written has gone beyond a moderate length), if the devout Leontius
               acquiesce in your wish as you Say, we will consent, and will not retain him against
               his will: and this as a concession to you, and in order to show that, in things such
               as these, it is not our endeavour to subserve to the best of our power human
               purposes, but to walk according to the divine laws only. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
