<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3098">To John and John, Presbyters and
               Archimandrites and the Rest</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">140-45</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.50">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the same John and John presbyters and
               archimandrites and the rest.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the first book the
               16th letter.</head>
            <p> If those who were enlightened in their understanding like you, and for this reason
               were properly called seers, were a cause of peace to others also by giving the inner
               man peace from warring passions, and heard from those who approached them the words,
               "Thy coming, seer, is peace," what wonder if you also by the long-suffering and
               humility implanted <pb n="141"/> in you have brought about a serene and peaceful
               state of affairs in place of the disturbance which had arisen? Wherefore we must also
               for everything praise and laud our God and Saviour Jesus Christ, our peace and
               tranquillity; who said to His disciples, "My peace I give unto you, my peace I leave
               unto you," and ordered them, to whomsoever they went, to say, "Peace to this house."
               Pray therefore that we may be men worthy of this peace, in order that it may also
               abide with us and never leave us, now that we have once received it, as in fact it
               wishes, provided of course that we do not do anything contrary to it. As to the
               religious Epimachus, because you the holy old man have, as you write, stretched the
               sinews of your mind and had recourse to the harshness of the strict execution of the
               canons owing to the admonitions that we gave, ought we also to extend this matter
               further with them, and ourselves also to scratch (?) in a more violent manner that
               which has once been done, even though in an inconsiderate manner, and make it come to
               an ulcer and end by being incurable? By no means. But on the contrary, we ought to
               devise some remedy and carry it out, by some kind of healing friction and humane
               refreshment. It does not seem that we are running counter to the intention of the
               canons in allowing him to conduct the prayers only and so forth, but not to offer the
               sacred sacrifice, <pb n="142"/> Accordingly let him have both the title and the
               privileges of a presbyter, on account of his long continuance in the monastic life,
               and on account of the fact that he thereby as far as possible purified his previous
               life, and on account of the man's attested devoutness, and because neither did he
               himself seek to be raised to this position, but was raised against his will and
               submitted to the decision and nomination of others. In fact even on the former
               occasion I did not write to you as a lawgiver, but rather as performing a service.
               And I did not do this of my own accord, but because some great "necessity is laid
               upon me," as the Apostle says, and because "woe is unto me if I do not" serve
               necessity and so "preach the gospel." Indeed, although the burden is heavy, yet still
               "I am entrusted with a stewardship," and, bowed down though I am, I must execute this
               with all fear and trembling. Still it would have been unjust that, because you "fear
               everything through devoutness," as it is written, while I submit to the necessity of
               the laws, the man who came to ordination against his will as we have said should be
               injured and not receive refreshment. Whence under compulsion and as a consequence we
               have, as is possible, been brought to these second thoughts, seeing that we too are
               bowed down by the weight of many sins, and stand in need, if any man else besides, of
               the clemency of God. But may you, sacred man, be <pb n="143"/> preserved for us in
               health and youthful vigour, being more powerfully strengthened with spiritual sinews,
               and correcting our paralysis, and putting forth wings and being renewed like the
               eagles, and singing with the prophet David and saying, "And I will go in unto the
               altar of God, unto God that reneweth my youth!": and there offering prayers on our
               behalf. As to the holy communion or oblation which is being sent to Alypius the poor
               child (so you often termed him in your letter) I have this much to say: that, if you
               had previously told his father also the very thing which you have often said, I mean
               that he ought not to be in doubt as to the existing state of things in the holy
               churches in Alexandria and in Egypt, since it is now (to speak with God's permission)
               free from association and communion with heretics, you would perhaps now have had the
               courage to say that the revered and sacred communion or oblation must not be sent to
               him. But, since the thing has been thus begun and has become known to the
               adversaries, what necessity is there for us to do further harm, and go on to ruin the
               boy who is about as your sanctity says to yield to his grandfather? Let the child
               therefore be refreshed with the usual refreshment from you on account of his
               believing father, and not be neglected on account of his unbelieving grandfather. For
               it is written, "The thoughts of the righteous are judgments." And henceforth for <pb
                  n="144"/> the future let us not turn aside to similar things, nor give occasion to
               those who seek occasion, nor in order to content one person disturb the whole church.
               Know well that I was loth to write that the believing Mitra ought to have sent his
               son to communicate with the church which by God's grace is clean and pure, the church
               which now looks to our banished self, and does not acquiesce in any cunning fraud.
               For, even though it had been right to send the often mentioned holy communion to the
               boy, how can it be anything but unreasonable that this boy should live with enemies,
               who reveal without shame even that which is thought to be ineffable? <add><emph>And
                  after other things.</emph></add> As to those who like the magnificent
               Anastasius are zealous for piety, and all who are settled in the land of the
               Philistines, who is there who is so wrathful and alien to the divine laws as to say
               that the communion or oblation ought not to be given them when they ask, to any
               extent that they wish and without stint? Our whole argument with you related to those
               who are residing in Alexandria and show doubts that are superfluous and intolerable
               because they inflicted injury on many. Do not therefore omit to give at the due time
               and to those who require it the indestructible grace, which as it is written was
               given for nothing, and is being asked <choice>
                  <sic>for for</sic>
                  <corr>for</corr>
               </choice> nothing. You know, even if we do not write it, how great punishment and
               reproof from God is caused by <pb n="145"/> neglect to give readily and without any
               hesitation. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
