<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Philip the Presbyter</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">145-48</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.51">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Philip the presbyter.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 40th
               letter.</head>
            <p> I have read the words written by your religiousness, not without sorrow, but with
               sympathy: not like a stranger but like a brother: not as one who is above law, but as
               one who is subject to law. Wherefore I am writing to you that you may rejoice, not
               that you may be distressed: that you may know yourself, not that you may despair. Do
               not think that what you have written needs a refutation of the same length. You
               perhaps made your letter so long from a desire to incline the reader to pity and draw
               attention to your purpose: but I listen to the sacred writings rather than to you:
               and in submission to the precise declaration of the Spirit I quote to you the
               ordinance of Koheleth which ordains that "there is a time for everything," and with
               the other things says this also, "A time to weep and a time to laugh, a time to mourn
               and a time to dance." At the proper time, as you say, you confessed the sins of your
               youth to the common and holy fathers. But to me you made the confession at an
               improper time and after the fitting season; for I acquiesce in your written statement
               in order that you <pb n="146"/> may know that, as the sacred text somewhere says, it
               is right to obey God under all circumstances. But perhaps you will say that even now
               you have not missed the proper time, seeing that the canons admit the confession of
               great sins even after ordination, and exclude those who confess them from the sacred
               ministry, and allow them to share only the privileges and the name of the priesthood.
               Know that I too am not unaware of this statute. But what can the effect upon me be
               when the Apostle cries, "The covenant which was before confirmed by God the law which
               was afterwards does not annul?" I describe as the covenant of God the testimony given
               by our common teacher and father John, the great man of God, when he presented you
               for ordination, and I heartily confirm it. It seems to me therefore great presumption
               for me to annul the testimony of a father of this character and such as he, or to add
               anything to this and give orders that go beyond it. For we all know that that man was
               not a doer of his own will, nor presumptuous in actions, but one who, if any other
               man besides, makes the blessing his own which is promised to those who "fear
               everything through devoutness." Wherefore also I assuredly know that after the
               confession which you made of your sins, unless he had received confirmation by
               inspiration from above, he would not have advanced you to this rank. Whenever
               therefore any of the lapses that you committed in youth troubles your memory, recall
               <pb n="147"/> your thoughts to him who gave you the testimony and forget yourself,
               and be "turned into another man," and boldly perform the duties proper to the sacred
               ministry: and do not show yourself excessive in devoutness and trust yourself to the
               pronouncements of the thoughts, lest you hear the sacred scripture reproving you and
               saying, "Be not righteous overmuch, neither make thyself over wise lest thou be
               astonied." Whereas you are here, there, and everywhere representing second marriage
               as a thing that is less serious than the greatest sins and yet is excluded from
               priestly functions, know that such a conception falls outside the range of spiritual
               interpretation. A second marriage was granted by way of indulgence, as a support of
               weakness: and he who has resorted to this of his own will and by deliberate judgment
               has enrolled himself among those that are weak and have been granted an indulgence
               and are in the second order, and are not raised to the first sacred rank. It is
               therefore manifest presumption, and contempt of the sacred laws, for a man to enrol
               himself among those that are weak and objects of indulgence, and to do this with the
               law's aid and openly, and then strive to rise to the first sacred rank, which is
               composed of those who are sound. But a man who-has sinned in the times of his youth
               has not fallen under sin because he judged it lawful to sin, but has committed an
               involuntary lapse, insomuch that he may be purified by penitence. I do not say this
               in <pb n="148"/> order to show a second marriage to be a sin (far be it!); it is
               rather a support for weakness, that does not place those who are married outside the
               company of those who are saved, but assigns them a low rank. Incline your ear
               therefore to the divine law, and when it bids you perform priestly functions say the
               words that are written, "Speak, Lord, for thy bondsman heareth." However, if for the
               present you shrink from offering the perfect sacrifice, I will allow you to abstain
               for a time, but not to go so far as to bind yourself under such an inhibition. But in
               all other functions you shall not be restrained in any way whatever. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
