<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3107">To John and John the Presbyters and Archimandrites</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">148-51</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.52">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John and John the presbyters and the
               rest.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 42nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> I sent an answer at once to the earlier letter which reached me from your sanctity:
               and, because no ship was at hand, the letter was delayed several days: but I expect
               that you have by this time received it. As to the epistle that has just been sent,
               about the slave who was sold by the Jews and the question regarding him, I have
               nothing to write. For a letter was written by me about a similar matter to a certain
               Theodore the God-loving bishop of Olba (this is a city in Isauria), and I have
               thought well to give an <foreign>ison</foreign> or <pb n="149"/> copy of it at the
               end of this letter, so that from it you may know what our own conclusion was. As to
               clergymen who come from outside, who hold the correct faith but are not united in
               communion with us, the answer is plain: <foreign>i.e.</foreign>, that we must not
               admit these men to the exercise of the ministry: but in all other respects, in order
               to promote sound and correct opinions, must hold intercourse with them as with our
               own people and extend goodwill towards them. If we do not do this, we shall, unknown
               to ourselves, be circumscribing, so to speak, the right ways of the Lord. But, if any
               man, being a clergyman, wishes to hold entirely aloof from communion with those to
               whom he is subject, let him go to the God-loving archbishop of the city of the
               Alexandrines or to the banished bishops, and the privileges of communion will be
               properly conceded to him by them. For your love of God it is a sufficient answer to
               these men to say that without the bishops you can do nothing, and this does not lie
               in your authority. By this plan you will be preserved from irregularity, and they
               from finding any occasion of stumbling or of offence. As to those in Isauria and in
               First Cilicia, an epistle that has just been sent to us is very gloomy: and, not to
               say anything harsh, it accuses those of First Cilicia of remissness, and it announces
               a grievous persecution and expulsion of the orthodox in Isauria, as well of the
               devout monks, as of the clergymen and of those who are among the believing people,
               not to speak of what has happened in consequence, that <pb n="150"/> all have
               abandoned communion with Stephen the disturber, the present prelate, and are not
               unaware of his treachery and falseness and the evil habits ingrained in him. The
               wretched man has even presumed to send some of the clergymen who have been corrupted
               by him here also to the saintly Isaurian bishops in banishment, as if summoning them
               to him, and heaping vanities upon vanities, as is written, and "beating the air" in
               vain, as the Apostle says. However these impious men do not cease from making
               confusion, and from audaciously attempting to no purpose even things that are
               impossible, and from polluting the water for drinking with their feet, in order to
               give those who are not cautious turbid pollution to drink according to the prophetic
               saying. Isidore the illustrious tribune has started in peace for Pelusium, after
               promising the devout presbyter Thomas to do all things in accordance with God's
               pleasure. He had also after the conversation held here written to the devout
               presbyter Epimachus to tell his religiousness to go in the direction of Pelusium. In
               order therefore that you may not be ignorant of what has happened, this also has been
               added in this letter. Console and comfort with loving disposition the God-loving
               Isidore bishop of the city of the men of Chalcis, who is troubled with a bodily
               infirmity, or rather who is being better proved in the furnace of trials; and. reckon
               it all as a gift to me: though <pb n="151"/> I know that I am acting superfluously in
               this, since ready help and zealous attention in these matters are innate in you and
               belong to your character. For you must believe that I was much distressed when
               learned that he had been again seized with the same kind of infirmity. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
