<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3108">To the Bishops from Syria in
               Alexandria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">151-62</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.53">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the bishops from Syria in
               Alexandria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 64th
               letter.</head>
            <p> To the saintly God-loving brothers and fellow-ministers, the bishops who are under
               the apostolic see of the city of the Antiochenes, and are now settled in the great
               Christ-loving city of the Alexandrines, Cassian, Constantine, Antoninus, and the
               rest, Severus greeting in the Lord. Though I am with your love of God in the spirit,
               I should have wished to be present in the flesh also, or, while absent in the body,
               to communicate with you more constantly through this remaining source of comfort, I
               mean by means of letters, concerning the hope laid down beforehand for those who have
               believed in Christ. But, since, when men are living without fear, every time is
               convenient to them for sending letters, but, when they are under constraint or
               imprisoned, it does not lie in their power to do this, even against their will they
               check and silence the ardour of affection: but when need demands they then cut the
               fetters of constraint, and do not submit <pb n="152"/> to the ropes that fall to them
               among the strong, to speak in the words of the Psalmist, but move their tongue, and
               serve the divine law. For this reason Paul used to say that he "endured evil things
               as an evildoer even to bonds for the Gospel's sake," but that "the word of God was
               not bound." Therefore I also the mean one look to that pattern and say, and that very
               justly, "Though I flee for Christ's sake, yet His word has not fled; for it is
               present in every place where the law of the Spirit wishes to carry it." Therefore I
               salute you, and embrace you, the sharers of my flight, whose feet are beautiful, who
               do not preach, but by accepting persecution as the law requires walk aright and
               follow Him who said, "When they persecute you in this city flee to another"; or
               perhaps it is better to say that by the very fact of being persecuted you loudly
               proclaim the gospel, and by the fact of being silent speak. Therefore, since you have
               been brought to such honour, Christ who is persecuted with you is present with you
               also, and He is a chief and leader for you in purpose and in commands. Those who were
               removed to the land of Babylon, and endeavoured there also to live in accordance with
               the law, and were bereft of the sacred fane and the service, and did not even sing a
               song, because it was not lawful to do any of these things outside the tabernacle or
               outside the sanctuary, <pb n="153"/> but still set themselves to live in accordance
               with their fathers' customs and to pronounce right judgments had the Holy Spirit
               dwelling in them, insomuch that the divine Daniel being most divinely inspired from
               that source convicted those wicked elders, and those three boys not only performed a
               miracle by exulting in the furnace, the burning effect of the fire having been
               assuaged, but also sang a prophetic hymn of praise. Who is there therefore who will
               not say with greater justice that the Holy Spirit is dwelling among you, even when
               you are settled by the evangelic throne of the holy Mark, and are dwelling in a very
               loyal city, one whose special possession and high honour in addition to its other
               excellences is correctness and distinction in the faith, and as a chief and leader
               and counsellor and good teacher of everything that ought to be done and counselled
               you have the saintly Timothy the archbishop of this city, a man who not only fills
               the place of my meanness, but is even able to shelter me owing to his high position?
               Hence also the case of the religious Paul, formerly bishop of Olba in Isauria, has
               been very well treated by you and brought to a very proper conclusion: and this
               resolution that you have adopted is not at variance with the sacred ecclesiastical
               ordinances. Fora time of persecution more particularly invites us to be more than
               ordinarily mild, and to gather together the scattered limbs of the church, and to
               block the exits of unreasonable schisms. Secondly, if one understand the
               <foreign>diataxeis</foreign> or canonical commands also not accord<pb n="154"/>ing
               to the letter after the manner of a Jew, but according to the spirit and intention of
               the church law, one will find that they desire that a bishop who has been unanimously
               deprived by the synod in the province shall in those cases only be denied restoration
               in another synod when the synod that has pronounced his deposition remains in the
               same mind. For the eighty-fourth canon says as follows: "If anyone has been
               excommunicated by his own bishop, he shall not be received by others unless he has
               first been received by his bishop himself, or a synod has been held and he has
               presented himself, and made a defence, and has persuaded the synod and received
               another verdict. And the same rule applies also to laymen and presbyters and deacons
               and all that are included in the canon." The ninetieth canon also says as follows:
               "If any presbyter or deacon shall be deprived by his bishop, or a bishop also by a
               synod, and shall dare to trouble the king's ears, and, when he should betake himself
               to a greater synod of bishops and offer the pleas which he thinks he has to a larger
               number of bishops, and accept examination and judgment from them, shall treat these
               with contempt and trouble the king, these men shall not receive any forgiveness, nor
               shall an opportunity of defence be allowed them, nor shall they expect any hope of
               future restoration." It is therefore manifest from this too that it is possible for a
               man who has <pb n="155"/> been deprived by a smaller synod to be received in a
               greater one if the charges and complaints against him are examined and investigated
               afresh. It is in a sense similar to this that the eighty-second canon also is to be
               understood, which says: [Here follows the citation given at p. 124]. For the
               substance of these three canons is this: that, when a man has been deprived by a
               small synod; it is possible for him to discuss the causes of his deprivation before a
               greater synod and obtain restoration, if the great synod decide to absolve this man.
               But, if he shall dare after his deprivation to perform any priestly function, even
               access to a greater synod shall be refused him, if those who have once effected his
               deprivation continue to maintain the same judgment of deprivation. For the whole
               purpose of the canons is directed to this; that the verdicts! of those who have duly
               decided shall not be annulled, so long as they continue to maintain their verdict
               which they have pronounced. But, if these men (I mean those who deprived the man)
               with the same unanimity recede from the unfavourable verdict, and betake themselves
               to another which absolves him, how can anyone doubt that the forgiveness is certainly
               warranted by law, especially if another synod greater than it also confirms this? If
               therefore the saintly bishops in Isauria who effected the deprivation of Paul and his
               companions continued to maintain the same ver<pb n="156"/>dict of deprivation, it is
               absolutely necessary that the severity of these canons shall prevail, and that the
               punishment which was inflicted upon them shall be in no point annulled by the
               authority of a greater synod. But, if they also all alike consented to absolve those
               who were condemned, and Solon also of saintly memory, the bishop of their metropolis,
               acquiesced in this decision, we for our part will not show ourselves harsh searchers
               of the canons, which in no way prevented those who have deprived a man from coming to
               a more lenient state of mind, but laid down a law and issued a command regarding
               another synod, saying that it has no right to lay additional commands, to speak in
               the words of the Apostle, upon the bishops who effected the deprivation, and
               tyrannically to annul the judgment given by these. We find that the holy fathers for
               the benefit of the churches often receded and granted an indulgence even after
               sentence of deprivation had been passed by a catholic and oecumenical synod, for the
               sake of the general benefit and peace of the churches themselves. For instance in the
               holy synod at Ephesus Helladius of Tarsus and Eutherius of Tyana, and Dorotheus and
               Himerius were deprived together with Nestorius, on the ground that they were infected
               with opinions akin in impiety, and were afflicted with the same madness as he to a
               greater extent than the others. And yet afterwards, when the bishops of <pb n="157"/>
               the East had abandoned the unreasonable schism and submitted to the resolutions of
               the holy oecumenical synod which assembled in the city of the Ephesians, upon Paul
               bishop of the city of the Emesenes coming to the city of the Alexandrines and on
               their behalf asking Cyril the chief champion of orthodoxy, a man who in apostolic
               contests endured dangers even to death, that they might remain in their sees in the
               position which they actually held he waived the deprivation of the said wicked men,
               insisting only on this point which was more particularly necessary, I mean that the
               deprivation of Nestorius should be confirmed by all of them together and in writing,
               and that they should confess that the holy Virgin is the God-bearer and such
               conditions as follow upon these. This he stated in the letter to Eusebius the
               presbyter, in which he wrote as follows: "I have read the letter from your
               devoutness: and I have found you to be distressed by the supposition that the peace
               of the churches has been completed upon an unreasonable basis; but I imagined that it
               was by love that your gentleness was moved. However it is probable that you have no
               accurate knowledge of the points settled. For. certain persons are, I learn,
               circulating letters purporting to have been written to me by the devout and religious
               bishop John. But it is probable that either they are forgeries or they contain
               additions made to please those who hold the opinions of Nestorius. For, in accordance
               with the resolution of the holy synod in the metropolis of the Ephesians, I did <pb
                  n="158"/> not give him communion until he had anathematized in writing the
               doctrines of Nestorius, and confessed that he held him to be under deprivation, and
               assented to the ordination of the devout God-loving bishop Maximian. But when the
               religious Paul bishop of the city of the Emesenes exerted himself vigorously on
               behalf of those who had been deprived, Helladius mean and Eutherius and Dorotheus and
               Himerius, and begged that, when the peace of the churches was established, their case
               also might receive a <foreign>typos</foreign> or determination, I used these words:
               'I do not take any account of those who have been deprived: but they must remain in
               the position in which they in fact are now.' But the insult which they levelled
               against me I have forgiven. For it was not: indeed fitting that for this reason and
               no other the churches should fall into a state of schism and division, when the more
               necessary point was brought to a conclusion, I mean the requirement that the
               doctrines of Nestorius should be anathematized and his deprivation acknowledged by
               those who would not do this before, and they also confessed in writing that the holy
               Virgin is the God-bearer." This generous forgiveness he bestowed, for the sake of the
               peace and union of the holy churches, upon men who, as the succeeding time showed,
               were incurable. And yet he endured for the sake of an object that was better and of
               higher advantage, I mean for the sake of the unification and binding together of <pb
                  n="159"/> the more important limbs. For in the same letter he added these words
               also: "For, even though Helladius in Tarsus and certain others do not think rightly,
               this has nothing to do with those who wish to think what is right. For let two or
               three go if they wish, so long as the churches everywhere hold one-and the same
               faith." How then are we for our part not bound to regard the mind of those who fed
               and governed the churches of God with such understanding, and to conclude that the
               course sanctioned by you in the instance of the religious Paul: must also be followed
               in that of the devout bishop Elpidius, particularly since Paul as I have learned
               during the time of his deprivation presumed so far as to attempt the performance of
               high-priestly acts or services, but Elpidius, they say, did nothing whatever of the
               kind. I forbear to mention also the celebrated case of the holy John who was bishop
               of Constantinople. Since you read church histories, you know that he incurred
               deprivation; but, because of his reputation for right teaching and in order that
               those in the royal city who were in separation on account of the mention of his name
               might be reconciled to the body of the church, the holy Cyril waived the point, being
               apostolically minded in this matter also, and not seeking his own but that which
               belongs to Christ Jesus, and setting the benefit of ecclesiastical union and
               reconciliation against all subtle words and strict procedure, and that though in
               letters he often <pb n="160"/> contended for canonical strictness. Therefore I bestow
               all praise upon the whole of your God-loving synod, seeing it both examined the
               demands of strictness, and at the same also considered the suggestions of a
               benevolent mind. In fact both those who desired strict procedure did so because they
               took account of preserving an appearance worthy of confidence and suited to the
               church, and equally also those who inclined to mild measures were not of this opinion
               because they had anything else at heart than to bring about a bond of peace and to
               gather together those who were dispersed. However in such cases as these that plan
               must be followed which gathers together the limbs of the church and has clemency as a
               superfluous advocate, and the example of the fathers who were thus minded in similar
               cases, and thus provided for what lay before them. Do not therefore think to
               yourselves that you did anything unreasonable in discussing this matter with one
               another (it is not right or proper for us to say that you were divided). Did not this
               happen among the apostles also? The book of the Acts relates that "certain men had
               come down from Judea and were teaching the brethren, saying, 'Unless ye are
               circumcised after the custom of Moses, ye cannot have life': and, as Paul and
               Barnabas had no small dissension and dispute with them," the disputation passed to
               other churches also, until Peter the chief of the apostles and James, who was termed
               brother of our Lord, but had <pb n="161"/> received the first episcopal office in
               Jerusalem, were inspired from above, and brought forward the prophetic words, and so
               put an end to the dispute that had been raised: and they extended their resolution to
               the other churches also, so that all members. of all of them might say the same and
               think the same. I forbear to say that there was a quarrel not only about doctrines
               but also about a person between Paul and Barnabas, since the one said that they ought
               to take John who was called Mark with them on their preaching, while the other said
               not. These things are written as a pattern for us, in order that we may not fear and
               be caused to fall. It is not possible that being men we should not be angered: but,
               if we are angered, we must turn from our anger. Therefore in the case of Paul and
               Elpidius the devout bishops also let the suggestions of a benevolent mind and the
               course of forgiveness prevail, and let them share in the privileges and title of
               bishops, but not thrust themselves into their cities, if the time invite to this,
               seeing that other God-loving bishops have once been lawfully designated to their
               sees, nor have any share in the rights belonging to that parish: a principle which,
               as I have been told, they have in fact with great propriety as well as with much
               justice acknowledged to you in writing. For they also shall not lack any kind of
               consolation which, while consistent with the canons, will not cause any useless
               annoyance or injury to anyone, if it take place here. For indeed "our life is swifter
               than a runner," as it is written: <pb n="162"/> and "what the day that is coming will
               bring forth" we know not at all. I have written this epistle while suffering the
               affliction of a fugitive and unable to set footin [...] as itis written, [...] and,
               as [...] says, no book and no [...] surrounds me. But [...] remembering the sacred
               [...] and [...] in[my] memory the laws and customs also that were practised from of
               old in the holy churches. Wherefore also I have both received and duly praised the
               resolutions canonically adopted by you and inserted in an epistle concerning those in
               the Christ-loving city of the Antiochenes who wish to come to repentance. For they
               were lawful and proper, and such as, while not falling outside the limits of what is
               lawful, bore the marks of a loving disposition and of clemency. If anything else also
               of this kind should happen, [...] </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
