<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3112">To Theodore, Presbyter and Archimandrite of
               the Monastery of Father Romanus among the Saints</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">164-67</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.55">
            <pb n="164"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Theodore presbyter and archimandrite of
               the monastery of father Romanus among the saints.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 3rd book the 32nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> Even I, though am in hiding and live in different places at different times on
               account of the present stress, was not unaware of your religiousness' praiseworthy
               life. Wherefore also I thought the expressions of John the Evangelist and Apostle
               fitted to be addressed to you by me, which he composed when writing an epistle to
               someone and speaking thus: "I rejoiced greatly when brethren came and testified to
               the truth that is in thee, how that thou walkest in the truth." Continue therefore to
               show the same energy, and press forwards, and enlarge the rational flock of those who
               practise with you the ascetic life of solitariness, and let them henceforth have a
               'measure of wheat' of the doctrines of philosophy with understanding, as the gospel
               text advises; which also promises a blessing to him who does this carefully and with
               diligence, saying, "Blessed is the bondservant whom his lord shall come and find so
               doing. Of a truth I say unto you that he will set him over all that he hath." The
               question also that you have now been pleased to ask of the religious presbyter Thomas
               by your letter was in truth in consonance with your <pb n="165"/> understanding. For
               he sent me the letter that you wrote, and, when it came to my knowledge, I praised
               it. And, owing to the urgency of the matter, I considered it right to treat all other
               things as secondary, and send you this mean letter: in which it is pointed out that
               all of you who hold to communion with us must not recognise any distinction between
               those who are banished from the East, and made illustrious by the combat of
               confessorship, and the saintly bishops in Egypt, and that you must reckon that to be
               one church which is compacted together in the orthodox faith, and confession and
               communion, and is most pure and free from the no-association with the heretics; and
               that you must also have no vain hesitation about ordinations: but that both your
               religiousness and the other religious archimandrites of the holy cloisters that have
               been banished from Palestine! on account of the word of truth must after probation
               present your own brethren to the God-loving bishops in Egypt, in order that they may
               ordain presbyters and deacons for you, and satisfy the requirements of your need. How
               is it anything but an unreasonable state of affairs and one fraught with matter for
               every kind of accusation that, while the bishops who have been banished from other
               countries and bear upon them marks for Christ's sake flee to the great orthodox
               apostolic church in Alexandria as to a mother, certain men out of a childish mind
               should create a distinction that does not <pb n="166"/> exist between those who are
               thus united and make up the compact union of the limbs of the one body, and through
               the very facts themselves proclaim the immobility and steadfastness of the holy
               persecuted churches in the East and those in Egypt, which are already preparing to
               suffer the same things, and showing the immoveable nature of their piety? I think
               that the events which happened a short time ago in Alexandria have reached your ears
               also, events capable of showing even to those who are very foolish the steadfastness
               and fixedness of the saintly archbishop Timothy, and of the God-loving bishops under
               him, and of the churches in their cities: so that one may fitly utter the celebrated
               expressions of Isaiah the prophet, "Tabernacles that shall not shake; nor shall the
               pegs of her tabernacle be moved for ever, and her cords shall not be broken asunder."
               Therefore for a man to try to separate by vain thoughts things that are so admirably
               united, and to divide things that are so indivisible through the inspiration of grace
               from above is a thing fraught with matter for every kind of evil-speaking and
               fault-finding. This we warn both your love of God and all who communicate with us to
               shun, and to cast such stones of stumbling out of the Lord's ways as it is written,"
               and, as we said before, to reckon the ordination of the saintly bishops of the East
               and that of those of Egypt to be one, and not recognise any distinction between
               these. If you wish to read <pb n="167"/> this letter to any other persons also, in
               order to show what our opinion is, neither do we forbid this. How can it not be right
               that we should also proclaim openly in words the things that we in actual practice
               think and do? </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
