<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3114">To Proclus the Bishop</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">167-71</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.56">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Proclus the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after expulsion, from the 3rd book the 36th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The words that I wrote to the two of you in common were enough to show your love of
               God my opinion, since you thought me at all competent to give advice. For my part,
               since "I have boldness of speech towards you," as Paul says to the Corinthians, I
               thought that, inasmuch as you have been brought up from the earliest times in works
               of piety, and have stood with us from the beginning, and borne the assaults of many
               waves, that you are competent to give advice and direction to others also in what is
               right. However choice is an evil thing, evil indeed, and may involve even wise men in
               ruin in adverse times, for, "they were confounded and staggered like a drunken man,
               and all their wisdom was swallowed up," says he that sings figuratively and
               instructively. Wherefore I myself also recognise our nature's feebleness, and,
               inasmuch as I am subject to the same weaknesses, I grant you forgiveness for having
               <pb n="168"/> shown a common weakness and being in need of encouragement, Perhaps
               also some thoughts are springing up in your heart, which put such ideas as these into
               you and say, "This man, because he has nothing to do with the affairs of the world,
               and is not assailed by trouble of this sort, and does not know what kind of thing is
               the tie of nature that arises from the marriage connexion and the birth of children,
               will give you impassioned advice from beyond the boundaries, and will speak as from
               some exalted height with those that creep upon the earth." Therefore in answer to
               these things also we must use introductory words and say what is the truth. Paul the
               wise man and chosen vessel, who had Christ so firmly established in him that in
               giving ecclesiastical commandments he would sometimes appeal to the laws of Christ,
               and draw his admonitions from them, and at another put forward his own thoughts in
               place of a law and say, "I have no commandment of the Lord; but I give counsel;
               inasmuch as I have obtained mercy of the Lord to be a believer," when appointing
               bishops, did not take men from the training-school of the solitary life and set them
               over the churches, nor men of philosophic habits, free from wives, and without
               children, but he said, "The bishop ought to be the husband of one wife," and, "one
               that ruleth his house well and hath his children in subjection with all gravity"; and
               he was not assured as regards these ties of nature, the ties of <pb n="169"/>
               children I mean and of a wife, that they would corrupt the character of a shepherd in
               times of stress. But, as to what the character of a shepherd is, hear the shepherd
               Himself crying and saying, "The good shepherd layeth down his life for his sheep." If
               therefore we have been called by Him to so great a height of Spiritual authority, it
               is absolutely necessary that we should rise to the same height, and that we should
               "mind high things" and "seek the things which are above, where Christ is, sitting on
               the right hand of God": so that, when He "is revealed," then we "also may be revealed
               with Him in glory," and share with Him in splendour. But, that you may not think to
               yourself that you alone among bishops have had a wife and children, and are required
               to "resist sin even to blood," as it is written, and to distinguish yourself in
               combats on behalf of piety, the words of the apostolic legislation that have just
               been quoted, words that have a general application to every bishop, would in
               themselves have been sufficient answer to such a fancy: but I will quote to you from
               actual experience also an example worthy of consideration, which shows that in times
               of martyrdom the women also who were joined in marriage to those who held the rank of
               the episcopate contested and strove in the same contests. Here it is. Dionysius, who
               was bishop of the great Christ-loving city of the Alexandrines, in an epistle to
               Flavian bishop of <pb n="170"/> Antioch, in which he describes the combats of those
               who were martyred in the neighbourhood of Alexander's city in the days of Decius,
               after describing the other events introduces this statement also: [...] in sin, and
               utterly refuses to turn her eyes upwards while there is time. For for you, who bear
               with patience that which has happened in this matter also, a worthy reward will
               surely be reserved, although you did not treat her case with circumspection at the
               beginning. But, if you both exert yourself and bring her back from the error in which
               she is involved to repentance and recognition of the truth, then you will in truth be
               doubly a father to her, insomuch as to be able to say, "Behold! I and the children
               whom God has given me." For you must do all these things to the best of your power,
               in order that you may not have your conscience accusing you, as if you ought to have
               done something and had neglected it. You know well from the sacred writings what Eli
               suffered, because, though he spoke reprovingly to his sons and chid their folly in
               the unhallowed deeds which they committed, yet he did not deal with them as a ruler.
               But the Lord will, I know well, grant your sanctity understanding, so that with
               fatherly admonitions you may mingle such censures as are likely to produce conversion
               and are suited to a ruler, and that you may take the sheep upon your shoulders, and
               present it to the chief shepherd Christ, <pb n="171"/> and reckon it among those that
               are saved. For indeed He alone is able by His almighty power and His grace to make
               things possible that with men are impossible. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
