<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3116">To Didymus the Bishop</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">171-75</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.57">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Didymus the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 3rd book the 50th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The news of the attack of the barbarians! and of the captivity that has fallen upon
               those who live in your neighbourhood, and the siege and war that have been hanging
               over your city have caused intolerable grief and sorrow to all who hear of it, but
               especially to us. Our anxiety on other grounds and general sorrow was further
               increased by thinking of your religiousness, who have had to endure such an
               unexpected attack at the very beginning of your episcopate: since men who have been
               admitted to feed rational souls reckon common and public? calamities as their own.
               Wherefore David also the great among prophets and kings, when he saw his subjects
               being destroyed in the death-dealing plague by the divine wrath, being unable to
               endure the sight, begged that he might suffer instead of those under his rule, saying
               to the Lord, "It is I who have sinned, and I the shepherd have done wickedly: and
               these the sheep what have they done? Let thine hand be upon me, and upon my father's
               house." <pb n="172"/> And by so saying he changed the wrath to mercy, and stayed the
               plague. Therefore you also must know that such events are fraught with no small
               hardship: but, when men consider things in the right spirit, and accept the
               chastisement as a help, they bring them great profit, and lead them into close
               relationship with God. Therefore we also, looking at what has happened, believe that
               it is by divine providence that you have been raised to a sacred headship of this
               kind, in order that you may show yourself a man capable of comforting the flock that
               has been entrusted to you. As to the question that you ask about presbyters who have
               grown very old, I mean whether their customary share in the distribution of presents
               ought to be cut off from them, on the ground that they cannot perform the sacred
               ministry, and others introduced in their place who ought to be supported, and receive
               the portion cut off from these, know that such a thing is not legal, nor otherwise
               holy. If men who perform bodily services as soldiers for kings on earth, when they
               reach old age, receive higher stipends, inasmuch as they have previously toiled and
               laboured in wars, how is it anything but abominable that men who have served in the
               sacred military service should not only not receive higher honour in their old age,
               but even be deprived of the customary emoluments? David's soldiers also once thought
               something like this, when they went down with him to fight against the barbarians who
               had come against them, and mightily overcame them, and stripped them of all the booty
               <pb n="173"/> that had been carried off by them from the wars with Israel. For,
               when they returned from the war and their minds were somewhat uplifted on account of
               their victory, they claimed that they alone should take all the things that they had
               captured from the barbarians, and not give an equal portion to those who stayed in
               the camp and guarded their baggage, on the ground that they had not taken part with
               them in the fight in exactly the same fashion. And upon this the just David was
               indignant, saying that those also who remained to guard the baggage ought to get a
               portion equal to that of those who formed part of the array in war. Moreover also he
               repressed their greed and said to them in rebuke, "And who will hearken to these
               words of yours? For they are not inferior to you. But, as his portion is that went
               down to the war, so shall his portion be that stayed by the baggage. They shall part
               alike." Knowing therefore from the divine writings that these things are laid down as
               law, give greater gratification, if possible, to those who have grown old, both in
               stipends and in honour. For honour is the due of. elders, and the enjoyment of the
               good things that: come after war. The great governor Moses also wrote in Numbers that
               he said to Hobab his wife's brother, who was journeying with Israel in the way in the
               wilderness, "Leave us not, forasmuch as thou wast with us in the wilderness. And thou
               shalt be an <pb n="174"/> elder among us. And it shall be, if thou go with us, we
               will do thee good out of all the good things which the Lord shall do unto us." But I
               beg your love of God not to associate indiscriminately with those who unreasonably
               cut themselves off from our communion, men who magnify with lips only an orthodoxy
               that is inactive and runs no risk, while they take no part in the sufferings of the
               persecuted church which it has suffered for the sake of the sound word of faith and
               is still even now suffering, but justify themselves in vain. Lack of discrimination
               towards them confirms them yet more in the evil itself, and they think to themselves
               that we blame ourselves as if there had been something wanting in our conduct, and
               honour and praise them as men of strictness. We listen also to our Saviour in the
               Gospels crying, "He that is not with me is against me: and he that. gathereth not
               with me scattereth." Ignatius also the great bishop and martyr, who fed the church of
               the Antiochenes after Peter the captain of the apostles, and, because he was full of
               the Holy Spirit, was called "the God-clad," says in his letter to the men of Smyrna,
               "Shun divisions, as the beginning of evils." Further also in another letter of his to
               those at Philadelphia he says thus: "If anyone follows a man who makes a schism, he
               does not inherit the kingdom of God." Again in writing to the Ephesians he
               expresses the same thing in a more fearful form, saying, "He therefore that <pb
                  n="175"/> does not join in the assembly has already behaved proudly, and separated
               himself. For it is written, 'The proud God resisteth." Irenaeus also a man of ancient
               times, bishop of the city of Lyons (this is one of the cities of the men called
               Gauls), who was a hearer of Polycarp bishop of Smyrna and martyr, who was a disciple
               of John the Evangelist, wrote thus, in his fourth book against heresies, about the
               Lord who will judge every breathing thing, and as it is written the whole "world in
               righteousness": "But he will also judge those who create schisms, who are men void of
               the love of God, and seek that which is for their profit but not the union of the
               church, and for small and contemptible reasons cleave and divide the great and
               glorious body of Christ and, as far as in them lies, destroy it, men who speak peace
               and make war, who truly strain out the gnat, but swallow the camel. For it is
               impossible that any benefit can spring from them of the same kind as is the injury
               that springs from their schism." To these things therefore direct your mind, and
               beware of the obstructive forces everywhere: especially of those that arise from
               thoughts on the right side, which lead astray from the "royal road": and, looking to
               heaven and making God your guide in all things, cry, "Direct my paths according to
               thy word"; and you will surely go straight, and not fail to do what is right. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
