<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3119">To Didymus the Bishop</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">176-78</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.58">
            <pb n="176"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Didymus the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 3rd book the 90th
               letter.</head>
            <p> I have learned with accuracy the whole story of the devout deacon Sannus: and how
               before coming to the see where your love of God is priest he lived an indiscriminate
               or disordered life, and how you brought him back to devout habits, and how you laid
               down an injunction for him to keep. Now after examining the whole matter I have found
               that, because he appropriated to himself some small sum which formed part of the
               revenue, you were wroth and angry with him, and removed him from the charge with
               which he had been entrusted. Therefore I beg you to receive this man, and place him
               in the same rank, without any difference whatever. If by careful observance he
               observed all the other points on which reform was difficult, and gave up the
               long-standing practice of disorderly habits, which is like a necessity of nature, and
               was converted to a devout life, and took upon him the character proper to deacons,
               let us not upset everything on account of a sin in one single point: for it is
               impossible for everything to be reformed at once. This is the practice of teachers
               also, gently to bear with pupils once and twice and many times, when they are at
               fault and do not repeat without mistake, until they attain to perfection. Physicians
               also after the same fashion, when they warn patients to abstain from things <pb
                  n="177"/> that are pleasant and harmful, are often defeated and grant them
               indulgences, allowing them to taste some of the things that they like: and they do
               not in every point insist upon strict observance of the irksome methods demanded by
               science, but they treat the patient in accordance with what is possible. This method
               of gradual treatment and cure was shown in a figurative manner by our Lord and God
               Jesus Christ also in the Gospels. When He might have healed, one of the blind men who
               were brought to Him by word only, as He did in the case of that leper, saying in a
               manner befitting God, "I will be thou clean," and immediately upon the word completed
               the cure, He cured him with a certain delay and procrastination. For "He led him," he
               says, "out of the village. And, when He had spat on his eyes, He put His hands upon
               him and was asking him if he saw aught. And, his eyes having been opened, he said, 'I
               see the men walking like trees.' Then He put His hands again upon his eyes and his
               sight was restored and his eyes were opened, and he saw everything clearly."
               Therefore He that is our God and the instructor of our souls by working this cure
               with a certain wise delay instructs us that the bishops in His holy churches, who are
               His representatives, ought to make use of gradual modes of treatment in order to
               bring those whose minds are blinded to the light, until their eyes are gradually
               opened and they see the rays of truth clearly. <pb n="178"/> Accordingly do you also
               adopt this plan, both in this present affair and in others that happen after the same
               pattern. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
