<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Photius and Andrew the Presbyters and
               Archimandrites of the Holy Cloisters in Caria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">179-91</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.60">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Photius and Andrew the presbyters and
               archimandrites of the holy cloisters in Caria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 7th book the 15th
               letter.</head>
            <p> Since you loyally fulfil the active part of the ascetic and philosophic life,
               therefore you also gather the fruits of knowledge from your labours, which are sound
               faith and zeal on its behalf which raises itself to God, and devoutness and a spirit
               of understanding and of discretion. [...] [You also therefore, who through practice
               in asceticism are pure in your minds, in the same manner burn in the spirit, and
               carry the flame of zeal blazing in you: knowing as you do that all zeal is not
               praiseworthy, but that which is according to knowledge. <pb n="180"/> For you listen
               to Paul accusing the Jews and saying, "For I bear record of them that there is a zeal
               of God in them: but not according to knowledge": and you have restrained the ardour
               of zeal with the cords of devoutness: for "blessed is the man that feareth all things
               on account of devoutness." The case of the man who was received by you to communion
               and was converted from the heresy of the Nestorians and the Diphysites and the
               believers in two persons to the orthodox faith and said that he had received
               ordination to the diaconate you have thought fit to bring to the knowledge of my
               meanness, and learn whether you received this man lawfully and in accordance with the
               strictness of the canons or not. We say therefore that, in so far as you required him
               to anathematize on oath and in writing the heresy of the Nestorians and of the
               Diphysites, and renounce communion with them, the transaction was good and lawful:
               and he should not otherwise have shared in the reception of the divine mysteries,
               unless he had after this model done something to satisfy the mind. But neither should
               he have been presented for the ministry of the diaconate at all, nor on the other
               hand should he have proclaimed in writing the diaconal rank. For no canon or precept
               orders that those who have been converted from the heresy of the Nestorians shall
               receive ordination afresh. If they received ordination afresh, those also besides who
               were bap<pb n="181"/>tized by the same heresy would always be baptized afresh. For,
               when men who have received ordination from particular heresies receive the laying on
               of hands afresh, those also who have been baptized by those very same heresies are
               baptized afresh: as the synod of the three hundred and eighteen holy fathers ordered
               in the case of the heresy of Paul of Samosata, and the heresies of those who are like
               them in impiety. And no one has ever been shown to have perfected by a second baptism
               those who flee from] the Nestorian and Diphysite heresy, and have taken
               refuge in the church, of the orthodox. Timothy also of saintly memory, archbishop of
               the city of the Alexandrines, who wrote in more severe terms from exile owing to the
               extreme ardour of the people, which would not consent even to cast a glance at those
               who derived ordination from the Diphysite error, which Proterius introduced there,
               after his return both communicated with Paul of God-loving memory, high-priest of the
               city of the Ephesians and head of the holy churches in Asia, in the Encyclical
               formula, upon his anathematizing with the bishops under him the Chalcedonian impiety:
               and also, after he had reached Alexandria, received those who came from the heresy of
               the Diphysites in the rank in which they were, bishops I mean and presbyters and
               deacons, upon their anathematizing the heresy itself in writing, and accepting such a
               period of separation for peni<pb n="182"/>tence only as he judged and determined to
               be good. In such cases in fact it is in the discretion of high-priests to shorten and
               to extend the spaces of time according to the consciousness of the penitents with
               regard to the sins committed by them. But he has not been shown to have done anything
               else whatever as to these men which impairs or disturbs the strictness of the canons
               in any point whatsoever; no second ordination, no second baptism, no chrism; as some
               from unreasonable fervour and inconsiderate zeal dared to do, at the beginning
               immediately after the synod at Chalcedon had been held, and became a cause of schisms
               and of divisions. For this reason also, after the holy Timothy of whom we are now
               speaking had thus received those who came from the error of Proterius and of the
               Diphysite heresy in accordance with the laws of the apostolic church, many men, fired
               as it were by some disorderly madness and self-willed ardour, separated from
               communion with him, while they did their best to inflame others also among those who
               were more than ordinarily weak, like those who said, "We have no part in David,
               neither inheritance in the son of Jesse," and divided Israel into two. Hence also
               they ascribed to them the name of the Novatians who do not accept penitence for sins
               committed; and for a long time they disturbed the church, although they gradually
               melted away, and as the book of the Acts says "were scattered and <pb n="183"/> came
               to naught," like the rebellious band and seditious flock of Theudas and of Judas the
               Galilean. These things we have related, not because we would reckon acts done by
               heretics valid (they are in fact invalid and without foundation and unsubstantial),
               but because we would explain that healing is not applied to converts from heresy in
               one way only, but according to the nature of the error: perfection and the cure of
               the disease being granted to some through baptism and ordination, to others through
               chrism, to others through their anathematizing the heresy in writing, and repudiating
               it and showing fruits of penitence. It is in fact absolutely necessary for us to
               follow the canonical precepts and regulations of the saintly bishops as medical
               directions given with understanding, and from them to apply to each man the cure
               suited to him. Therefore he also who has been received to communion by your love of
               God, if he scrupulously fulfil the prescribed time in the reforming practice of
               penitence and you bear witness to it, will be allowed the position of deacon by the
               orthodox bishops, upon presenting to them a written. petition containing a confession
               of his sin and an anathema of the heresy. For the voice of a high-priest and bishop
               and his permission is a law of the Spirit, and full of power to turn the convert into
               another man, as is written about Saul when he heard the voice of the prophet Samuel,
               and went in the way that he ordered <pb n="184"/> him to go: and the sacred scripture
               speaks thus: "And it was so that, when he turned his shoulder to go from Samuel, God
               gave him a changed heart, and all these signs came upon him that day." Those also who
               are in the rank of laymen, if they repudiate by anathema the Nestorian and Jewish
               heresy of the Diphysites, and by sincerely repenting place themselves within the
               bounds of the orthodox apostolic church, and are included among the sheep of the
               great God and chief shepherd Christ, will immediately cast from them everyone soever
               who is an alien, and will be invisibly adorned with the manifestations of the Holy
               Spirit. If a man on entering by night a house full of torches? is completely pervaded
               by the flashing light, who doubts that the church of the orthodox, which is full of
               the gifts of the Holy Spirit, causes the man who opens the eyes of a repentant heart
               to be pervaded by the light that is suprasensual and divine? The power of the true
               church assembled in a pure fashion in the Lord's name is so great that it even
               constitutes men who come to it prophets, men who have not joined the congregation in
               order to share in any divine gift, but in order to carry out a royal order. For in
               the first book of Kingdoms it is written thus: "And Saul sent messengers to take
               David. And they saw the church of the prophets, and Samuel was standing at their
               head. And the Spirit of God came upon the messengers of Saul, and they prophesy. And
               it was told <pb n="185"/> Saul and he sent other messengers and they also prophesy.
               And Saul again sent a third set of messengers, and they also prophesied." If
               therefore at a time when the practices of the legal shadowy service prevailed the
               Holy Spirit granted such things to the assembly and the name of a church, what great
               and wonderful thing will it not do in the church that was bought by the divine blood
               of the Lamb and God, and has nothing shadowy in it, but the whole sun of
               righteousness flashing upon all the acts that are performed in it? For many other
               instances might have been added to those mentioned. At the very beginning when I was
               set over the Christ-loving city of the Antiochenes, and immediately, so to speak,
               upon my being raised to the episcopal throne (unworthily indeed, but still by God's
               mercy), certain men who were infected with the self-created religion of the
               Re-anointers, following a certain deceiver named Theodotus, who unlawfully
               re-anointed converts from the Nestorian heresy to the orthodox faith, composed a
               petition consisting of uncanonical propositions, and had this given to me as I was
               going out into the street by a certain man who was himself also a victim of their
               disease; and ] have composed a certain short treatise against it. Accordingly out of
               respect for the love of teaching and the strictness of your religiousnesses I have
               thought it necessary to look <pb n="186"/> for this and copy it out and send it you,
               in order that nothing bearing upon this subject may remain unknown to you, so far
               as the power and the limited capacity that has fallen to the lot of my meanness
               extends. For we must "walk in the royal road," as it is written," and "not turn aside
               to the right or to the left." For many, starting from considerations that are rather
               upon the right side than otherwise, have been led into excess, and so fallen into the
               very pit of destruction. For this reason also the text of the law commands that he
               that pursues after justice shall pursue it justly: that is, know the principles of
               justice and be instructed in them when you pursue that which is just: and be free
               from all passion, and be in this respect a just seeker of justice, and restrain
               yourself on all sides, and stand within the bounds of justice. Many by the very fact
               of wishing to be just have become mentally drunk, and have injured justice through
               their justice which had the appearance of being strict. Whence also the wise
               Koheleth, or rather the teacher of wisdom (for the true Koheleth is Christ, the head
               of the church and the wisdom and the sublime and substantial power of God and the
               Father), checking excess, even if directed to the right side, gives admonition,
               saying, "Be not very righteous nor contrive superfluous wisdom, lest thou be
               astonied." On all points therefore I praise your religiousnesses for having informed
               us of this present question, in order that you may wisely follow the precepts of the
               Holy <pb n="187"/> Spirit: for it is written, "The wise turn not aside from the mouth
               of the Lord: but they reason in assemblies." Accordingly, when a man is not so
               minded, but, making his will law, does what comes into his mind, death is the
               penalty. For he that said these things said also this: "Death lights upon the
               uninstructed." In answer to your other question I shrink and hesitate to say
               anything, and I tardily and reluctantly bring myself to answer, lest I be thought to
               be a cruel and harsh man, when I bring forward the strictness of the church
               tradition. For indeed this custom has prevailed in the holy churches up to the
               present day, I .mean that after the reading of the holy revered book of the Gospels
               there should be a petition on behalf of the catechumens, one of the deacons
               proclaiming the names, and the presbyter thereupon offering a prayer applying to
               those whose names have been proclaimed, in order that they may receive the laver of
               regeneration and the communion of the holy mysteries, and that immediately afterwards
               another proclamation and prayer should follow on behalf of those that are possessed,
               in order that they also may be freed from the. possession of evil spirits, and may
               receive the communion of the all-holy body and blood. Further, when the holy symbols
               that are consecrated in the mysterious sacrifice are about to be brought out into the
               church, and to be placed on the holy altar, the first of the deacons, looking out of
               the door of the deacons' chamber, utters the <pb n="188"/> fearful and awful words,
               "No catechumen, no possessed person, no one that is incapable'," and so those that
               consecrate and those that have been consummated begin the ineffable sacred sacrifice,
               and send upwards the mysterious words. But I have nowhere found in the divine canons
               that such a distinction as this concerning those that are possessed is contained in
               them, the tenor of which is that if a man fights with a fierce demon, and is in the
               habit of assailing and attacking those who come in his way, and rends chains and
               fetters asunder like the man mentioned [in the Gospels which Paul the great also in
               writing to the Corinthians commands men to do, and to discern what is the power of
               the all-holy body, and to consider its greatness, and what the disposition is in the
               heart of him who is to communicate in it. This is what he says: "But let a man
               examine himself, and so let him eat of the bread and drink of the cup. For he that
               eateth and drinketh when he is unworthy eateth and drinketh condemnation to himself,
               in that he hath not discerned the Lord's body. For this cause the sick and diseased
               among you are many, and there are many that sleep. For, if we judged ourselves, we
               should not be judged. But, being judged by the Lord, we are chastised, that we may
               not be condemned with the world:" even as <pb n="189"/> He that cares for our souls
               and is their benign instructor directs everything to this end, that He may not
               condemn us on the day on which He will judge the world and the earth in
               righteousness, in the last condemnation to which there is no end. Those that do not
               judge themselves, but communicate without fear in the holy body and blood He judges
               for a time, chastising them with sicknesses and with diseases that they may come to
               conversion and penitence. And some, even when they are incorrigible, He removes from
               life, in order that they may not be afflicted by endless torments of greater severity
               and greater bitterness in the world to come. Blessed therefore is he who has been
               visited here and been chastised as by an instructor and been moved to prepare for the
               better life, and does not "owing to his hardness and impenitent heart," as the
               Apostle says, "lay up" for himself "a store of wrath for the day of wrath, and for
               the revelation of the just judgment of God, who will render to every man according to
               his deeds." Therefore he also who is possessed by an invasion of evil spirits must
               submit to the canon of the apostolic church, and endure the chastening with
               devoutness, and take upon him thoughts and expressions of thanksgiving and make
               confession to the Lord and say, "I have submitted to the Lord and made supplication
               to him": and He will assuredly have pity upon him (for "He is one that loveth mercy,"
               as the prophet Micah says), and will <pb n="190"/> rebuke the operation of the evil
               spirit, and will deliver His creature. For a man to be contemptuously disposed, and
               to communicate in the sacraments or take part in the sacred ministry contrary to what
               is commanded makes the assault of man-hating spirits yet more fierce. This is also
               confirmed by the wise John who was bishop of Constantinople, in the sermon entitled
               "On the treason of Judas and on the Passover and on the institution of the mysteries,
               and concerning the principle that we should not retain anger," in that he wrote as
               follows: "For then also it was after Judas had received the oblation that the devil
               assailed him; not that he despised the Lord's body, but that he despised Judas on
               account of his presumption: in order that you may learn that it is especially those
               who communicate in the divine mysteries without being worthy that the devil
               constantly assails and attacks, as he attacked Judas then. For privileges benefit
               those who are worthy: but, when men enjoy them undeservedly, they expose them to
               greater punishment. And these things I do not say in order to frighten, but in order
               to secure." As I said before, the intention of the disciplinary regulations of the
               canons is to preserve the visible appearance of the church blameless. For this reason
               they forbade those also who are possessed by an invasion of demons to communicate in
               the holy mysteries: but invisible and secret afflictions [they left] to the <pb
                  n="191"/> conscience of each man. [...] </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
