<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">[Missing Incipit]</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">191-93</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.61">
            <p>[...] a law-court, or to cry out or to annoy in return those who annoyed him, or to
               insult in return those who insulted him, or to bring an action against them for the
               insult to him, similarly and much more is it unbecoming for him who has just received
               the high-priestly chrism upon the crown of his head, and from whom the sweet savour
               therefrom is newly breathing, to involve himself in any of the said matters, Do not
               think to yourself, because the man who was ordained high-priest is not clad in white
               raiment, that he is without the garments that are suprasensual and shine more
               brightly than the brilliancy of the sun, and are as much better than those of men who
               have just been baptized as a high-priest is greater than one who is among the people,
               and as a shepherd is higher than a sheep. <add><emph>And again after other
                  things.</emph></add> But you say that the devout brother Joseph told you
               such-and-such a thing about the devout brother John, and the devout father Zacharias
               such-and-such a thing about another topic. But know that in every matter it is not
               the word of one man that is needed, but that of two or three witnesses. For the
               sacred law says of everyone soever who is tried, whether he be good or whether he be
               evil, that "under two or under three witnesses he shall die that dieth: he shall not
               die under one wit<pb n="192"/>ness: and again, "One witness shall not continue to
               testify against a man, [in all] iniquity and in all sin and in all sinfulness soever
               that he commit. At the mouth of two witnesses, and at the mouth of three witnesses
               shall every word be established." I have used these arguments not in order to show
               that your religiousness is lying (I am convinced that you wrote as you heard): but in
               order to establish the fact that, according to church regulations and the precepts of
               the holy fathers, and the laws of the God-inspired scripture, I cannot upon this
               report pronounce a sentence of censure or of condemnation against anyone, while I am
               far away. Your love of God ought therefore to have devoted that evening to thoughts
               of patience: and on the next day taken with you in the morning the saintly bishops
               the lord Constantine and the lord Victor, as in fact you actually did, and [with] all
               gentleness and humility, [and with] God....also present....at the discussion [first
               described] the circumstances of the annoyance that the deaconess and archimandritess
               Heracliana inflicted upon you, and the insults which, as you write, were levelled
               against you by brother John; and thus your sanctity would have judged, with the awful
               tribunal of Christ, before which we shall all stand, before your eyes, whether it was
               right for your love of God on account of the annoyance that you justly felt to remove
               those sisters from the monastery of the religious Heracliana as persons who were
               suffer<pb n="193"/>ing injury or not, and what method of treatment ought to be
               devised (?) for the affair in order to remedy the injury; and the use of this method
               would have been decreed; and besides this fitting punishment would also have fallen
               upon brother John, inasmuch as he would have been shown by proofs to be an utterer of
               insults, and a man who is living an unchaste and indiscriminate life. If these things
               had been thus decided by discussion, and made known to my meanness, would without any
               hesitation have confirmed them, seeing that they would have been carried out in
               accordance with the custom of the holy churches, and in accordance with the rules of
               the monastic life. <add><emph>And again after other things.</emph></add> But, since
               these things are thus recorded and supported by evidence, if anything displeasing to
               God be done in secret, know that it is not possible that until the end [...] </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
