<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Misael the Deacon</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">195-99</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.63">
            <pb n="195"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Misael the deacon.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 9th book the 43rd
               letter.</head>
            <p> I received the letter of your religiousness, which was forwarded to me from
               Alexandria, from the devout Andrew the reader on the eighth of July. <add><emph>And
                  after other things.</emph></add> The holy Basil also, the teacher of truth,
               says in his ascetic treatise that he who is entrusted with the duty of ministering to
               the needs of a monastery, even if it be the archimandrite, ought not to use or spend
               any of the property of the brother. hood on any pious object, for example on the
               support of the poor and needy or on the ransoming of captives. Therefore neither
               would the case of the saintly man, though it seems to be a matter of piety, have
               given you a right to do anything without my consent, if you are certain from the laws
               and from the will which left the legacy? that it is mine. For you must excuse me from
               adopting the honorary expressions used by friends or by men who are otherwise on
               familiar terms with one another, "My things are yours," and, "You are my lord, lord
               both of my own person and of what possess." For the subject of the present argument
               is the true state of the facts. Moreover also the saintly man does not need a gift
               from us, seeing that he has the serene queen, who will provide him <pb n="196"/> if
               he wish even with more than he needs, and now he has all the orthodox also on account
               of his attested steadfastness in the matter of the confession of the faith. These
               things I have written for the sake of the principles of the evangelic laws, and for
               the sake of preserving a blameless conscience. If it were not so, I reckon things
               once given by you just as if they had been given by me. <add><emph>And after other
                  things.</emph></add> As to the impious Sergius, who is called Bar Fathya and
               has become broad in impiety, so far am from saying that it was by my advice that he
               was ordained deacon that I even anathematize him and the man who, if even in this: he
               speaks truth, ordained him: the one for unlawfully sleeping with his father's wife or
               concubine, and the other for daring to perform ordinations without witnesses in other
               men's cities which do not belong to him at all, without an invitation and on his own
               authority, and not even without price but for filthy lucre. Under the same anathema
               lies also Anatolius, who after ordination to the diaconate has married a second time
               and is godless in his doctrines, even if it is not stated by us, and Podolirius who
               has taught his children to play the harp and dance, and has made them serve the
               devil, and has fallen under the divine canons of the apostles. To the same anathema
               those also are liable who cause confusion <pb n="197"/> besides these, and imagine
               vain things against the orthodox faith, like those who once "imagined vain things
               against the Lord and against his Anointed," and fell from His glory. For these too by
               always reckoning the belly and the passions that are subject to the belly as a god
               inflicted a stain and a blot upon us by being numbered with the orthodox. Therefore
               they must plead not to us but to God, whose name they are profaning among the nations
               as Isaiah and Paul say. <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> But I was
               much distressed that the serene queen presumes to say such grievous, not to say
               blasphemous, things against the holy fathers in respect of doctrines which she does
               not understand, and mocks at the holy Alexander the archbishop, who is one of the
               prelates of the holy synod at Nicaea, and father of the apostolic preacher
               Athanasius, on the ground that even in the theology of the Trinity he termed person
               "nature," and jeers at him as one of those who practise manual crafts, a coppersmith
               for instance or a carpenter of the name of Alexander, or as she says by way of
               accusation an advocate of the treasure-chambers. Let her then mock and jeer at the
               other saintly Alexander also, who was in the same times bishop of Constantinople, and
               by stretching out his hands all night and praying brought it about that, when the
               impious Arius was going to communicate hypocritically with the orthodox, his entrails
               fell through his belly and he gave up the <pb n="198"/> ghost; if the fact that a man
               is called Alexander is a jest, and an occasion and subject for jeering. What are we
               to do about these things, except be silent and grieve our heart, and ask God to have
               mercy upon our many lawlessnesses? For, though much might have been said in answer to
               these things, it is better for us to be silent. As to the mischievous words that the
               heretics invent, the expressions of the holy fathers show what they are, blinding as
               they do like some lightning-flash their keen eyes, and enlightening the minds of the
               orthodox and understanding, while the uninstructed and unlearned see that God is
               glorified and admired among His saints, as David says in song, for the things at
               which they jest and against which they blaspheme. I speak the truth and do not lie
               when I say that, since I wrote the treatise <title>Against the Grammarian</title>,
               there has been no one among the believers who had a high or moderate or small share
               in divine knowledge who was not astonished when he found such expressions of the holy
               fathers collected there, some expressed at length others in few words, and stopping
               the mouth of the blaspheming heretics, who plot against the truth itself. From what
               you now say, that the serene queen has not shrunk from saying such presumptuous
               things against the holy fathers, I certainly imagine that she has also spurned and
               despised, as vain trifling and superfluous futility, <pb n="199"/> my little treatise
               on the question whether our Lord and God Jesus Christ should be said to be from two
               substances even as from two natures, which she thought good to accept when it was
               copied by you in large letters, or through fear of the king's laws which were put
               forth against my writings has not dared to accept it. I wrote to you at that time
               from Chios and to the magnificent and Christ-loving chamberlain Julian to give it to
               be copied: but you wrote nothing at all to me upon these matters. He who writes an
               answer should reply to all the points contained in the letter. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
