<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Castor</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">39-41</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.7">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Castor, bishop of Perga.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               232nd letter.</head>
            <p> The order of devout subdeacons in your see has asked a certain petition of us, which
               does not pass beyond the holy canons, but is contained within the fathers' landmarks
               as the sacred scripture says. For your. sanctity well knows that there is a legal
               commandment in Moses, or rather a commandment of Christ who spoke through him, "Thou
               shalt not remove the landmarks that are from of old, which thy fathers set up." What
               this is it is necessary for <pb n="40"/> us to say clearly. Those of the said order
               of subdeacons who presented the petition to us say that they are greatly contemned
               and insulted by the readers and psalter or singers of the holy church that is under
               you, inasmuch as they are trying to seize their place by violence, and seek to grasp
               for themselves the first rank, contrary to every consideration of justice and the law
               that prevails in the holy churches. Everywhere under the sun the order of subdeacons
               ranks before that of readers: both when named in the sacred tablets, and in the
               reception of the divine body and blood of Christ: and no one will anywhere see a
               reader mentioned before a subdeacon by the sacred voice of those that proclaim.
               Therefore your love of God also must preserve the same order, and not be so negligent
               as to place discipline second to the covetousness of individuals. You, who are a
               teacher and expounder of the divine words, are not unaware that even in the hosts
               that are in heaven there are certain ranks and degrees which are ranked before one
               another, those which are high as well as those which are low, those which ascend as
               well as those which descend. For Paul who was caught up to the third heaven shows
               this, when he writes to the Colossians and says, "Whether they be thrones or
               dominions, whether they be principalities or powers, and by such names shows that
               there is some order which bestows fair adornment even upon the heavenly and invisible
               spirits, and thence descends to <pb n="41"/> the church also, which was founded by
               God the Word who became incarnate and made the things that are seen and the things
               that are not seen, but differs in no way in its similitude from heaven, by reason of
               the great mystery of religion that is every day administered in it Wherefore also the
               same wise Paul in his epistle to the Ephesians writes thus about it: "And he himself
               gave: some apostles: and some prophets: and some preachers: and some pastors, and
               teachers:" and in another place, "For God" (he says) "set first in his church
               apostles: next prophets: next teachers;" and all that follow. By all these things we
               are taught to honour order, and to shun disorder and confusion: which principle we
               urge your sanctity also to observe in this present matter also, which gave occasion
               for this letter. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
