<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Timostratus</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">4-44</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.8">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Timostratus the duke.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               256th 258th letter.</head>
            <p> To me it appears something to be prayed for and desirable to communicate with your
               greatness by letter: and to return the greeting that is owed to you as if it were
               some necessary debt, and not make this the accidental result of causes about which I
               am even <pb n="42"/> ashamed to write. Though I was glad to see your magnificence's
               recent epistle, it was in sorrow that I ceased the reading of it. For I found the
               cause or subject of the letter to be grievous when tested by the divine purpose, and
               difficult and impossible and "after the flesh" to speak in the language of scripture,
               and one that is sensually judged. Whereas the divine apostle, or rather Christ who
               speaks in him, limits and restricts the gift of ordination under a certain threat,
               and says, "Lay thine hand suddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other men's
               sins; keep thyself in purity," by many the thing is considered as one of the ordinary
               trades, that of a smith let us say or a carpenter, or as some office that brings with
               it the gift of sustenance, and an occasion of <foreign>dapane</foreign> or expense
               and a relief for need; as if it were not permissible for us to acquire the means of
               life from any other source than this. And the good men do not know that a man must
               pass through all the degrees of the church, and obtain some kind of previous training
               for priestly functions, and thus be admitted to ordination as presbyter or as deacon:
               and this because the thing is a matter of difficulty and rarely to be undertaken in
               accordance with the previously cited statute which says, "Lay a hand suddenly on no
               man, neither be partaker of other men's sins," and yet further enacts, "Keep thyself
               in purity"; and each of the additions declares the awfulness of the Statute, and
               shows that the hand should in some way <pb n="43"/> be drawn to the head of those who
               are ordained under great necessity and unwillingly. In order to explain the first
               reason for which ordination is a formidable matter, these few words are enough for
               us. But I will add also a second reason, which is concerned with material
               considerations. This is that our holy church is very poor and needy, and that it is
               so much distressed and laden by the weight of interest, that it is hardly able even
               to hold up its head, but debts upon debts are added to its account, and interest upon
               interest is piled up against it. Of this all who live in the great city of Antiochus
               are witnesses: and think there are not many even among those beyond its bounds who
               have not heard of the fact. And nevertheless certain persons in the royal city, and
               others in its neighbourhood, being worried by certain persons, do not cease every day
               so to speak writing to our meanness and asking for ordinations; and they think that
               this is not a matter to excite anger. And so foolish did this desire make some men,
               that they even made a show of desiring the dress of the priesthood only, and not
               seeking further to receive sustenance also: and, having once obtained their object,
               when the time of distribution came, they so to speak held out their hands before all
               the others: so that not only were those who made a mockery of divine things laughed
               at for the guile and treachery, but we also who were fraudulently deceived. These
               things I have been compelled to write to your magnificence, because suffer in myself,
               and because I know that my <pb n="44"/> letter is addressed to a Christian, and to
               one who is capable of sympathizing with me and is perhaps also able to hold out a
               hand to me who am wearied and stupefied like a man who is being strangled by
               creditors, and am compelled to find sustenance for need without sufficient incomes
               and revenues, considering the immoderate extent of a demand that is pious indeed, but
               still difficult to satisfy on account of its frequency. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
