<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3086">To Stephen, Bishop of Tripolis</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">44-46</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="1.9">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Stephen, bishop of Tripolis.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 8th book the
               276th, 277th letter.</head>
            <p> Sinful and vile man though we are, nothing pleases us so much as to try to do
               everything that we wish to do with reason. Wherefore also we accept and praise your
               love of God for having been in doubt with regard to one of the paragraphs that were
               written by us: regarding which we must by all means make a canonical answer; for it
               is written, "The lips of a priest shall keep knowledge, and they shall ask for law
               from his mouth." What is the question which you ask because you were in doubt?
               Whether the devout presbyter Stephen ought to be reckoned among the holy clergy of
               the holy church in Tripolis, when he does not bring with him a dimissory letter from
               him who ordained him. <pb n="45"/> Now in the first place we hear that the man was
               ordained by force, and that he recoiled from or objected to an ordination outside the
               bounds, because he cannot live in a strange city which is not his own. And in the
               second place, even if this which we have stated is not the fact, we ought to know
               that those who do not hold to the orthodox faith, and therefore to the pure communion
               of our apostolic throne, have no share in strict canonical form, and we ought not to
               seek a dimissory letter from these, as if it were something necessary and required by
               law, or any other canonical requisite, when men flee from association with these, and
               come over to the sound teaching. This we may learn easily and without trouble from
               the epistle of the holy Cyril (every utterance of whom one would say is a law of the
               church) to Nestorius, in which he asserted himself to be in communion with all who
               had been separated by him, and had received from him either a ban of excommunication
               or a decree of deprivation, in these words: "But we are all in communion with all who
               have been separated by your devoutness and deprived on account of the faith, laymen
               and clergymen." Do therefore the things which have been decided by us to be right
               without any doubt or hesitation, and know clearly that, if we had not taken much
               account of the saintly memory of Severus the presbyter whose is the lot of the
               saints, we should not perhaps have written to you any such thing. For your love of
               <pb n="46"/> God must be assured that it is our earnest endeavour and desire not
               to write anything at all to the God-loving bishops under the apostolic throne about
               ordination, or about the enrolling of individuals in the order of the clergy, unless
               perhaps some just cause somewhere arise, as we see to be the case in the present
               instance also to which we are now referring. As to the venerable cross remaining
               fixed before the house of Theodore the illustrious governor and
               <foreign>vindex</foreign> after the former fashion, let your sanctity make it your
               earnest concern that it do so. It is the duty of bishops like you to cut short and to
               restrain any unregulated movements of the mob, if they should indeed occur, and to
               set themselves to maintain all good order in the cities, and to keep watch over the
               peaceful manners and customs of those who are fed by them. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
