<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3008">To Alypius</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">427-433</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Alypius.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               257th letter.</head>
            <p> In many instances, when it was necessary for some sanction to be given to an action,
               I have known your illustriousness to set great store by the judgments of my erring
               and uncertain mind, as I persuade myself that it is. <add><emph>And after other
                  things.</emph></add> You certainly, I think, <pb n="428"/> remember that I
               engaged in. a. discussion with you about your consort, whom, having been struck by
               some unexpected suspicion, you drove from your house, and acted like men whose
               marriage has been dissolved, not even giving her the necessary sustenance; and how I
               quoted to you the laws of the Lord and God and Saviour of all, that men are not
               permitted to put away those that cohabit with them under. any other conditions except
               for one reason, I mean, that of fornication; and fornication we judge to be that
               which is manifestly detected, and demonstrated by witnesses or manifest proofs, so
               that, if any suspicion otherwise occur, we do not define this as fornication: but
               rather we turn the supposition into a gentler channel. For "in matters that are in
               doubt we must incline to clemency," as the Theologian Gregory says. I have indeed
               gained sure knowledge that the woman is not liable to charges of fornication so much
               as to going out freely. But such a thing as this invites you to forgiveness, and does
               not give you cause for separation. But, if you are strict in requiring modest
               conduct, know clearly that you are commanded to practise the same observance towards
               your wife as you wish her to practise towards yourself. Christ our lawgiver speaking
               through Paul said, "The wife hath not power over her body: but the husband: and in
               the same fashion the husband also hath not power over his body: but the wife." Re<pb
                  n="429"/>flect therefore whether you also have never been discovered to have been
               seduced by the pleasures of the body. But why do I say "pleasures"? Whether you have
               not in curiosity gratified your eye with greedy gazing, making yourself in no lovely
               fashion a spectator of another's loveliness; the eye which the divine word condemns
               to be plucked out, in. order that it may not bring eternal torture upon the whole
               body: whether you have not relaxed under the influence of the touch: whether you have
               not indulged the sense of smell: whether your ears have never taken delight in
               dissolute songs: whether you have kept all your senses untainted. He that is a strict
               examiner of the doings of others shall have the same judgment exacted from him in the
               case of his: own sins also. If "the head of the wife is the husband," how is he to
               find fault with the rest of his body as being diseased, when he himself is not in
               sound health? <add><emph>And again after other things.</emph></add> And many think in
               the case of a man that when he sins with his body he deserves forgiveness, but a
               woman deserves to be afflicted with grievous punishments. But this is not so: but
               exactly the contrary. For scripture says that a woman shall be admitted to
               forgiveness, inasmuch as she is the "weaker vessel": but a man, inasmuch as he holds
               the place of head, must be an example to the other members of the same body.
               Therefore be <pb n="430"/> not merciless or hard to your member, if you obey Christ's
               laws; and do not apply amputation and cut it off from you: but claim it as part of
               your body, in order that Christ, the Word of God, who out of graciousness became head
               to the body of the church that was infirm, may claim you also as part of Him. If He
               raised human nature, which had committed fornication, to heaven by showing Himself as
               man upon earth, what terrible thing shall we think ourselves to be doing, if we show
               ourselves gentle to our own members, or rather if we are not found to be harsh to
               them beyond what is right, and that when they are not committing unpardonable sins?
               In fact Christ plainly proclaims to us that we ought not casually and lightly to cut
               off her who has been united to us in one flesh through trusting vain suspicions: and
               He says that separation was introduced into the polity or social life by Moses on
               account of our own hardness of heart: but "from the beginning it was not so," He
               proclaims to the discerning. How therefore, tell me, shall we ourselves have
               forgiveness, when we do not conduct ourselves, I do not say according to the gospel
               laws, but not even according to the figurative laws used by Israel who conducted
               himself according to the flesh and was a child? For such statutes were given to them
               in the Book of Numbers by Moses, or rather by God who gave the statute to Moses. He
               says that, if a man say that his <pb n="431"/> wife has committed adultery, and do
               not find her doing this evidently, or be able to prove the act by witnesses, but is
               excited by the rage of jealousy, that he shall commit such judgment to God: and that
               he shall approach the priests of his time, not entering a suit of jealousy, but
               offering "a sacrifice of jealousy." And look, I pray, at the principle that is
               carried out in the sacrifice, how even before the actual methods of conviction are
               used it defends the woman. Whereas it was the custom for fine wheaten flour to be
               offered in sacrifice, he commanded barley meal to be offered on her behalf,
               signifying by the barley the falseness and futility of jealous suspicion: but neither
               shall oil (he says) be poured over the sacrifice, on account of the asperity and
               unkindness of the occasion: and, when the sacrifice has been performed in this way,
               and the rest of the sacred rite has been duly accomplished, then the woman shall
               drink the water of conviction, the priest having first prayed over the same water,
               and shall either repel the evil suspicion from her by suffering no evil in her body,
               or shall be found to be guilty of the charges, and fall into God's hands by her belly
               being rent and the penalty for the deeds that have been done paid by her on the spot.
               Wherefore have I repeated this to you? That you may learn that we also ought not to
               entrust the judgment upon this matter to ourselves, but to refer everything to our
               sacrifice which is Christ. He is no liar who said that <pb n="432"/> unless our
               "righteousness exceed that of the scribes and of the Pharisees" we shall not "enter
               into the kingdom of heaven". Therefore both according to the old law and according to
               the gospel polity," where the suspicion is not clear, let us not take ourselves but
               God as the judge of these things. And we must obey Paul who gives wiser advice than
               we do. He says, "Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come and
               make light the hidden things of darkness, and reveal the counsels of the hearts; and
               then shall every man have praise from God." That you have just cause for making the
               charge we are clearly persuaded: but that the woman has not offended beyond
               forgiveness I think you have already been persuaded by what has been written. But, if
               this does not persuade, we say this. She has sinned, she has done all that is evil as
               you have said, she has recognized her sin, she confesses that she ts guilty, she
               weeps and groans, she takes refuge in your mercy, she begs your clemency; seize the
               opportunity. Commit yourself to God: prepare pity for yourself by showing pity. You
               also being a man are certainly in need of mercy. Look at common nature. Consider the
               instability of human things. We are certainly not walking upon ground that is firm
               and not to be shaken. Let us expect ourselves also to fall, and let us set upright
               those that have fallen. The saying <pb n="433"/> is not mine: "Let him that thinketh
               he standeth take heed lest he fall," says divine scripture. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
