<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To a Woman on behalf of Maximus in the Name of Abba</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">433-36</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.2">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same in the person of Abba on behalf of brother
               Maximus, to a certain woman.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 1st book the
               272nd letter.</head>
            <p> I have asked our holy father Abba about that question as requested in your modesty's
               epistle, and I have received a complete answer from him. He said that those who have:
               once been united in marriage, seeing that marriage "is honourable and the bed
               unsullied," ought not to desire to separate from one another by reason of religion
               except where there is consent. For the divine Apostle says, "Deprive not one another,
               except it be by consent for a time, in order that ye may give yourselves up to
               prayer, and again come together." For the same said above that it is the husband who
               has power over the wife's body, and, <foreign>vice versa</foreign>, that it is the
               wife who has power over the husband's body: saying, "The wife hath not power over the
               body but the husband: and in the same fashion the husband also hath not power over
               his body, but the wife." It is therefore manifest that, unless the husband consents,
               the wife who separates has no forgiveness, and she makes herself a cause of <pb
                  n="434"/> his turning aside to fornication. If then your husband consents, you are
               permitted to place yourself under the yoke of piety: there is no one who will find
               fault with so praiseworthy and admirable a choice. But, if the husband cannot
               restrain his body, and therefore will not permit you to do this, put up with the
               marriage-state: such intercourse that saves the husband is better than an abstinence
               from pleasures that is unknown to the canons. The aim of divine scripture not in this
               only but in everything else too regards not the person of him who has obtained mercy,
               but that of him who is infirm: and it especially wishes that those who are strong
               shall condescend to those who lie on the earth. It does not accept the man who
               regards his own interest only, but the man who rather treats his neighbour's interest
               as if it were his own profit. So therefore in this present case also it is pleasing
               to God that both of you should attain and win the goal of purity consisting in
               continence: but, if the inclinations of your husband's will do not accord with your
               own readiness, the laws of holy scripture judge the marriage-state to be better, in
               order that they may gain you both. This we say on the assumption that the husband
               wishes to live chastely, and restricts the pleasures that cannot be restrained to
               intercourse with his wife only. But, if he goes beyond what is right, and does not
               keep the marriage unsullied, but associates with other women also after the manner of
               a beast, then the wife incurs no danger by neglecting such a man, and giving the
               preference to the excellent state, <pb n="435"/> and taking no account of the
               marriage, but soaring on piety's wing, and turning her eyes to the solitary life, and
               keeping her holiness of mind and of body always unsullied. This also our said holy
               father further laid down, saying that, although the husband be living chastely, being
               content to have intercourse with you only, but you have already chosen for yourself
               to live among virgins, and have included yourself in their order, although the thing
               was not right in its beginning, for you ought not in fact to have left your husband
               while he was living chastely, yet still it is not seemly for you now to separate from
               the virgins, and give them also occasion for stumbling. It is to be feared lest, if
               you return to your husband, they also may imitate such a practice, and may defile
               God's bridechamber after having been once united to Christ the heavenly Bridegroom.
               It is impiety of a high degree that after having been set apart to God they should
               prefer the corruptible intercourse rather than the immortal and heavenly connexion.
               But, if you have not yet lived with virgins, but only withdrawn from intercourse,
               according to the principle stated by us above act in common with the husband, and, if
               he does not consent, you ought to follow his inclination, and prefer the
               marriage-state to purity, because this is pleasing to God. But, if the husband does
               not desire intercourse with you, but wishes you to live within the house with the
               children who have been born to you from the common <pb n="436"/> marriage even if
               they be males, this too is also acceptable to God. These things have been said as in
               a letter: but we think that in what we have written we have in no point failed to
               answer the question of your religiousness. This epistle has been addressed to you by
               our holy father himself in his own very words; for he was able to make his own
               spiritual. mind clear without the greatness of his divine thoughts being befouled by
               the squalor of my words. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
