<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3011">To Theodore, Tribune and Notary</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">436-39</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.3">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Theodore the tribune and notary.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 4th book the 80th
               letter.</head>
            <p> I think that I still see the torch of the divine light shining in you, under the
               influence of which you would have almost gone so far as to betake yourself to the
               philosophic life, had it not been that you restrained that tyrannical desire like
               some fiery steed by the bits of God's laws. What are the bits? "Art thou bound to a
               wife? seek not release." And again "Let every man in the calling wherein he was
               called therein abide." And again, "Deprive not one another, except it be by consent
               for a time, in order that ye may give yourselves up to prayer, and again come
               together." If then you have by devout and God-loving conduct attached your spouse to
               the same zeal and yearning for <pb n="437"/> the good life, fly, and withdraw to
               philosophy. But, if she has not attained to this excellence, and cleaves to the life
               here, and is unable to restrain the impulse of the flesh, seek not your own good but
               your fellow's. The whole force of Christianity as well as the commandment supporting
               the law and the prophets that says, "Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself,"
               points to this: the commandment which the Lord above all fulfilled when He graciously
               showed Himself to us by His coming in the flesh, and He said "A new commandment I
               give unto you that ye love one another as I have loved you, that ye also may love one
               another; and by this shall every man know that ye are my disciples, if ye love one
               another." How then shall we not offend against the laws of love, if we suffer the
               wife who has been reckoned to be one and the same flesh with us to perish? for, just
               as no man of sense prays that his head may be sound, while his other members are
               afflicted with paralysis, or are filled with disease, (for the head also will
               certainly share in the malady), so it is not in accordance with sound understanding
               for us to concern ourselves about our own salvation, while we neglect our wife's,
               when we shall on her account be brought to hell. Although in the Gospels with leaving
               father or mother or children there is also included without division the leaving of a
               wife, yet this must necessarily be subject to the later apostolic distinction. In
               fact in <pb n="438"/> external laws also, and in fine in every statute and conception
               general loose statements assuredly follow later distinctions. That the wise Paul
               understands the meaning of the Lord's laws better than we do we shall admit even
               against our will, But let us not think it the wife's consent if the wife permit the
               husband to go merely in order that he may betake himself to a life of continence,
               while she turns aside to the pleasure of worldly passions and a dissolute life; but
               only if she choose the same continence and philosophy as the husband, or, if not
               this, at least chastity and purity. Indeed, when Paul permitted separation from
               society by consent, he used the plural, saying, "in order that ye may give yourselves
               up to prayer," and not "in order that the husband alone may give himself up," or
               contrariwise "the wife." This epistle I have written to you in proportion to my
               poverty. If you obey this, you will obtain the reward for the choice of philosophy,
               and that for the education of your children, training them "in the training and
               teaching of the Lord". I forbear to say that you can also in all characters practise
               philosophy, seeing that you have a soul-possessing pillar of excellence in that
               sharer of your name and your belief and man of God: whom also I beg you greet. Who
               could voluntarily forget you, good couple that you are, the modesty of your
               character, the gentleness <pb n="439"/> of your thoughts, your sadness, your
               cheerfulness? For, while you are sad for piety's sake, you yet also by God's grace
               avoid wildbeast-like harshness, and you show the mercy of pity towards the needy and
               poor. Through you your father Asclepius of learned and illustrious memory also reaps
               a blessing, inasmuch as it was to form the material of your beneficence that he
               amassed the profits derived from law-courts. For alone, if I may so say, with few
               others he failed to conform to the passage of Koheleth that says, "There is a
               sickness which I have seen under the sun, riches kept for him that springs from them
               to his hurt." Wherefore also you seem in your sleep to see him feasting when you are
               justified. Accordingly as one that is wise in the Lord take the same Koheleth as a
               good counsellor and "all that thy hand findeth to do do according to thy might"; and
               reverse the order, and feed your children by good works, and leave them to God as a
               patron. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
