<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Conon the Silentiary</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">439-42</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.4">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Conon the silentiary.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               227th letter.</head>
            <p> John, the soldier of Christ, being ardent in everything, and fervent through
               abundance of faith, has thought fit to address an epistle to me containing a <pb
                  n="440"/> question that is overbold and passes beyond canonical limits about your
               modest daughter, and about those who are eager to take her in marriage. He gave in
               fact the names of those who are wooing her, and also in the name of your magnificence
               asked that the question might be brought before the holy old men, and before some of
               the women who have practised an ascetic life, in order that they may say to whom it
               is most fitting for the girl to be joined in marriage. But I, knowing that fathers
               who have the spirit of discretion turn deaf ears to such questions, in order that
               they may not seem to be bringing upon themselves the reputation of soothsayers and
               charlatans, did not dare to write anything of the kind to them, lest perhaps I might
               even expose myself to sentence as an uninstructed person, for being clad in the
               philosophic and solitary garb and yet propounding to them questions suited for those
               that live in the world, which those attempt only out of compliance with the pleasure
               of those that ask, men who pass all their time in Byzantium, and often turn their
               attention even involuntarily to such voluntary service, to use a scriptural
               expression. But we know a few of the fathers who return answer, being stirred by God,
               and not by the questions or the propositions, but by abundant Spirit: of whom the
               sacred text says, "Speech in the heart of a man is as deep water, and a flowing river
               and a <pb n="441"/> fountain of life." The wealth of grace is so to speak plentiful,
               and of its own accord it makes those that surround it outside share in any gift. If
               your greatness had gone to some such men in order to visit them, you would perhaps at
               any rate have derived, not as the result of the question or of the proposition, but
               as the product of such plentiful store, something that would have been of service for
               the solution of the question and the understanding of the present matter. As to those
               who have received such grace from God let this suffice. But, since the utterance of
               our Saviour says in the Gospels, "To every one that asketh thee give," whether it be
               a gift pertaining to the intellect, or one pertaining to the senses, it is necessary
               for me also who see few things, and, far from being able to foresee or preconceive
               the future, do not even know what lies at hand, to say what my advice is. It is that
               you should give the girl who has been brought up by you in faith and in the love of
               God to that one among all her wooers who has the most correct and orthodox
               disposition as regards faith in Christ, and sets himself most earnestly to lead a
               devout and modest life: for this all other things also follow as in the second line.
               In fact He is no liar who said, "Seek first the kingdom of God and His righteousness,
               and all these things shall be added unto you": since to speak the truth it is indeed
               an abominable <pb n="442"/> thing, and one that does not greatly gratify God, or
               perhaps even excites His wrath, for us to pass over manifest judgments as to what it
               is right to do, and facts from which God's pleasure is especially to be seen, from
               whom everything whatsoever that is good comes down, and give directions by unknown
               things or by predispositions, and commit everything to revelations; for some have
               even applied this meaning to the words, "Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God." If
               you will turn your eyes towards the said object, and choose what it is right to do,
               you will not stray from the right course, seeing that: you will obtain God as a
               surety for the future and for a goad result. The Apostle also admonishes us saying,
               "Whatsoever ye do whether in word or in deed, do all in the name of our Lord Jesus,
               giving thanks to God and the Father through Him." </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
