<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Theodore, a Byzantine Monk and Brother-in-law of the Prefects</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">442-47</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.5">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Theodore the Byzantine monk,
               brother-in-law of prefects.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the 18th
               letter.</head>
            <p> It was perfectly obvious that your devoutness would fall into "a later mind" as is
               written after thus inconsiderately beginning the solitary life; and this after many
               arguments had often been discussed between you and <pb n="443"/> me, and scriptural
               principles and patristic admonitions; which the God-clad doctors of the holy church
               left to us, directing every man in every order and kind of life known to the gospel
               to the royal road, and handing down the advice that we should beware of turning aside
               to the right or to the left, as the divine scripture says. However, as you have in
               fervour betaken yourself to such a garb and mode of life, you need another
               exposition. Before attaching yourself to Jesus and taking up the cross you were
               yourself free to consider what mode of life was best for you to choose. But, as. you
               have gone up to the hill of philosophy, do not any: more return to the land of Sodom,
               lest you be fixed as a pillar of salt. To bury a father also was right, and in full
               accord with reasons of nature: but even this was thought a secondary matter after
               following Jesus. You should at the beginning have listened to Koheleth who says, "Let
               not thine heart be hasty to utter thy speech before God's face; since a dream cometh
               through a multitude of trials." However, since as I said we have come to this, we
               will now quote the admonition of the same Koheleth which says, "Better is it for thee
               that thou shouldst not vow than vow and not pay." This too is worthy of
               consideration: that, when Moses the great was prescribing the array of physical war
               (which however signified the nature of the spiritual array), he ordered the. rulers
               of the sons <pb n="444"/> of Israel in time of battle to cry to those that were going
               out to combat and say, "Who is the man that hath built a new house and hath not
               dedicated it? let him go and return to his house, lest he die in the war and another
               man dedicate it. And who is the man that hath planted a vineyard? And who is the man
               that hath betrothed a wife?", and things like these. If a man then, when the law gave
               him liberty to stay at home for one of these reasons, had in ready ardour taken up
               arms and hastened to join battle with the foemen, and accordingly stood even at the
               very pinnacle of danger: and afterwards had come to remember the passibility of the
               flesh, and had gone back again, would anyone be right in saying that he had not left
               the line of battle and been enrolled with deserters and traitors, because before
               going out to the combat he had permission from the law to remain within the house?
               Certainly not. Accordingly you also, who have joined battle with invisible enemies,
               and stripped yourself not against blood and flesh, but against principalities and
               powers and spirits of wickedness," must not trade upon laws which you rendered
               superfluous by taking arms: but keep the same excellent mind in which you made light
               of children and of wife, and perform true service to the "Father of the orphans and
               Judge of the widows," and He will be more truly a husband to the wife, and a father
               to the children. We must also examine the character of <pb n="445"/> times and of
               persons, and so apply the divine commandments to deeds to be done, and choose those
               that are good instead of those that are bad. For this reason among animals also some
               are clean and allowed to be eaten and hallowed for sacrifice, those whose hoof is
               parted, and those that besides this chew their food also and masticate it, and chew
               the cud as it is written. Often, when a thing a short time before appeared to be
               lawful and a matter of duty, the interposition of some small circumstance has at once
               and immediately rendered it unlawful. For instance, after the twelve men whom Moses
               sent had explored the land of promise, together with Caleb and Joshua the son of Nun
               he urged the whole congregation to go up to that land; but, when they showed fear and
               hung back and turned to contention and abuse, and after the transgression against
               God's commandment and the wrath threatened against them prayed the next day that they
               might go up, he who the day before had been urging them to go up prevented them from
               doing so, saying, "Ye shall not prosper. Go not up, for the Lord is not with you;"
               and nevertheless they went up, and they roused God to double exasperation. You too
               therefore, who put on the angelic garb of the monastic life without restraining the
               fervour that led you to this by the strict letter of the canons, have other men also
               as an example, who were fired with a fire or fervour like yours. Imitate them, and
               distin<pb n="446"/>guish yourself in the struggles of the solitary existence,
               lest, while wishing to correct a small fault, and that at an improper time, you
               forget yourself and fall into a pit of evils, and dishonour the sacred garb by
               involving yourself in worldly cares. As it is an unhallowed and profane thing for us
               to apply to human use a revered vessel that has once been set apart for the service
               of God, so also is it foul and abominable for a man who has given himself to God, and
               hallowed in some sort his own life, to turn back to the claims and judgments of the
               flesh. Say farewell therefore to the thoughts that call you to live in the world, and
               keep to the road that lies before you, until you reach, as it is written, "the goal
               of victory of the upward calling of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord." There is
               only one thing which I would have wished added to, the beginning that you have made;
               that you had joined yourself in everything, both in community of opinion concerning
               the faith and in community of habitation, to the holy fathers of the house of the
               saintly presbyter Theodore; which also you were in the beginning impelled to do and
               for which you were very eager; and I do not know how the hater of what is good
               hindered you. But it is easy for us not to be cheated by Satan to use the language of
               the divine Apostle. These things we have written while much harassed <pb n="447"/>
               with many affairs and not able even to breathe, because we are inflamed with love
               towards you, and know that we owe even more to your excellent person. Never at any
               time shall we be forgetful of the good deeds that you have shown towards us. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
