<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Caesaria the Patrician</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">448-55</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.7">
            <pb n="448"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Caesaria the patrician.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 3rd book the 46th
               letter.</head>
            <p> It seemed to me perfectly credible that, as stated by your glorious modesty, you
               gained so much profit from reading my mean letter with understanding. The good soil
               that is like your God-loving soul knows, it knows indeed, how, even when receiving
               barren seed, to give forth fruitful produce in plenty, insomuch as to reach to the
               perfect measure of a hundred. <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> As to
               the short treatise that is being circulated and carried about by certain persons,
               which you say is inscribed with my name and bears such an ascription, a treatise that
               I shrink from even taking upon my lips, seeing that it is full of ignorance and
               stupidity, know that it is not the work of our meanness at all: but a forgery either
               of certain foolish men who are called orthodox, or of heretics who wish to hide their
               shame and make it appear to those who come across it that it is we who keep men away
               from communion with them by fraudulent words, not they who separate from them by
               reason of their sound faith, and recognise and abhor their manifest impiety and
               Jewish opinions. Let not this too be unknown to your God-loving <pb n="449"/>
               highness: that a certain devout presbyter also came from the East, and showed us
               other letters also purporting to be mine, that are in part forged and falsified; the
               forgery and garbling having been done by certain persons whose business it is to
               forge such things to their own destruction as the Apostle says. And we brought him
               the documents themselves: and after comparing the genuine documents he reprobated and
               condemned the falsehood, and cursed the wicked men who commit such wanton wickedness
               against the truth. And no wonder if the devil through his own instruments wrought
               such things against us the sinner and weakling, considering that in the same way he
               contrived similar things or even more serious against the apostolic doctors of the
               church also. The great Basil in the letter addressed to the ascetics and solitaries
               under him, at Orobiane and at Chalane, asserts that certain persons were circulating
               forged and spurious letters against him: as to whom he also says; "Many letters are
               being circulated against me, which contain abuse and derision and speak evil of us in
               respect of the actions: for which we have a defence ready before the court of truth":
               and again; "My words shall judge me: but for the offences of others no man shall
               condemn us." Moreover in another letter also, writing to those at Neocaesarea, he
               showed that certain persons were also inventing dreams against him, thinking by this
               also to cast aspersions upon his <pb n="450"/> faith: about whom even while laughing
               at their absurdity he says, "Men who acted so shamelessly against us as even to
               invent certain dreams against us, bringing charges against our teachings as hurtful."
               But,.since I do not read negligently anything that is written to me by your believing
               excellency, but do so with much consideration and diligently, I think it to be
               necessary for us to give you some short answer on another matter also. You besought
               me to pray on behalf of your modesty that the Lord would release you from the bonds
               of this world, and would bring you to the calm haven of penitence, seeing that you
               are buried as you say in the evils of this world. Do not forget therefore, you whom I
               revere above everyone, that the apostle Paul in his epistle to Titus lays down a law
               for women that are yoked in marriage in these terms; "Let the young women be lovers
               of their husbands, lovers of their children, chaste, pure, good housekeepers, subject
               to their husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed." It is therefore manifest
               that, if anyone depart from the canon of this statute, and be carried though but a
               little to the right side or the left, he will be judged as a transgressor against the
               law. A woman who fears God and obeys Christ's commands must practise love of her
               husband as readily as the love of God itself. If the husband is the head of the wife
               in the same fashion as the Lord is the head of the church, a woman who loves her
               husband chastely <pb n="451"/> through the medium of her husband loves Christ the
               Head of all heads. On the same principle also a woman who keeps her house, and keeps
               the things within the house with strenuousness and watchfulness, imitates a man who
               presides over a church and wisely administers the sacred things on the care of those
               that are in need. That every believer's house also is a church the same Paul further
               bears witness when in greeting certain believers in his epistles he says, "Greet also
               the church that is in your house." One may fitly admire the way in which the Apostle,
               after saying that women who love God ought to be such as keep their houses,
               immediately added "good housekeepers." For there are women who from their great
               carefulness in housekeeping are induced to make profit out of the goods, and are
               hence incited to covetousness, the mother of evil deeds. Wherefore, to cut away such
               a vice, he said that such women ought to be good, in order that by the justification
               and consolation of those that are in need the house also may be increased; seeing
               that the blessings that are from heaven will be measured to them in return, and they
               will through beneficence lay down beforehand a good foundation for themselves in the
               future life. At. the same time by naming them good he also inculcates kindness to
               menservants and bondmaids, and all that are bound under the yoke of slavery. Of the
               love of a husband also and of chastity this is the criterion, not that a wife <pb
                  n="452"/> look at her personal chastity only, but how far she regards her
               husband's preservation also with watchful eyes, and makes every effort that he too
               may be content with intercourse with her only, not that he may turn himself to
               another connexion. If she herself be chaste, but do not concern herself about her
               husband falling into fornication, she has, unknown to herself, become chaste in half
               her body and in half of it defiled, in that she is transgressing against the divine
               laws. If in fact they are not two, according to our Saviour's saying, but the two are
               reckoned as making one flesh, what profit is there in the chastity of one portion,
               when the conjoined portion is led away to lasciviousness? Marriage is then
               "honourable and the bed unsullied," when the whole of it is hallowed in the whole
               body. But the whole body is husband and wife, having the same mind, and treating the
               marriage as a mystery of God, and hence making the procreation of children to be
               blessed, and from all sides bringing praise and glory, not reviling, upon the word of
               God. If you walk by these laws and know your place, and do not desire other things
               beyond the measure that is commanded, you will be an inheritor of the kingdom of
               heaven, and with the wives of those patriarchs Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and all
               that are such, you will receive the promises of immortal life: who also lived with
               men that were owners of sheepfolds (?) and lords of cattle and of much wealth and
               armed <pb n="453"/> themselves for war when the time summoned to this also, and with
               them fulfilled God's commandments perfectly. These things I have written because I
               gave my attention to the words contained in the letter of your believing soul, and I
               considered the fire of the Spirit that is in you, and I feared lest out of great
               fervour you might incautiously form some plan that is at variance with the laws of
               piety; for you know such pleas, which by the use of considerations that are rather
               upon the right side are apt to deceive the pious. The words of divine scripture that
               have been cited would even by themselves have been enough to confirm your love of God
               in acquiescence with the admonition of our meanness: but I have thought it good to
               corroborate what I have said from the teaching of the fathers also, and to plant the
               loyal disposition more firmly in you. The wise John, who was bishop of
               Constantinople, towards the end of the commentary on the Gospel of Matthew, in the
               exposition the beginning of which is "But Jesus stood before the governor wrote in
               these terms about the cunning of the devil, by which he has cheated specially fervent
               souls: "He has also a third evil trap: as for example: when he
               <sic><reg>throws</reg><orig>thows</orig></sic> an appearance of devoutness over
               a sin. 'And how has the devil succeeded so far as to cheat even in these things?'
               Hear, and beware of his counsels. Christ commanded through Paul that wife should not
               separate from husband, and they should not defraud one another, except perhaps by <pb
                  n="454"/> consent. But some women, having on the ground of a desire for continence
               separated themselves from their husbands as if they were doing some devout action,
               have thrust them down into adultery. Reflect therefore what an evil thing it is that,
               while undergoing so much toil, they should be charged with having done the greatest
               wrong and pay the utmost penalty, and thrust their spouses down into a pit of
               destruction. Other persons again by abstaining from foods under the law of fasting
               have gradually come to reject these: a thing which itself also brings heavy
               punishment. And this happens when they assign greater validity to their own thoughts
               than to the determinations of the scriptures." Therefore I beg your glorious modesty
               to turn the glances of your understanding on all sides, and hear the divine laws, and
               listen to Paul who says, "Let every man wherein he was called therein abide." Since
               God called you under the yoke of marriage, in it also maintain a loyal contest, and
               show prowess: and be one that loves her husband and loves her children and is a good
               housekeeper, in order that through these things you may at the same time be also one
               that loves God. Never on account of these things term yourself one buried in the mire
               of evils, and flee from the bonds of the world: but flee from the bonds of evil. For
               in these we are all in the same fashion bound. The divine text somewhere says, <pb
                  n="455"/> "Who will boast that he hath a pure heart? Or who will be confident of
               being pure from sins?" But we who have believed the gospel try, as far as is possible
               for men, to purify our soul through commandments: in order that God, looking upon the
               readiness of our heart as is sung in the Psalms, not upon the weakness of our nature,
               may admit us to mercy and graciousness in the day of judgment, and make us sharers in
               the kingdom of heaven, because the heavenly One became man and consorted with those
               that are on the earth, having become a man in truth and without difference and not in
               semblance. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
