<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3127">To Georgia, Daughter of Anastasia the
               Hypatissa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">455-59</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="10.8">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Georgia daughter of Anastasia the
               hypatissa.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 5th book the 22nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> Since for my part I never regard your glorious modesty's affairs with indifference,
               but with great earnestness concern myself for your salvation, as for that of a
               beloved daughter, and I look into God's deep judgments, by the evidence of actual
               facts I perceive that you are supported by great help from above, and conduct your
               life with very watchful care. For that you should have reached the flower of your age
               and not yet been yoked in marriage to your glorious parents perhaps and to the others
               who love a worldly manner seems a reason for anger as well as a matter of sorrow. But
               I regard it as a thing of <pb n="456"/> great profit and pronounce it to be so. This,
               I think, is the meaning to which the statement made by the wise Paul to the
               Corinthians also points; "If any man thinketh that he is put to shame in his virgin
               if she hath passed the flower of her age, so also ought it to be." What he says is in
               fact something like this; "What is thought by some to be a cause of shame, I mean
               that a virgin should reach an advanced time of life, this I have thought to be both
               advantageous and beneficial." Just as the fruit of a tree, when taken before the
               time, causes no pleasure by its taste, because it is without the sweetness that gives
               the pleasure, but actually hurts the teeth, by reason of its sharpness or acidity, in
               the same way also a virgin who has not yet ripened in her season so to speak, but has
               the disposition of the flesh undeveloped and too tender, hurts and does not profit
               the man who marries her: because her character is not fixed, and inasmuch as her time
               has not yet come is unstable and not constant, but rather easily excited and driven
               to childish wrath, and disturbed perhaps by melancholy and irrational gloominess. How
               is it anything but shameful that, while a wrestler does not go down into the violence
               of the arena [unless he has been thoroughly trained in wrestling, or a soldier] into
               the battle array, unless he has been thoroughly trained <pb n="457"/> in military
               matters, a virgin should be introduced into the society of marriage, and should pass
               to the headship and government of her husband's house without having been perfectly
               trained in her parents' house, or learned how she should govern a house, and in what
               way she ought to behave to each of those that are under her authority? It has often
               happened that bad men, when they have obtained women who are undeveloped and of
               unfixed character, have perverted them to their own bad model, and stamped the lines
               of their own wickedness upon their tender disposition as upon wax. Whence, when they
               have been sated and not been able [...] your modest mother in your father's glorious
               house, and through advanced age has been instructed in administrative science, and
               has been perfectly exercised in such useful exercises, and you have at the same time
               also increased the wisdom of your character, you will go to your husband's house like
               some image and statue that is perfect in beauty and not lacking in anything, and you
               will be to him "a helper like unto him"; since woman was in fact created by Him who
               said in the beginning, "It is not good that the man should be alone; let us make him
               a helper like unto him." A woman who is trained and skilled in governing a house, and
               intelligent and a real helper in the world's difficulties, is in truth a <pb n="458"
               /> haven fora man. For in fact, when a man has gone out to [...] in a law-court,
               either because he is doing or because he is suffering wrong, or again he is often
               inflamed to anger, and wantonly insults or on the contrary is insulted in his turn,
               the anger of another blowing against him like some storm. But, when the time calls
               and he returns to his house for food, agitated and disturbed by anxieties, he
               encounters his wife's intelligence: he finds her temper both placid and calm: he
               tells what has happened to him in the street. Then she like a trained physician
               gently looks into the hidden sources of trouble: she touches his heart with
               intelligent words, and learns the causes. And, when she has found that he has been
               excited without good reason, she appeases the fury of his mind by offering peaceful
               [...] that I have written these things also. And I beg you, lady, not to tell anyone
               whatever that you have received this letter from me, even if he be an angel from
               heaven. You will in fact both bring danger upon me by telling it and vex God; and you
               will make many angry with me, because I did not write to them too just as I have done
               to you. But we believe that Christ, the God of orthodoxy, who every day carries out
               the words that say, "Other sheep also <pb n="459"/> I have which are not of this
               fold; and I must bring them also and they shall hear my voice, and they shall be one
               flock and one Shepherd," will make your glorious and exalted father also His own. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
