<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Misael the Chamberlain</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">459-63</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="11.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Misael the chamberlain.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               100th letter.</head>
            <p> How can I express my admiration of the labours of your magnificence which you
               display towards my meanness in the way that they deserve, seeing that I have one
               mouth and one tongue? Still however, since you do not care about praises upon earth,
               but make it your one and only endeavour that through good works your name may be
               written in the book of life, I pray as a sinner that this grace may be abundantly
               bestowed upon you by God the bestower of gifts that are so great. For by your
               faithful care you have delivered our church that was in a pitiful condition through
               the hostile contrivances of the illustrious Aegilas from a heavy burden. <pb n="460"
               /> But it wounds me deeply that, because your soul has been smitten with divine love,
               it should conceive the idea of adopting the philosophic and solitary life, though it
               is living in a philosophic manner and has within that which it seeks as if it were at
               a distance. By God's grace, while you conduct yourself in so chaste and ascetic a
               fashion, you have this privilege also that has been bestowed from above, I mean not
               only to believe on Christ, but also to suffer for His sake, and endure distress with
               Israel when in turmoil; whence also the illustrious crown of martyrdom is being woven
               for you. By desiring retreat or solitariness at a time so unsuited for it you are
               doing the same as if one of those three boys, of one of whom you are namesake, when
               the golden image of Nebuchadnezzar the fighter against God was set forth, and he was
               required to stand up and confute the error, had fled and withdrawn, thinking to win
               safety for himself, and not bow his head to the abominable and unlawful object of
               worship. In. that case they would not have obtained such glory with God as that which
               they gained by undergoing the trial of the furnace, and quenching the fire by their
               virtue, and gaining God as a witness to their modest and humble mind by saying, "Our
               God is in heaven whom we serve, one that is able to deliver us from the burning
               furnace of fire; and if not be it known unto thee, O king, that we do not serve thy
               gods, and the golden image <pb n="461"/> which thou hast set up we do not worship";
               in order that these words might be an instruction and a pattern in piety to all in
               later times too who should love God. How then can you, when the king is pious, flee
               from the fight with the heretics, instigated as you are by a God-loving thought, and
               refusing to endure their blasphemies, and looking at this only, and reckoning our
               nakedness as nothing? If this is carried into effect, you will now double for me
               personally the grief that I felt by reason of the departure of Peter the presbyter?
               who is among the saints, and will throw me "fall after fall," as the great Job
               somewhere says: and then I shall know clearly from facts themselves that God has
               utterly abandoned us, and has turned away His face from those that praise Him in the
               right way: and we will say as is written "to the mountains, 'Fall upon us,' and to
               the hills, 'Cover us.'" I forbear to say that neither will you obtain that desire,
               seeing it will not be in accordance with God's judgment that you will be abandoning
               the life in the world. Further also a story like this has been conveyed to us by
               those who have grown old in asceticism. In the times of the Arians, two men who lived
               in the philosophic manner remained in the desert, and in the unsocial life. And, when
               the word of truth was being attacked, and was being obscured by heretical craftiness
               of speech, and they were called to give help (for they had in fact qualifications for
               fighting on behalf of piety), they were <pb n="462"/> disinclined to do so, because
               they clung to philosophy, and action seemed to them irksome. And the one put
               constraint upon himself, and showed more respect to the commandment than to the peace
               that he loved, and hastily set off to take part in the contests, and obeyed those who
               called him. But the other remained according to his pleasure in the desert, and the
               spirits of evil came and assailed him with greater vehemence, and he became possessed
               of the feeling that he had been stripped of God's grace and help, and was in danger
               of being devoured by fiends as it were by lions; and he was awakened and reflected
               upon his thoughtlessness, and he changed his mind and immediately followed his
               brother's good resolution, and took a hand with him in the contests on behalf of the
               faith. I say nothing of Obadiah who served under Ahab the grievous tyrant, and
               secretly fed a hundred prophets in a cave, contrary to the pleasure of the holder of
               power. I also pass over the selling of Joseph, and the bondage to the Egyptian woman
               and her false charge, and the other stories: since not only have you heard the sacred
               writings, but you are in fact well-versed in them. Wherefore these things too we have
               written as a mere admonition only so to speak, by which we urge you, inasmuch as you
               live not to yourself but to God, immediately to say what has been written and has
               been handed down by our Lord as a teacher, "Nevertheless not as I will but as thou
               wilt." <pb n="463"/> It is in truth a great sin for us to desert Christ when He needs
               help. Such a man acts in the same way as a man who is rich and quickly passes by one
               who is hungry, and one who is naked or sick, or shut up in prison; for the need of
               all these Christ makes His own. Wherefore also He bitterly inveighs against the crime
               and holds it up to reprobation before the theatre of the world or rather before all
               rational nature, saying, "Inasmuch as ye did it not to one of these little ones,
               neither did ye it to me." May we all escape having experience of these words! </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
