<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3006">To the Patricians</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">199-203</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="2.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the patricians.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 3rd book the 5th
               letter.</head>
            <p> As the brightness of the stars brings comfort to those who in the depth of night
               raise their looks towards heaven, so it is good for us also, whose <pb n="200"/>
               mind's eye is darkened by the darkness of sorrow, to look towards you the rational
               stars of the sacred Senate. If we are allowed to enjoy your genial splendour, all the
               cloud: of despondency will pass away, and we shall certainly see the sun also which
               is surrounded by you shining gently upon us as at hot noonday. It has come to the
               ears of our worthlessness that our pious Christ-loving king believed that some of us
               without having priestly rank are officiating as priests with profane hands and
               handling the sacraments, Such reports it is the practice of slanderers to put forth
               about us: who, being unable to accuse the orthodoxy of our faith for which we were
               persecuted, betake themselves to such unholy futilities. But our acts are known to
               everyone, even if we ourselves keep silent. Although we are sinners, yet we are not
               unversed in the divine scriptures, nor have we an uninstructed mind with regard to
               them (I forbear to say that we make these our meditation by night and by day, as we
               are commanded?). Trying therefore as we do to direct our own life by them, we know
               that all who coveted the priestly functions without being in the position of priests
               suffered sudden death. Such were Dathan and Abiram and the company of Korah: who
               wished to usurp the high-priestly office of Moses and Aaron, and dared to burn
               incense, and the earth opened and swallowed some of them up, <pb n="201"/> while
               others were consumed by the strange fire. Another man, because he presumed to touch
               the sacred ark with profane hand when it leaned over and was about to be dashed to
               the ground, was immediately struck lifeless. And what of Uzziah the king? Is it not
               the fact that, because he inconsiderately dared to be called a priest, he was smitten
               with the scab of leprosy between his eyes before he passed the sacred barrier or
               veil, and was thenceforth ashamed even to reign? How then could we who through mercy
               devote ourselves to the study of such teachings, and so know that there was power
               even in the legal shadowy service, have presumed to officiate as priests with
               unconsecrated hands at the heavenly sacrifice, which even to angels is inaccessible,
               but out of benignance has been made accessible to the priests only, because they
               typify Christ? For it is in truth He who down to the present time offers Himself
               every day on our behalf to God and the Father. Those who minister in the new
               covenant? do not offer any new 'sacrifice upon the altar, but celebrate the memory of
               that one, in which Christ, God the Word the high-priest, the priesthood, the new and
               glorious victim, and noble oblation preparative for immortal life, offered Himself.
               In fact the wise Paul also in his epistle to the Hebrews says of Christ, "By one
               offering He hath perfected them that are sanctified:" and again, "So also Christ,
               having been once offered to bear the sins <pb n="202"/> of many, shall appear a
               second time without sin, to those who look for Him for salvation through faith." That
               Christ's mystery is inaccessible even to the sublime hosts Isaiah the loud trumpet of
               the prophets bears witness who said that one of the suprasensual and immaterial hosts
               of the seraphs took a coal with the tongs and not in his hand, and laid it on his
               lips and said, "This shall purge thy sins." That the coal signifies the one Christ
               made out of two elements, of the Godhead I mean and of the manhood which are each
               perfect, undoubtedly does not escape your God-loving excellencies. Holding therefore
               to such right principles, in order to cause perfect confidence in what we say, we lay
               ourselves under the direst curse, to fall from the glory of the Holy Trinity and not
               attain to the hope promised to Christians, if we are conscious in ourselves that any
               such presumptuous deed has been committed by our fathers or is being committed. If
               anyone presumes to lay hands upon the priesthood without having received the sacred
               ordination lawfully and in accordance with the apostolic canons, let him be anathema,
               and let him be ranked with men that rob a sanctuary and lie in wait at altars. The
               other slander also we cast from us and assert that no one who has been admitted to
               the clergy in the churches has been re-ordained among us. Wherefore we even place
               under anathema the man who re-ordains these <pb n="203"/> or says that they must be
               re-ordained. But, if anyone after he has been admitted to the clergy has turned his
               eye towards the solitary mode of life, and, being trained in the toilsome exercises
               of philosophy, and desiring to know how to bear contempt for Christ's sake, has
               debarred himself for a time from the ministry, this is not re-ordination (far be
               it!), but a philosophic and divine exercise which renders the priest more worthy of
               reverence. It is in fact the custom of our fathers to look to the soul's profit only,
               and, when men have once taken upon themselves to practise philosophy, whether they be
               priests or whether they be kings, to lead them on through the performance of humble
               services, in order that by trampling upon pride they may imitate Him who humbled
               Himself for our salvation and became flesh and took the form of a slave. For the
               correct definition of philosophy is this, that a man imitate God as much as possible.
               Therefore, now that you know these things, we beg your glorious noble eminences to
               convey them to the ears of our Christ-loving triumphant king. For it is not just
               that, when we are near and able to give satisfactory answers to the slanders against
               us, that we should be condemned by default as if we were absent. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
