<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3096">To John and John, the Presbyters</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">204-07</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="2.2">
            <pb n="204"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John and John the presbyters.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 1st book the 6th
               letter.</head>
            <p> Your holinesses' letter, which was brought me by Zenobius the devout deacon, has
               refreshed me greatly, and has been to me, as in the words of the proverb, "as cool
               water that relieveth a thirsty soul." <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add>
               As to what you say about those who are residing in Byzantium, the report that has
               been received is true, that they contended about precedence. In fact at an earlier
               time also they discussed this doubtful point, and the proper regulation was given.
               Now however, when they are outside the phantasy of worldly sleep, they ought not to
               have contended as with a shadow and seen dreams. But may the hateful passion of
               jealousy and envy perish from among men, a passion that goes down with a man even to
               Hades itself and is a thing unendurable! For this reason the God-inspired scripture
               says, "Wrath is merciless and anger sharp, but nothing endureth jealousy." For both
               the merciless wrath and the sharp anger eat away and destroy those against whom they
               are whetted: but still it is sometimes possible for us to assuage them and turn them
               aside, by lapse of time and by methods of treatment and by gifts. But jealousy there
               is nothing than can endure. This passion knows one relief, the destruction of the man
               <pb n="205"/> who is its object, and his ruin: and in the same fashion also the
               death of the man himself who is jealous: especially that of the soul before that of
               the body. For the very wise book of Job says, "Jealousy slayeth him that is in
               error." Such annoyances I received from the two aforesaid men: and He who came down
               from on high and humbled Himself for our sake and said,: "My peace I give unto you,
               my tranquillity leave unto you," breathed upon them and extinguished their gall, and
               even caused them wholly to disappear. Do not wonder if these strove about precedence.
               Such things indeed happened even in former times. When in old days Helladius
               succeeded to the see of the men of Caesarea after the great and renowned Basil, a man
               who lived a virtuous life and was worthy of such a succession, and was one of the
               Holy men of the synod of the hundred and fifty, Cappadocia having been divided into
               two, Theodore, a man praiseworthy both for faith and for character, was bishop of the
               other metropolis (this was Tyana): and under him among others was Bosporius, a good
               man and one who had reached such a high standard of holiness that even his grave
               performs miracles down to the present day. But, though they were both of such a
               character and so highly exalted in virtue, they strove with one another about some
               contemptible claim of right in their parish, and fell into great and long rivalry:
               and they had the two Gregories, he of Nyssa siding with Helladius and <pb n="206"/>
               he of Nazianzus with Theodore, and Bosporius the renowned, divided in sympathies, and
               like armed men bringing help to the generals when they engaged in battle, and writing
               letters in opposition to one another. If then those towers of the church and men of
               heavenly minds were convicted of sometimes walking upon earth, what will a man say of
               ourselves the gnats, who are ever flying over the sores and mire of passions and
               feeding on them? Nor yet at this must one wonder, mean that one of the very men who
               have been mentioned now uses humble words, saying, "It is against the things done at
               Chalcedon, not against the actual synod itself, that we must put forth a sentence and
               anathema." For Liberius, the bishop of Rome, resisted Constantius even to blood, on
               behalf of Athanasius the apostolic preacher of the orthodox faith, and went out to
               the figurative stadium, and readily allowed himself to be carried into exile: and at
               last, bent by the long continuance of the sojourn in the place of exile, he gave way,
               and yielded to the violence of the time. Hosius also the bishop of Corduba (a little
               city so named), who had always been arrayed on the side of the orthodox, owing to his
               extreme old age and advanced time of life, was overcome at Nice in Thrace, and
               submitted to compulsion. And Athanasius the champion of the truth in word and in
               deed, a man of practised skill in doing service, who discharges the rational shafts
               against enemies with understanding, <pb n="207"/> both in epistles and in treatises
               against the Ariomanita: calls Hosius "of honourable old age," and mentions him with
               distinction: while in respect of the contests undergone by Liberius he praises and
               extols the man; saying not a word of what happened to them under violence, but like a
               wise man passing rapidly over it with closed eyes, as the saying is. Let us also
               therefore, inasmuch as sacred contests lie before us, follow the spiritual captains,
               and in respect of actions on the right side, both be ourselves edified and edify
               others thereby, in order that the others also may be strengthened: but human actions
               let us pass rapidly over. For we are mortal and weak, and we are put under compulsion
               and led by force by spirits of wickedness. Let us pray therefore that the details of
               our weakness be not greatly exposed. But you for your part have the power of sharing
               the contest with everyone through your prayers. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
