<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3111">To the Orthodox in Emesa</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part I</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/668</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 3 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">207-229</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="2.3">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the orthodox in Emesa.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 93rd
               letter.</head>
            <p> Men often think that time is bringing them new and unwonted events. Nevertheless
               they are not such as are wholly without similar instances in times that have already
               passed. This is confirmed by Koheleth who <pb n="208"/> says, "There is nothing new
               under the sun. Many indeed have desired the priesthood in an unhallowed manner; of
               which unlawful thought an instance was provided in time past by Dathan and Abiram,
               and the company of Korah who rose against Moses and Aaron, the first priests under
               the shadowy law. A scion of this impious action and of this audacious deed is this
               also which has just been reported to me in the desert, where I am dwelling unseen for
               the sake of the common hope and substance of our salvation, which is the orthodox
               faith. I learn that a certain Gregory and Isaiah, who register their fathers' house
               the one in Pontus, the other in Armenia, have appeared in the countries of the East
               and are falsely and lyingly ascribing to themselves the great name and the functions
               of the episcopate: and it is reported that their mad practices do not extend to words
               only: but Gregory in the great distinguished Christ-loving city of the Antiochenes,
               and Isaiah in the illustrious believing metropolis of the Emesenes, have laid their
               presumptuous and illegal hand upon certain men, and by a mockery as in a play will
               create certain men ridiculous priests for filthy lucre; like those whom Jeroboam the
               rebel created, after he had led the ten tribes away from the lawful service which was
               established through Moses the great, and fashioned golden calves, and by one and the
               same creation instituted at the same time both the hateful thing and the
               falsely-named hierophants of <pb n="209"/> the creation itself. Gregory, I learn, has
               created a fraud more plausible than that of Isaiah; having in fact stated of himself
               that he is bishop of Diocaesarea which is situated in the Pontic diocese, and that he
               left his throne on account of the sound faith: which, if true, would be worthy of
               crowns, and of all praise that is warranted by the spiritual laws: and, to speak
               plainly, a thing preparative for the kingdom of heaven according to the voice of the
               Lord that cannot lie which cries in the Gospels, "Blessed are they which have been
               persecuted for righteousness' sake for theirs is the kingdom of heaven." But Isaiah's
               elaboration is, I learn, twice as abominable: and it has been so badly concocted
               that, even if the foolish tale were established, he would have no confirmation
               whatever for his position nor any plausibility. Certain men in Egypt told me that he
               says he is a bishop, but, when he alleges ordination to have been performed over him,
               he produces no evidence or proof, names no city, and says that it was performed by
               one man, and by him when he was drawing his last breath and lying dead. For, when he
               kept perversely lying and was asked for proof of what he was saying, he came down to
               this as the sum of the allegation and tripped himself up. This is in fact established
               by the sacred text which says, "He that is incautious with his lips in that he is
               perverse shall be tripped up." Who is there who is reckoned among Christians to whom
               it is not manifest that these things stand outside all <pb n="210"/> canonical order
               and the apostolic church? Indeed from the very beginning those who were disciples and
               eye-witnesses and ministers of the Word Himself divided the bishops among cities, and
               to each church as to a spiritual bride figuratively united the bishop as a
               bridegroom. A witness of this is the divine Paul who writes to Titus and says, "For
               this cause left I thee in Crete that thou shouldest set in order the things that are
               wanting, and appoint presbyters in every city as I commanded thee." Here he calls
               bishops presbyters: for indeed after saying, "In order that thou shouldest appoint
               presbyters in every city," he went on further to say, "For the bishop must be
               blameless, as the steward of God." This the holy John also, who was bishop of
               Constantinople, interpreted in this way when he wrote as follows about Titus: "This
               man was highly approved among those who were with Paul: and, if not, he would not
               have entrusted the island to him in its entirety, nor have commanded him to supply
               the things that were wanting ('in order that thou shouldest set in order the things
               that are wanting'): he would not have entrusted him with the selection of so many
               bishops, if it had not been that he had great confidence in the man." The apostles
               also divided the peoples by the lots of the Holy Spirit: and each of them took
               possession of the inheritance that was given to him, and was contented with it: and
               the gift of it was made to him by inspira<pb n="211"/>tion from above. This gift the
               singing prophet compared to the wings of a dove that are covered with silver and her
               feathers superbly decorated with gold; and he foretold that this grace would be given
               them openly and in actual deeds, in that he addresses his words to them thus, "If ye
               lie among the lots, there there are the wings of a dove that are covered with silver,
               and her feathers with the yellowness of gold": the words manifestly showing this,
               that, if each apostle had not been satisfied with the lot that fell to him and shown
               regard for order, the Holy Spirit would not have bountifully bestowed upon them
               illustrious powers of working signs and wonders, and teaching that shone after the
               fashion of silver, and the steadfastness in sufferings which gold shows when tried in
               the fire of the furnace. But the excellent Isaiah does not fear to give himself out
               as holding a bishopric not obtained by lot and irregular and without a city. Who has
               seen a marriage-chamber of an unnamed bride, and a foul bridegroom without a consort,
               or rather one who becomes everything to himself, as the nature of his fiction
               requires? I hear that those who after the fashion of some brute beast have adhered to
               his error, three or four wicked creatures, bring forward a canon also to substantiate
               their fraud which is without substance and full of all absurdity. This they also say
               is a canon of Simon the Cananaean, and it has never prevailed in the holy churches
               and been accepted by holy <pb n="212"/> synods, or been named in them at all. How
               could it have been, when the holy canons once for all enact that the ordination of a
               bishop must not be performed under any other conditions by him who has the right to
               ordain except when all the bishops of the same province take part in the solemn
               function, or, if they are not all present, at any rate there shall be no smaller
               number than three, and the others also shall give their <foreign>psephisma</foreign>
               by their letters, even if they are absent in body? For in ecclesiastical regulations
               enactments carefully made at a later time in the churches allow no play to those of
               ancient date. For. example Cyprian the divine among bishops, who adorned the chief
               throne of Africa with all excellencies, but above all with a crown of martyrdom, once
               assembled a synod of the saintly bishops under him and ruled that converts from
               heresy must not be accepted, unless they have received the baptism given by the
               orthodox. And in modern times, now that the high-priests who fed the churches in the
               West and in the East, as well as the great and holy synod of the three hundred and
               eighteen, have discussed the quality of heresies, and enacted that we ought not in
               the case of all of them to accept penitents through baptism, no one presumes contrary
               to this conclusion to apply baptism to those who come from all heresies, as seemed
               right at an earlier time to Cyprian: but, if anyone contrary to the law which has
               prevailed shall <pb n="213"/> presume to re-baptize, he will fall within the grasp of
               the canons as having performed unlawful actions. The bishop also of the city renowned
               for its orthodox faith of the city of the Alexandrines was in old times appointed by
               presbyters. But in modern times, in accordance with the canon which has prevailed
               everywhere, the solemn institution of their bishop is performed by bishops: and no
               one makes light of the accurate practice that prevails in the holy churches and
               recurs to the earlier condition of things, which has given way to the later clear and
               accurate, deliberate and spiritual injunctions." However, if agreeable, we will also
               adduce the canon that is given out as having been enacted by Simon the Cananaean, in
               order that everyone may learn that Isaiah's partners in the idle 'fiction are
               stirring up destruction against themselves, as the common saying is. It is said to be
               as follows: "I also, Simon the Cananaean, command you by how many the bishop ought to
               be ordained. A bishop should be ordained by two or by three bishops. But, if anyone
               be ordained by one bishop, let both him and the man who ordained him be deprived.
               But, if necessity arise for him to be ordained by one, since a large number cannot
               come, because there is a persecution or some other cause, let him bring a
                  <foreign>psephisma</foreign> of authority from several bishops." Where then are we
               to place the fictitious ordination of Isaiah, <pb n="214"/> which passes all
               plausibility? Who are the bishops who confirmed for him the ordination that was
               performed by one as he says? or where are those who made the
                  <foreign>psephisma</foreign> about him? It is known to everyone that the apostles
               made all their enactments through the Holy Spirit, and saw the future like the
               present through the illumination of the heavenly light from above. Therefore it seems
               that Isaiah's ordination escaped the notice of Simon the Cananaean, and the fact that
               it alone was to be devoid of bishops to make a <foreign>psephisma</foreign> about
               him, and to confirm that which was lame and imperfect. This is an absurdity, and a
               piece of silly trifling: nay rather it is a fit subject for sorrow, and fraught with
               tears. For how will even the spirits of the saints refrain from sighing when they see
               the high priesthood, which is awful even in the sight of the heavenly powers
               themselves, turned into a mockery? For of such a kind are the mysteries to which we
               summon, which, as Peter the chosen one of the apostles wrote, even "the angels desire
               to look into." What need is there of many words, when the very devices of Isaiah the
               stony man, who has taken to him all the madness of Satan, show the demon-like nature
               of the act? He has indeed refuted his impiety which he falsely reported of himself by
               means of another impiety, adding iniquity to his iniquity according to the saying of
               the Psalmist in the Psalms." For he did not even stay his presumptuous and unholy
               hand at <pb n="215"/> the name of deacons and of presbyters, but he assigns bishops
               also and archbishops to peoples and to cities, after the manner of the giants of the
               fable who sprang from the earth. And "let so-and-so," he says, "be archbishop of
               Egypt: and so-and-so of Pamphylia: and another of Palestine": and, since he lacks
               instruments for such madness, I have learned that he even collects men for himself
               from the crossroads, some blind men some lepers, some men with other bodily
               afflictions or suffering from disease. When I say this, I do not put forward the
               infirmities of the body as something shameful (the one real sickness and disease is
               the sin of the soul and falling away on our part from God), but I am desirous of
               showing the folly of the lunatic, how he is eager to lay his unholy and
               all-presumptuous hand even upon irrational things, if one may so speak, if the
               fatuity of men fail him. The holy Basil also in his letters mentions such roving
               pseudo-bishops as having been foolishly instituted by the foolish Apollinaris,
               writing thus: "Is not the great mystery of religion. made a laughingstock, in that
               bishops are going about without people and clergy, carrying about the bare name only,
               and doing no such right action as tends to the extension of the gospel of our
               salvation?"; so the spirit of error, which uttered much nonsense in Apollinaris and
               in the heretics who resemble him, but was deaf and dumb, as the Gospel says," was in
               Isaiah <pb n="216"/> and knew how to do uncanonical acts. Many other things might be
               said to refute the illegal fraud and this irrational madness. But, since the
               greatness of the unseemly and unstable abomination reaches to absurdity, it is a very
               superfluous thing to extend the discussion unnecessarily. What synod of saintly
               orthodox bishops has accepted this? Who has not closed his ears and refused to endure
               even so much as the bare mention of this unlawful report? In what other country did
               not the gentle Isaiah deceive, or to what place did he not betake himself, as we may
               hear those that know relate? Did he not move his erring steps to Egypt seeing that he
               has no stability, but as Jeremiah the prophet says loved to move his feet'? did he
               not betake himself to Pamphylia, boasting and lying and saying that he was called to
               this illegal episcopate by Leontius the saintly old hermit, who practised the
               philosophic life in the wilderness? for on the contrary he was actually anathematized
               by him by word of mouth, as all who dwell in that country testify. Did he not also
               come to the great Christ-loving city of Alexander, having been driven to it, like
               some ship without a helmsman, by the stormy waves of error; and, after he had been
               rejected by all, form the plan, as he in fact said, of confirming the fiction
               regarding him by supposed signs, and setting himself to imitate Christ, and fast
               forty days continuously, in order to raise a dead boy who lay like meat that has been
               dried <pb n="217"/> and thrown into an earthenware vessel; but, when the greater part
               of the forty days had passed, he was sorely tried by the lack of food, which was
               broken by bread taken by stealth, though he hypocritically pretended not to have
               tasted anything; while the dead boy's father was beginning to mourn and weep at
               having been disappointed of his hope, and was crying aloud and wailing bitterly and
               after the manner of a rustic (he was a gardener); but the body having become putrid
               filled the house with noisome corruption and a deadly smell, so that the pretended
               bishop, simulated faster, and false miracle-worker was in danger of being delivered
               to the fire, seeing that his hateful conduct had been exposed, if it had not been
               that he hid himself and escaped from the hands of those who sought to inflict a just
               vengeance upon him for the drunkenness of his mind? Is inquiry therefore needed in
               the case of such men, who from the declaration of our Saviour himself have the
               confutation which plainly says of false shepherds like them, "By their fruits ye
               shall know them"? If "the less is blessed by the greater," as the wise Paul says, let
               us examine as a proposition who it was who gave Isaiah the fictitious ordination. Was
               it one who has the right of ordaining bishops and, being a metropolitan, knows also
               the prayer for the appointment of high-priests? or, if as a concession we grant this
               point also, how does a bishop of a metropolis give a man who is ordained by him
               authority to institute <pb n="218"/> archbishops among peoples and cities; as in
               fables and dreams? If, as he says, bishop Epiphanius of saintly memory was actually
               drawing his last breath and giving up the ghost, a man who was not bishop of a
               metropolis, but of one of the cities under a metropolis, and gave him the hand of
               ordination at the moment of death, and never finished the ordination such as it was,
               what are we to say of such a prayer? and how is it not a matter for tears, if Paul in
               speaking to the Corinthians about all prayer says, "I will pray with my spirit, I
               will pray also with my understanding," while Isaiah's institutor uttered the prayer
               which is, if one may so say, higher and more solemn than all prayers, I mean that
               which institutes high-priests, with faltering tongue and indistinct and feeble voice,
               when he had not even ordinary intelligent consciousness, and heard it repeated from a
               book like a small boy who goes to school, and each word was pronounced and lisped to
               him by those standing round him, since they elaborate this also as part and parcel of
               the snare and fraud? All the details of this elaborate play and of the case show
               weakness and lack of substance, but set the saintly bishop Epiphanius free from
               calumny, who departed blamelessly to the Lord, and, when he stands before the
               judgement-seat that does not respect persons on the last day, will have no knowledge
               of what the prayer of the ordination of a bishop is, and by the sentence of the just
               Judge will send those who calumniate him to the fire that is <pb n="219"/> not
               quenched, and the wicked Isaiah to the outer darkness, with those that are "clad in
               strange apparel," as one of the prophets said. Why should one repeat the whole story?
               It has been told me that he has reached such a height of madness as even to entitle
               himself "high-priest of high-priests," and even "apostle" also, and thereby to show
               everyone that he has received the evil spirit of Montanus and of Mani. For in fact
               those also named themselves apostles, and presumed to exalt themselves to the title
               of Paraclete which cannot be shared by any creature, and fitly belongs to Christ only
               and to the Holy Spirit; imitating Satan the chief of the rebel host, who in ancient
               times said, "I will exalt myself to heaven, and above the stars of heaven will I set
               my throne," and is also expected through Antichrist, as Paul the speaker of divine
               things foretold, "to sit in the temple of God and make it appear concerning himself
               that he is God." And yet, after those stupid unlearned advocates of the error have
               gone through all these things which show the artificial nature of the fiction, they
               presume, hear, to cite, as if the imaginary ordination of Isaiah were valid, the
               action that was taken in the case of Gregory the Miracle-worker, I mean how Phaedimus
               who ordained this man hunted him by the power of prayer when he was fleeing from the
               burden of the bishopric, and when absent and at a distance uttered a prayer, so that
               even when absent he was involved in the chains of prayer, and <pb n="220"/> was
               caught in the nets of the Spirit from which there is no escape, and hastened to him
               who was lawfully pursuing him, and thus underwent and received all the legal
               requirements of ordination, and did not stop at the prayer made at a distance, as is
               thought by the men who are bereft of intelligence and do not understand what they
               read. A witness of this is Gregory, who wrote his history, the brother in blood and
               in the Spirit and in the office of the high-priesthood of the great Basil, and bishop
               of Nyssa, who wrote as follows: "For this reason Phaedimus having been by some
               specially divine impulse roused to the task before him, paying no regard to the
               intervening space by which he was separated from Gregory (seeing he was three days
               journey distant from him), but, looking to God and saying that he himself was seen by
               God at that hour in the same way as he was, in place of a hand applies the spoken
               word to Gregory, dedicating to God a man who was absent in body, and allotting him to
               a city which down to those times had, it so happened, been held in the error of
               idols, so that, while those who dwelt in the city itself and in its neighbourhood
               were without number, there were not found more than seventeen who had received the
               word of faith, Having thus therefore received the yoke by force, and all the legal
               requirements having afterwards been performed over him, and having asked the man who
               proclaimed the priesthood over him for a short time to reflect upon the exact
               character of the mystery, he no longer thought it right for him, as the Apostle <pb
                  n="221"/> said, to 'attend to blood and flesh,' but asked God that a revelation of
               the secrets might be made to him." You see he has clearly shown that the prayer made
               at a distance only stopped his course of flight, but all the legal requirements were
               performed over him after he had hastened to him who consecrated him, and nothing
               whatever was lacking. At the same time it has certainly been admitted that, since
               Phaedimus was head of the-metropolis of the men of Amasia, that he had his bishops
               close by him, and with them pursued Gregory. For, when he pursued, he pursued
               promptly: so that, when he had caught the quarry, he immediately performed the
               ordination. Accordingly he had the bishops standing round him, and taking part with
               him in the prayer also that was made over the divine Gregory at a distance. But it
               seems ridiculous for us to pass beyond the proper limits in considering the silly
               arguments of those deceivers, and to go on to refute arguments that are feeble and
               have no substance, which some intelligent and devout hermits repeated to me in Egypt
               as having been invented by one of Isaiah's deceivers. To these I also said, "The
               saintly bishop Epiphanius we ourselves committed to the grave in our monastery in
               Palestine: and of these follies and futilities we have a clear written refutation.
               For indeed at the very end of his life he made a will, in which he appointed count
               Eusebius the Alexandrine of magnificent <pb n="222"/> memory, who was called
               'Eleonos,' who was living at that time his heir, because he knew that the man had
               spent all his property on the poor, ordering that what was left by him also should be
               distributed to the needy in an exactly similar manner: and Isaiah was to have charge
               of the distribution of it, who was then educating the sons of the magnificent
               Eusebius, who were being brought up in the monastic fashion. And the man who made
               these provisions at the actual very gate of departure from the world named Isaiah
               'presbyter,' thereby leaving a written confutation of the dead calumny. For, if he
               had had the intention of ordaining him bishop after the will, he would not yesterday
               have named a man in writing 'presbyter,' whom to-morrow he was going to make an
               unrecorded and unnamed bishop. This is manifestly foolishness. But let the reproof be
               turned against the head of those who invented the fraud." They, having heard these
               things and been delighted at what was said, said to me, "One of us was invited by
               Isaiah through a certain intermediary to become archbishop of Egypt. However all we
               Egyptians made answer with one consent, 'We for our part do not inquire into this
               foolish tale of Isaiah's ordination: but we hold to the canon of the holy and great
               synod of the three hundred and eighteen fathers, knowing an ordination that is
               performed by one bishop to be void and illegal.'" To this I made answer and said:
               "Let <pb n="223"/> your devoutnesses know that at a later time also, when Paulinus,
               being patriarch of the city of the Antiochenes, himself alone at the end of his life
               ordained Evagrius and appointed him his successor, while the orthodox bishops in the
               East lawfully ordained Flavian archbishop of the same Antioch, a synod was assembled
               to deal with this case: in the West in the city of Capua: and in the East at Caesarea
               in Palestine: because Siricius, who was then archbishop of Rome, had decided that
               after the discussion at Capua the task of making a more careful investigation of the
               actual facts of the case should be transferred to the East, Theophilus, the
               archbishop of the great city of the Alexandrines, having been invited to preside over
               those who were assembled: who owing to the overthrow of the heathen temples and of
               the images in Alexander's city had his time occupied and failed to join in assembly
               with them. And then the synod of saintly bishops which was assembled at Caesaria in
               Palestine reported its decree to the God-loving kings of pious memory, Theodosius,
               Arcadius, and Honorius, and made it known to them in these words: 'For we have read
               the letter of our reverend brothers to our reverend brother and bishop? Theophilus,
               and that which was written to ourselves the bishops of the East by the bishops at
               Capua, and that of the religious Siricius the bishop of Rome, to the effect that
               before all things we must <pb n="224"/> look to this point, <foreign>i.e.</foreign>
               not to disturb the canon of Nicaea which clearly lays down that it is not permissible
               for the ordination of a bishop to be performed by one only. There was further
               inserted in the letter of the religious bishop Siricius a decision also upon the
               hearing that was to be held: in which was inserted the statement "there must be one
               bishop of Antioch, he who has been legally and ecclesiastically appointed according
               to the canon of the Synod of Nicaea"; and which clearly decreed that an ordination
               performed by one is illegal and not to be accepted. With joy therefore we have
               received the accurate teaching of bishop Siricius concerning the church canons, and,
               following this letter, we have decreed that these things be ratified: in that we have
               given legal and just votes, to the effect that we know one bishop of Antioch only the
               religious lord Flavian the bishop.'" After I had given vent to these words, the
               devout old men and Egyptian monks to whom I was speaking added that the advocate of
               Isaiah's deception who promised them the archbishopric of Egypt used to say that the
               holy Timothy also, the archbishop of the city of the Alexandrines, was ordained by
               two bishops only, not by three according to the canon. And it has been shown clearly
               that Peter also the bishop, he of saintly memory, the apostolic man, who came from
               Iberia, our father, was present there, and held the gospel over Timothy's sacred
               head, and made up the number of <pb n="225"/> three bishops: he having been brought
               by force to the church by the orthodox people, and dragged from the very bed on which
               he was still lying as being an old and infirm man. But, while he was being carried
               along by violence, he in an ineffable manner heard a voice from heaven commanding him
               not to flee from the sacred service." Whence also he gladly and with much assurance?
               assisted in the ordination. Afterwards, when the institution had been thus legally
               completed, the whole synod of the God-loving bishops of the Egyptian administrative
               district after these things acknowledged and considered the saintly Timothy as
               archbishop: and again, when he was returning after exile to Alexander's city, all the
               bishops of the other districts made union with him through the Encyclical letter and
               proclaimed him archbishop. How then do those presumptuous and unlearned men presume
               to compare with those legitimate bishops the illegitimate Isaiah, who was not even
               carried in the womb at all or conceived like the abortive and imperfect offspring of
               mothers who bring forth abortions, but by the fact of wishing it only created himself
               bishop for those silly men? These things I have written not because I wish to upset a
               thing that is tottering on all sides and contains feebleness in itself, but because I
               desire none of the Statements made about him and discussed in my presence in Egypt to
               be unknown to your diligences: <pb n="226"/> since this other futility also was, as I
               heard, being advanced by that deceiver: "Some men, you know, in the churches buy
               ordinations for gold contrary to the canons. Therefore" (he says) "it is in no way
               beyond the limits of what is proper for me too to become a bishop contrary to strict
               canonical rule": and the wretched man is not ashamed of daring to confirm his illegal
               fiction by a similar illegality. Who when taken in adultery says, "I am not an
               adulterer because so-and-so also is a murderer," and, "I have not offended against
               the laws because that man also is an offender"? In the next place, in which of the
               churches of the orthodox, fellow, is it openly put forward as a law that it is right
               for some men to be ordained for gold, as you make the fictitious and illegal
               episcopate into a law, and call sin righteousness? If a man tramples in secret on
               church ordinances, he will give account to the just Judge, but he will not inflict
               any stain on the appearance of the holy churches, which is confident in its enjoyment
               of freedom from blame and reproof in all things. I forbear to say that he even
               presumed to circulate a fictitious letter as having been written by me, which makes a
               show of finding fault with the fraud concerning him, and gains the plausibility
               thence derived, but admits that the mockery of the spurious and pretended episcopate
               was carried to completion. Isaiah therefore, who has been on all points rejected as
               illegitimate and unhallowed, and has been cast out as a stinking abomination, is
               trying to force himself into your distinguished believing metropolis, though there
               also (speaking under <pb n="227"/> God's permission) he will not find an entrance.
               For the proof of your faith and loyalty has even by actual experience been
               disseminated among all men: and we know well and are confident that you are
               gloriously minded in the Lord, all you who belong to the revered clergy, who have
               respected the orthodox faith, and all you magnificent and distinguished
                  <foreign>ktetores</foreign>, who hold the first place, and all you who fill up the
               body of the church, and cleave to the sound faith. But I have thought it right and
               seemly for me and a deed consonant with the ordinances of the Spirit not to commit to
               silence that which has just come into my thoughts, but to testify beforehand to the
               delusion of error and mark it beforehand and point it out beforehand, lest, when the
               divine wrath comes upon those who are led to act in violation of the divine laws, and
               have become the prey of the devil, I find myself under condemnation for those men's
               blood. For He that speaks through Ezekiel says, "And thou man, have given thee as a
               watchman to them of the house of Israel, and thou shalt hear a word from my mouth.
               When I shall say to the sinner, 'Thou shalt surely die,' and thou speak not that the
               impious man may refrain from his way, the wicked man shall die in his wickedness, but
               his blood will I require at thine hand. But, if for thy part thou forewarn the
               impious man concerning his way that he may turn from it and he turn not from his way,
               he shall die in his impiety, and thou shalt deliver thy soul." In the same <pb
                  n="228"/> way as Isaiah Gregory also has been convicted, as have learned, in the
               great city of Alexander. For he too has been detected, and his guile exposed in the
               minutes of the records. Therefore, learning these things as you do through this mean
               letter of mine, if anyone presumes to name Gregory or Isaiah a bishop, or shall
               reckon as valid the profane ordinations performed by them, and does not reject even
               the very mention of them as being altogether abominable and unlawful, such a man
               shall be anathema, and shall be found an alien to the glory and communion of the
               Father and. of the Son and of the Holy Spirit, both in this world, and in the world
               that is to come. If anyone, despising our exile and the persecution by which we are
               persecuted for the sake of the orthodox faith, shall reckon the things written as
               nothing, he shall give account to Him who said to the holy apostles and disciples,
               "But when they persecute you in this city flee to the other"; and again, "He that
               scorneth me and receiveth not my words hath one that judgeth him; the word that I
               have spoken it shall judge him in the last day"; and again, "If they have persecuted
               me they will also persecute you"; and all the expressions that are like and similar
               to these. For, when men have such an unlawful and unholy disposition, and reduce the
               great mystery of religion to an absurdity, the sacred scripture commands us not even
               to give <pb n="229"/> them greeting, and not to receive these men in the house or
               take them under our roof, nor to have any dealings at all with them. "If any man," it
               says, "cometh unto you, and bringeth not this teaching, receive him not in the house,
               and say not to him 'Hail!': For he that saith to him 'Hail!', is partaker of his evil
               deeds." And again Paul the Apostle, "But I beseech you, my brethren, to mark them
               which cause the divisions and offences contrary to the teaching which we have
               learned, and avoid them. For such men minister not to our Lord Jesus Christ, but to
               their belly. And by mild words and blessings they deceive the hearts of the simple."
               If you observe these things, the words also that the same sacred Paul added to these
               will assuredly be fit to address to you in praise and approbation: and we will truly
               say, "For your obedience has reached the ears of all men. I rejoice therefore over
               you." For with this it is well to conclude what we have to say. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
