<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3135">To Ammonius and Epagathus</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">233-36</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="3.2">
            <pb n="233"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Amman and Epagathus.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">from those after banishment, from the 7th book the 29th
               letter.</head>
            <p> I am astonished at the extent of your admirable goodness, that after such expenses
               on my behalf, who am not worthy of anything of the kind, expenses which you have
               incurred from love of God, you have considered it right to bestow these things upon
               me even when I am at a distance in greater abundance and with greater generosity.
               <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> But I rejoiced greatly, and
               offered prayers of thanksgiving to Christ who is God and the giver of all good, who
               has willed that a male child should be born to you the Christ-loving Ammian beyond
               all human hope. Since you have submitted the choice of his name to my judgment, out
               of the abundance of faith that you possess, and make me bold by urging me to say and
               do things above the measure that belongs to me, I have judged it to be a good and
               fitting thing that he should be named John: since the holy Baptist and Forerunner
               also was born to his parents beyond hope and expectation; and I believe that through
               his intercession he will live and reach the due length of life and advanced old age.
               Indeed on the very day on which I received your welcome letter that notified <pb
                  n="234"/> his birth to me I placed it on the holy mysteries: and, when I was about
               to communicate after my custom in the divine communion (for it was a day of
               assembly), after the other lessons and the sacred song of Alleluia, I began to read
               the revered gospel: and I found the appointed lesson to be the story of the holy
               Forerunner and Baptist, and his divine martyrdom and consummation, when he was
               beheaded for the sake of God's law; and from the fact that it happened so I concluded
               that Jesus also the God of the sacred Gospels had sanctioned and approved the method
               of naming the boy which I had chosen, I beseech you not to delay even for the space
               of one day: but to seize the favourable opportunity tat has been given us by God, and
               present the boy to the God-loving father <choice>
                  <reg>Zʿura</reg>
                  <orig>Z'ura</orig>
               </choice>, for the divine laver of regeneration. But, when you enjoy such freedom
               from restraint, how can it be anything but a very unreasonable action, and such as to
               provoke Christ our Redeemer and God, to ask for the communion or oblation to be sent
               you by my meanness? Those persons to whom it is necessary to send it are those who
               are wholly deprived of divine communion: for, when the faith is one, the holy
               communion also is assuredly one, not something different and diverse, even if one of
               the offering priests have a heavenly and high, and the other a degraded and low
               character. It is not the man who offers the sacrifice, but Christ completes it
               through the words uttered by the offerer, and changes the bread into flesh and the
               cup into blood, by the power, inspiration, <pb n="235"/> and grace of His Spirit. For
               this reason too it happened once that, when a famine had extended over the whole
               land, and Elijah the prophet was living in the torrent-bed called that of Cherith, by
               God's command ravens brought him every day bread in the morning and flesh in the
               evening, the narrative signifying that, though certain men be unclean like ravens,
               they are mediators through whom the divine food is given and imparted to us, and they
               do not inflict any injurious stain on those who partake, nor does the uncleanness and
               loose character of those who administer the divine grace cause any detriment to those
               who are fed, provided of course that their faith is orthodox and sound (you are not
               unaware that the law inserts the raven among the unclean kinds of birds). Gregory the
               Theologian also, who was bishop of Nazianzus and teacher of all that is under heaven,
               in the discourse on holy baptism teaches that there is no difference whatever between
               the divine laver of regeneration performed by a priest of lax character and that
               which is given by a priest eminent for asceticism and the other virtues: explaining
               the matter by the following image and simile. As two seals, he says, of which one is
               made of pure unalloyed gold, and the other of lead, if they bear one and the same
               signet without difference in any point graven upon themselves, will both impress one
               and the same likeness upon wax without variation in any point, and <pb n="236"/> no
               one who has not seen them can discern from the wax which is the signet that was made
               by the golden seal, and which by the leaden, so, though one priest be a man of gold
               by reason of the purity of his character, and the other one that has the darkness and
               worthlessness of lead by reason of the remissness of his life, so long as they
               possess the one seal of the orthodox faith alike in all points, and in no way
               adulterated by heretical doctrine, both perform one baptism and one oblation, of the
               same power and glory, and nothing inferior in any point whatever. Therefore your
               intelligences in the Lord must with all assurance approach the divine communion of
               the saintly bishops who are living among you and of the God-loving presbyters who
               confess the same faith as we in all points and proclaim it with boldness, and do not
               shrink from fear, nor craftily adulterate it, as the Apostle says: for men such as
               these one ought to shun as manifest heretics. But, to speak with God's permission,
               you have plenty both of bishops and of presbyters that are genuine and have no
               adulteration about them. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
