<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3136">To Misael the Deacon</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">236-44</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="3.3">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Misael the deacon.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 7th book the 30th
               letter.</head>
            <p> Those who wish and desire to receive tokens of affection in God avoid under all
               circumstances receiving <pb n="237"/> such outside the scope of the divine laws or
               obtaining gratification beyond what these wish as something grievous: among whom I
               had come to believe with the greatest possible confidence that your devoutness was
               included. For I confess that I loved you and do love you greatly on account of the
               gentleness of your manners and on account of the modesty of your character: and, in
               fine, because for the sake of the orthodox faith you spurned all the stage-play of
               the world, and the deceitful pomps? of this life, and pleasures that wallow upon the
               earth and honours. But the request which, as I have been informed by letter, you are
               making, that the divine communion should be offered by my meanness and sent to you,
               for the sake of certain persons who are desirous of this, seems to have some kind of
               appearance of faith, but offends against the laws of the Spirit. For to those the
               oblation is of necessity sent who, while living in countries outside the boundaries
               and being orthodox, are deprived of priests to offer the rational and heavenly
               sacrifice. To speak with God's permission, since both saintly bishops and God-loving
               presbyters are living in the royal among cities, and without restraint and with
               boldness give the bread of life and the cup of immortality, it is a very superfluous
               and hurtful thing that the holy communion beyond the boundaries should be sent to you
               by my feebleness. Since there is one faith and the same sound <pb n="238"/>
               confession not corrupted at all by any adulterating doctrine, there is also assuredly
               one communion of different priests who offer it; who are as far apart as east from
               west, and confess the same unadulterated faith: although some be high and exalted to
               heaven, and elevated by labours of asceticism and the highest degree of virtues, and
               others men that creep on the earth owing to the remissness and idleness of their
               character. It is not the offerer himself who, as by his own power and virtue, changes
               the bread into Christ's body, and the cup of blessing into Christ's blood, but the
               God-befitting and efficacious power of the words which Christ who instituted the
               mystery commanded to be pronounced over the things that are offered. The priest who
               stands before the altar, since he fulfils a mere ministerial function, pronouncing
               his words as in the person of Christ, and carrying back the rite that is being
               performed to the time at which He began the sacrifice for His apostles, says over the
               bread, "This is my body which is given for you: this do in remembrance of me": while
               over the cup again he pronounces the words, "This cup is the new testament in my
               blood, which is shed for you." Accordingly it is Christ who still even now offers,
               and the power of His divine words perfects the things that are provided so that they
               may become His body and blood. But the priest who stands, since he fulfils a mere
               subsidiary function only, makes <pb n="239"/> no addition whatever to the rites that
               are performed, although he be an angelic and heavenly man in his character, nor does
               he detract anything from the divine grace, if he has lived a degraded and low life.
               This the divine writings confirm in another place also. Once, when Elijah the great
               among prophets was commanded to decree a famine against the land of Israel, because
               of the lawlessness and the prevalence of idolatry, he himself was commanded to dwell
               in hiding beyond Jordan, in the torrent-bed of Cherith; "and the ravens brought him
               bread in the morning, and flesh in the evening: and he drank water from the torrent."
               But the law given by Moses reckoned ravens among unclean birds. Hence this historical
               event that happened in the case of the prophet is pregnant with mystic and secret
               teaching, It teaches that the food given by God, which in the morning as it were,
               that is in the visible sense, is bread, but in the hidden and invisible sense (this
               is the signification of "the evening") is flesh and God's body, is in no way injured
               or impaired by those who mediate and minister, even if they be unclean men and loose
               in their character after the manner of ravens. Gregory also, the Theologian, who fed
               Nazianzus the small among cities, but is the teacher of the whole world over which
               the church is spread, who in the exalted nature of his theology reached to the
               citadel of Jerusalem in heaven, says in the discourse that was <pb n="240"/>
               delivered by him upon baptism that the same grace of adoption is obtained from the
               laver of regeneration both by a man who has received baptism from a priest eminent
               for virtues, and by a man who has received it from one who is degraded and grovelling
               in his character, both by a man who has received it from an archbishop, and by a man
               who has received it from a presbyter who holds the lowest rank. For both give one and
               the same seal, so long as they solemnize and preach one orthodox faith like in all
               points and sound. Just as, he says, a seal of gold and one of iron, or of some other
               cheaper material, so long as they bear one image and likeness engraved, not differing
               in anything, impress one and the same stamp on wax, and no one who was not present
               and saw can discern which is the wax that received the seal from the signet of gold,
               and which on the other hand is that which was sealed by the signet of iron, or by a
               cheaper signet, since both bear the same signet not differing in anything, in the
               same way baptism, and similarly also the offering of the sacrifice, in no way
               differs, not if the priest who celebrated these be, so to speak, a man of gold in his
               character and approved and illustrious, by reason of the purity which comes from the
               practice of virtues, nor if he be one who Is, so to speak, of iron, and a man who is
               murky and dark in his life. The difference of the character of those who officiate
               makes no difference whatever <pb n="241"/> in the mysteries that are celebrated, so
               long as both confess one orthodox faith, and are not stained by the stain of any
               heresy, nor do despite to the freedom of the preaching through servile fear and do
               not declare the glory of the truth "with open face, or act craftily and speak with
               treacherous and deceitful tongue both what pleases the heretics and what pleases us
               the orthodox, and laugh at both sides in an illiberal and meretricious fashion, or
               lie under the stigma of open abominations: for such as these one ought to avoid and
               spurn as standing outside the sacred limits: but let us not inquire into sins that
               are not open. Of these we are not the judges, but God, who searches into things that
               are unknown and knows things that are hidden, Paul, who had Christ speaking in him,
               rejecting grovelling fear, said, "But we are not of timidity that leadeth to
               perdition, but of faith that gaineth us ourselves": and spurning accursed craftiness,
               "For we are not as many which adulterate the word of God: but, as from the truth and
               as from God before God, speak we in Christ Jesus:" and again: "Not walking in
               craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully: but by manifestation of the
               truth commending ourselves to all conscience of men before God" And excluding open
               and notorious and stigmatized abomination he writes, "But fornication and all
               uncleanness and covetousness, let it not be even <pb n="242"/> or words of folly or
               of derision and of jesting, which are not desirable": and again in another place,
               "Thou that preachest, 'thou shalt not steal,' dost thou steal? Thou that sayest,
               'thou shalt not commit adultery,' dost thou commit adultery?" These things, being
               open and matters of shame, are certainly to be avoided, and are unhallowed. It will
               be good and useful and will further confirm what has been said, if we also adduce the
               actual words of the Theologian Gregory which run thus: "Say not, 'Let a bishop
               baptize me, and he a metropolitan or a bishop of Jerusalem' (for the grace does not
               belong to places, but to the Spirit), 'and he one of those of high birth; for it is
               hard if my nobility shall be insulted by a baptizer; or a presbyter, but he also one
               of the unmarried, and he one of the continent and angelic in his character; for it is
               hard if I shall be defiled at the time of cleansing.' Seek not trustworthiness in the
               preacher, nor in him that baptizes. Another is the judge of these matters and
               searcher of things that are not clearly visible: since, 'man on the face, but God on
               the heart——' But to you everyone is trustworthy for the cleansing. Only let him be
               one of those that are approved, and not of those that are openly stigmatized, nor an
               alien to the Church. Judge not the judges, you who need healing. Inquire not, I pray
               you, into the authority of those that cleanse you. Hesitate not concerning begetters.
               <pb n="243"/> One is better than another, or lower; but everyone is higher than
               you. But look at it in this way. Take gold: take iron: and both of them rings: and
               suppose the same royal image impressed on them. Then let them stamp wax. How will
               this seal differ from that seal? In no way. Recognise the material in the wax; and,
               if you are wiser than everyone, say which is the seal of the iron and which of the
               gold. And how is it one? "Because the difference is in the material, not in the
               image. So let every baptizer be to you. For, though he is more exalted in character,
               yet the virtue of the baptism is equal: and everyone who imitates the same faith
               brings you perfection in the same way." Strengthened therefore by these wise
               admonitions of the. God-inspired Scripture and of the approved instructors? of the
               apostolic church, inasmuch as you are entrusted with the ministry of God, warn our
               beloved brothers not to deceive themselves with such self-made fears, but to reckon
               and firmly believe the communion offered by our meanness to be one with that which is
               consummated by our fellow-ministers, by the saintly high-priests and God-loving
               priests who are living there, or are passing their lives in other places, and in all
               points think and say the same as we do, as aforesaid. If one man say, "I partake of
               the communion that was offered by so-and-so the patriarch," and another boastingly
               say, "I partake <pb n="244"/> of that which was offered by so-and-so the ascetic,"
               and another speak more proudly and say, "I partake of that which was offered by
               so-and-so who is. learned and skilled in the sacred doctrines and in the divine
               scriptures," such men will, unknown to themselves, have fallen into another
               blasphemy, and be assigning human conceptions to the gift of the divine power, and
               besides this abomination committing also the other sin of dividing the one Christ.
               These Paul will rebuke in the form of a question and very reproachfully when he says,
               "Has Christ been divided?", as well as another of our Saviour's disciples when he
               writes in a general epistle, "It is not right, my brethren, that these things should
               be so." Greet all that love us in the Lord. All our brothers who are with us greet
               you. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
