<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Caesaria the Patrician</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">244-49</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="3.4">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Caesaria the patrician.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 8th book the 54th
               letter.</head>
            <p> May our Lord Jesus Christ the great God and our Saviour rebuke the spirit of
               infirmity, as is written in <pb n="245"/> Luke, and free your glorious modesty from
               this long trouble (for it is He who chastises and slays not, and smites and heals, as
               the divine Scripture teaches"), and render you sound and strong. This is our prayer
               by night and day and at all times, as God knows who hears us when we entreat: and we
               believe that He will complete His mercy towards you. Since you also ask for the
               communion, and say that you have not communicated all this long time, see! we have
               now sent you this also, conceding on account of your infirmity a thing that is
               against the strictness of the sacred ordinances. But henceforth we beg you, and we
               adjure you by the divine power, and by Christ's infallible tribunal, before which we
               shall all stand, not to meditate, not to say do, anything of the kind again. It is a
               great and unpardonable sin that, when the faith of the orthodox priests is one, a man
               should take the holy and reverend communion from this one, and not take it from that.
               For it is Christ Himself and His mysterious words which are pronounced over the bread
               and the cup of blessing that complete the rational and bloodless sacrifice, not the
               priest who stands before the altar. This is taught both by the God-inspired words of
               the Old and of the New Testament, and by those who at different times fed the
               churches in an approved manner: the transgression of whose precepts brings great
               danger upon him who transgresses them: from which may <pb n="246"/> God deliver both
               you and our poor self! In the case of the religious deacon Misael also, as well as
               the Christ-loving brothers Ammian and Epagathus, who about two years ago sent me a
               box and asked to have it filled full for them with the communion or holy oblation, I
               did not fall in with the impiety and superfluity of the request, writing as follows:
               [Here follows a citation from ep. 2, extending from 'But, when you enjoy' (p. 234
               l.17) to the end]. But it is incumbent upon us to lay down as a law concerning these
               things the utterances of Gregory the teacher of truth which we have mentioned, the
               actual words of which are as follows: [Here follows the extract from Greg. Naz. given
               on p. 242 ff.]. If therefore both the divine laws of the sacred Scripture and the
               precepts of the saintly fathers and teachers give these commands, how is it not
               manifest breach of the law for a man to say, "I will not consent to partake of any
               other oblation but that which is consummated by so-and-so"? In the first place he
               divides Christ who in this also is one and undivided, and draws upon himself the
               condemnation of those who divide Him: in the second place, if such a man depart from
               human affairs, and go without having communicated and taken with him the last
               provisions, his soul will be liable to be seized by the demons, who will prevent it
               from making the upward journey and resting at once in some light countries, but will
               drag it away and convey it by force to the <pb n="247"/> depths of countries that are
               dark and not light: in the third place, he will also lay himself under the burden of
               another condemnation for opposing the precepts of the fathers and high-priests and
               laying down a law, if one may so Say, in opposition to these. Indeed Paul, when
               writing to the Romans about those who oppose political powers and authorities and
               their commandments, says these words: "Let every soul be subject to higher powers,
               for there is no power that is not from God: and those that exist are appointed by
               God. Whoever therefore opposeth the power opposeth the commandment of God. And those
               that oppose them shall receive judgment." If these words apply to political or
               military powers, how great will be the condemnation of those. that oppose the rulers
               of the holy church and their ordinances! For the difference and distinction is as
               great as between heavenly and earthly things. Withdraw therefore and dissociate
               yourself from such an awful and terrible judgment, and look upon all the orthodox
               priests as one and as Christ Himself: and reckon the sacrifice performed by all of
               them to be one, and do not lay down decrees against your soul, decreeing and saying,
               "I will not touch any sacrifice except that which is performed by so-and-so." It is
               said in the legal writings given through Moses that, if a woman, being in her
               parents' house, decree a fast against her soul, or vow and promise to accomplish any
               other action, or swear that she will do something <pb n="248"/> or other, and her
               father hear and keep silent and do not dissent, she that vowed or decreed shall
               certainly and by all means be bound to accomplish her vows and decrees: but, if, when
               her father hear what his daughter in the first instance decreed, he do not consent,
               but dissent and reject the decrees, God also will annul them, and will not require
               her that decreed to accomplish them. Know therefore that your excellency's decree
               also is null and worthless. For Gregory the father, the speaker of divine things,
               rejects it, and does not allow you to discriminate between priests, and say
               positively, "I will not communicate in the holy mysteries, unless they be such as
               have been consummated by so-and-so." Hear also what the legal commandment says: "But,
               if her father dissent in the day on which he heard her vows and decrees which she
               decreed against her soul, they shall not stand. And the Lord shall absolve her,
               because her father dissented." Do not therefore seek to accomplish in fact the things
               which you decreed, but which the father resisted and disowned; and the Lord will
               absolve you, and will free you from al! sickness of soul and of body, and will grant
               you power to follow His laws in all things, and to impute divine things, as divine
               things, to God alone, and not to any man. You say that all methods of treatment have
               been tried by the physicians, but all have been found useless <pb n="249"/> and have
               been defeated by the long continuance of the illness. Look therefore at the pattern
               of the praiseworthy woman in the Gospels who was troubled by an issue of blood for
               twelve years, and had spent all her wealth on physicians, and like her draw near to
               Jesus, and, as Mark the Evangelist says, tell Him as God the whole case and the
               truth. If you do this in a pure fashion He will assuredly say to you, "My daughter,
               thy faith hath saved thee: go in peace, and be whole of thy plague." Such illnesses
               need only the divine working in order to be healed, and this right-minded souls draw
               upon themselves in its entirety by confessing the sins that they have committed. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
