<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3021">To Zacharias of Pelusium</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">249-53</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Zacharias of Pelusium.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 1st book the
               208th, 209th Letter.</head>
            <p> You say, "What can be made pure by that which is impure?" But I say that this
               expression, inasmuch <pb n="250"/> as it was uttered in the right spirit, makes your
               offering pure, although it was by nature impure and a thing acquired by iniquity (we
               will refrain from mentioning this in words). For there is nothing that makes God so
               glad as for a man to be the first to blame himself, even though he be a man who is
               free from all blame. He who has been the first to blame himself, progressing by
               degrees, will certainly give up the iniquity also. Wherefore He cries through the
               prophet, "Tell thou thy sins first, that thou mayest be justified." So also that
               Canaanite woman, when she was compared to a dog and accepted the insult as true,
               heard the high and loud testimony, "O woman, great is thy faith, be it unto thee as
               thou wilt." You deserve admiration for giving, and giving in such a spirit: but you
               would certainly have deserved greater admiration, if while doing this you
               communicated with us the orthodox. Do not think to yourself that, because you
               communicate with those who have prayer-house buildings, and for this reason say that
               you communicate with the church, that you say anything sound. This argument is
               childish and ridiculous: for a church is a collection of pious men which is joined in
               one union by right belief. As a witness of this, take Gregory the Theologian. In the
               discourse against the Arians he said, "These have the houses, we the indweller: these
               the temples, we God, and the privilege of becoming temples of the <pb n="251"/>
               living God and living ones, soul-possessing oblations, rational whole
               burnt-offerings, perfect sacrifices to God through the adored Trinity: these a
               people, we angels: these presumption, we faith: these the power of threatening, we of
               praying: these the power of throwing, we of enduring: these gold and silver, we the
               pure word. You have made for yourselves houses of two stories and three stories (know
               the words of Scripture: "A cooling chamber divided by windows"): but these are not
               yet higher than my faith and heaven to which I am going. Small is my flock, but it
               does not go towards the rock. Narrow is my fold, yet it cannot be leaped over by
               wolves: yet it is not such as to admit a robber, or to be captured by thieves and
               strangers." So far he. And we might have further quoted many other testimonies of the
               God-clad fathers, which say this same thing. But, not to extend the discussion to a
               great length, I leave the rest on one. side, but will cite for you a passage from a
               certain presbyter (Isidore, I mean, a native of your city of Pelusium, who was wise
               in learning and in piety) which is sufficient for this present purpose. In writing to
               a certain bishop named Theodosius he speaks thus: "Let Eusebius who presides over the
               people that have their habitation in Pelusium learn what a church is. For it is most
               shameful and grievous that, when he does not know even this same thing, he should
               think to perform priestly functions. <pb n="252"/> For that the gathering of holy men
               gathered from right faith and illustrious character is a church, is well-known to
               those who have tasted wisdom. And that he, not knowing this, is pulling down that
               which is really the church by giving offence to many, while raising up the
               church-building, and spoiling the former by driving out the earnest men, while
               embellishing the latter with fine marble, this also is well-known to everyone. But,
               if he were to gain any distinct knowledge that a church is one thing and a
               church-building another (for the former is made up of spotless souls, while the
               latter is built of stones and beams) I think he will give up pulling down the former,
               and embellishing the latter beyond what is needful. For it was not for walls, but for
               souls that the King of Heaven came here. But, if he pretends not to know the fact
               stated, although it is abundantly clear even to those who are very deficient, I will
               try to explain this by examples. For, as a sacrifice-building is one thing and a
               sacrifice another, and an incense-building one thing and incense another, and a
               council-building one thing and a council another (for the former means the place in
               which they assemble, and the latter the men who deliberate, on whom the issues both
               of danger and of safety rest), so also with a church-building and a church. But, if
               he shall say that even so he has not understood, let him learn that in the apostles'
               days, when the church abounded in spiritual gifts, and a glorious mode of life was
               practised, there were no church-buildings: <pb n="253"/> but in our days the
               church-buildings are embellished beyond what is right: while the church (but I do not
               wish to say anything harsh) is jeered at. For my part, if the choice had been laid
               before me, I would have chosen to be in those times, in which church-buildings
               embellished in this way did not exist, but the church was crowned with heavenly and
               divine gifts, rather than in these, in which the church-buildings are embellished
               with all kinds of marbles, but the church is stripped and bare of those spiritual
               gifts." </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
