<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3144">To Caesaria the Patrician</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">272-75</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.10">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Caesaria the patrician.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From I those which were found outside the 23 books, the
               15th letter.</head>
            <p> Out of piety that loves instruction you ask whether some of the orthodox are doing
               well in not communicating with the heretics, but listening to the reading of the holy
               Gospel, or even staying during the time of the mysterious prayers, but not
               communicating in the rites that are being performed. To those who are not ignorant of
               the divine laws the answer is manifest. John the Evangelist, the speaker of divine
               things, wrote: [Here follows the citation given on p. 263]. If then it is not right
               to offer even a bare greeting to those who bring another teaching and do not teach
               <pb n="273"/> the orthodox faith, how can one communicate in prayers and in
               lessons or in any other such things with such men as these? And Paul the wise
               commands us to turn away even the very face from those who are in servitude to
               heresy, writing thus to Titus: [Here follows the citation given on p. 264]. He
               therefore who joins in assembly with the guilty renders himself subject to the same
               judgment. Nay even the holy canons of the Church have manifestly repudiated the
               principle of a man praying with heretics. For the hundred and thirty-fifth canon
               says; "It is not right to receive the blessings' of heretics, which are rather
               no-blessings and not blessings." And there immediately follows the hundred and
               thirty-sixth also, which says; "It is not right to pray with heretics or
               schismatics." These statements give the strict rule. But, when I the mean one, as far
               as my mean knowledge extends, consider the broadness of the God-inspired scripture, I
               find that men who hold ministerial posts or high offices, and are obliged to
               accompany and attend upon rulers, receive an indulgence, if, when they go in with
               them and hear a lesson and prayers, they keep themselves perfect: I mean if they do
               not communicate in the communion from which they are divided. For instance in the
               fourth Book of Kingdoms there is something like this written. A certain captain of
               the host of the King of Syria of Damascus, by name Naaman, who was a leper, went to
               the prophet Elisha, and received <pb n="274"/> cleansing from his affliction. And
               through his healing he recognised the one and only true God of Israel, the Maker and
               Creator of all, and spurned the falsely-named gods and his fathers' worship and
               error. And, when he was about to return to his own country, he said to the prophet
               that he would no more look upon the strange gods and vain demons, "But," he says,
               "although the King of Syria go into the temple of the demon in their country who is
               called Rimmon, and I also go in with him to do him honour and to support him with my
               hand, I will worship the true God in my heart, and I will recognise Him only, but I
               will not communicate with the king in the error and worship the demon with him. Only"
               (he says) "pray for me, that God may be gracious to me in this thing also on account
               of necessity." And the prophet was silent and did not praise or blame: but by silence
               he followed a middle line and gave him indulgence: and, having invoked peace upon
               him, he sent him away. But it is well that we cite also the actual words of the
               divine scripture, which Naaman spoke to the prophet himself, which run as follows:
               "Thy slave will no more perform a burnt-offering or a sacrifice unto other gods, but
               unto the Lord only. And in this thing the Lord will be gracious to thy slave, when my
               lord goeth into the house of Rimmon to worship him there, because he leaneth upon my
               hands. And, when he worshippeth in the house of Rimmon, I, being with him, will
               worship the Lord God. And the Lord will be gracious to thy slave in <pb n="275"/>
               this thing. And Elisha said to Naaman, "Go in peace." Therefore, seeing that your
               glorious devoutness knows these things, I pray that with pure and sincere faith you
               may walk in the Lord's paths both in deed and in word. For besides your other
               excellencies I admire also your practice of reading and meditating on the divine
               words, the fruits and flowers of which are displayed in your God-loving letters,
               which gladden those before whom they come. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
