<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Ammonius a Presbyter of Alexandria</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">253-57</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.2">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Ammonius a presbyter of Alexandria, in
               which he gave him information as to the mention of Peter who was bishop of
               Alexandria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 1st book the 22nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> You bear witness to a wisdom in us which we do not possess, and you call yourself
               weak in comparison with this, as if we were inviting you to a wrestling-arena or a
               contest: but for my part I will in due season use the words of Job who says, "But
               where was wisdom found? and what is the place of understanding? Man knoweth not the
               way thereof, neither is it found among men." Wherefore I looked to the Giver of
               wisdom, and to Him I yielded abundance of <pb n="254"/> understanding thoughts, and I
               do not come to your brotherly person with many words, but: use as few words as
               possible. For I think that either you have forgotten what I wrote to you before, or
               you are purposely turning your mind away from it. For what else ought I to have done
               but communicate with you when the mention of Peter was inserted in the sacred
               tablets, without raising any objection but I ought not also to be required to praise
               and call distinguished a man who is not at heart so regarded by me, although you are
               otherwise minded. <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> Whereas you say of
               Peter who was bishop of your city that he wrote to those who were at one time and
               another bishops of the city of Antiochus, and openly anathematized the things done at
               Chalcedon against the right faith, and the impious Tome of Leo, know that we too are
               not unaware of this: but we express blame on the ground that he embraced the
               communion of those who did not write the same things as he did. Indeed not a single
               man among those outside in the epistles that he addressed to him can be shown to have
               anathematized those who spoke or speak of two natures after the union, let alone the
               Chalcedonian Synod, or the blasphemous Tome of Leo. Tell me: if now also upon our
               writing to the prelate of the royal city maybe, and anathematizing the things that we
               actually anathematize he were to draw up a trimming letter, containing only a
               confession of the right faith, but not further an anathema of the offending <pb
                  n="255"/> things also, would this suffice for a pure, sincere, firm conjunction?
               Not in the least. For instance, when Timothy was instituted after the expulsion of
               Macedonius, and sent a synodical letter to the saintly John, archbishop of the city
               of the Alexandrines, with nothing satisfactory about it, his holiness both wrote an
               epistle in answer, and through some method of mediation required him to remove the
               offending things by anathema; for he had held his peace, and had adopted the
               reprehensible course of silence. But the party of Dioscorus and Chaeremon, having
               always been hirelings and hucksters of piety, were not contented with this only, but
               also caused a letter to be drawn up by the pious king, addressed to the saintly John,
               archbishop of your city, which contained no small complaints, on the ground that he
               had not been contented with the Henotikon only, as Peter and Athanasius and John who
               succeeded the latter had been, without requiring: reference to be made in actual
               words to the impious things done at Chalcedon or to the impious Tome of Leo. And they
               induced the illustrious king for the purpose of proof to include in his pious letter
               a copy of the letters; the letters that Peter, Athanasius, and John addressed to the
               bishops who were outside: which had been produced at an earlier time also in the city
               of the Sidonians, when the synod of bishops was assembled there, and cast great shame
               upon us who were combating on behalf of orthodoxy, and nothing else was left to us
               <pb n="256"/> except only to hide ourselves and yield to manifest refutations. To
               these was also attached a letter of the pious John the archbishop written to
               Dioscorus and Chaeremon, to the effect that he did not ask for anything beyond the
               Henotikon only with no further addition. Do not therefore tell me that Peter wrote
               this and that to those who in earlier times occupied the throne of Antiochus' city:
               but show that they ever took upon themselves to write things agreeing with Peter's
               statements. Or, if you do not show this, he will be clearly convicted of having
               communicated with those who did not say and think the same as he did. How then did
               you bring yourself, and that though you are firm on all points, to write this
               assertion: "We for our part have done nothing new or great in anathematizing the
               Synod of Chalcedon and the impious Tome of Leo" The analogy of the dead man, who
               defiles or does not defile water, and the difficulty arising from it you must not
               take in this way, subjecting the mind to bodily conceptions, and restricting
               pollution to the effect of a multitude of bodies. In the mind of those who examine
               with intelligence, a mention whether one or many of men who have committed impiety
               causes the same abomination: which nothing else can extinguish except an abundance as
               I have said of the water of right faith, copiously poured upon everyone, <pb n="257"
               /> and a loyal anathema of the offending things, like much water which covers the sea
               according to the expression of the prophet. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
