<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3018">To Dioscorus, Archbishop of
               Alexandria</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">257-60</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.3">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Dioscorus archbishop of
               Alexandria.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">from those during episcopacy, from the 1st book the
               115th letter.</head>
            <p> Even when the brotherly person of your love of God is sending an embassy to the
               royal among cities, we are not separated from you in spirit: but we lift up to God
               hands that are not holy, but are much paralysed by sins; yet still we lift them up
               and entreat Him, who holds in His hand the hearts of those that are held like rushing
               water, to incline our serene king's pious soul to compliance, and bestow grace upon
               your words, in order that you may obtain all that your mind desires, and rescue the
               Christ-loving city of the Alexandrines from the wrath that threatens it, while time
               is granted you to feed your flock by "the water of stillness." When this has been
               brought to pass, we will again offer prayers of thanksgiving to Christ the Saviour of
               all and God, and will rejoice, and rejoice together with you at seeing by actual
               deeds themselves that our Lord 1s near and that He cares for us, so that even those
               who are outside our communion will say when they have seen <pb n="258"/> these
               things, "Truly God is among you." This fact also we reckon to be a part of such
               graciousness towards us, that the God-loving bishop Soteric who is placed at the head
               of the God-loving bishops of First Cappadocia should wish to unite with us, and
               should put forward propositions by means of which we ought to draw those who are in
               the royal city also to lawful conjunction, and the God-loving bishops of Second
               Cappadocia also are associated with him in such a purpose. Accordingly I have thought
               right to inform your sanctity, in order that by common consultation we may decide
               upon what ought to be done. They say that we ought to receive them upon their giving
               us satisfaction? up to this point, I mean up to the point of confessing the orthodox
               faith and anathematizing the things done at Chalcedon and the impious Tome of Leo,
               who was head of the church of the Romans (would he had never been so!), and those who
               speak of two natures after the union and the energies and properties of these. We are
               by no means unaware that Timothy of holy memory, who lived in toils and labours of
               piety, in so far as to dwell in exile, and reckon it a pleasure to suffer for Christ,
               on his return thence under the Encyclical letter which had this effect, received to
               communion those who were separated upon their anathematizing what was wrongfully done
               at Chalcedon, and the impious Tome. of Leo; but, since we must do all <pb n="259"/>
               things with deliberation, and support ourselves by brotherly counsels, therefore we
               have referred the consideration of this matter to your sanctity, in order that you
               may immediately inform us of your opinion. For it is manifest that we will do those
               things which you judge to be proper. When we also received the sacred letter of your
               holiness from Pamphylia, we rejoiced at learning at the same time how you had also in
               scrupulous fashion and with consideration and in the manner that became you joined
               the God-loving Castor bishop of the metropolis of Perga in the conduct of the
               mysterious service, and had communicated with him in the divine mysteries, teaching
               him by what you did to keep the possession of the sound faith "with all observance,"
               and to hold the beginning of our stability firm unto the end, as Paul says in his
               epistle to the Hebrews." This will more especially be the case if they keep
               themselves free from association in communion with those of contrary opinions. Of
               this I for my part bore testimony to the Cappadocians also, reminding them moreover
               of the patristic law. For Basil of saintly memory in an epistle to a certain Urbicius
               who was a monk at that time wrote in the same strain: "We beg therefore that these
               things receive ecclesiastical correction, and that you hold aloof from communion with
               the heretics, knowing as you do that indifference in these things takes away from the
               boldness before Christ." In <pb n="260"/> fact, to speak the truth, if a man believe
               rightly, but reckon association with adversaries as nothing, it is time for him to
               say like Paul, "I am become sounding brass or a tinkling cymbal." </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
