<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To John the Count from Antaradus</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">263-66</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.6">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John the count from Antaradus.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               390th letter.</head>
            <p> Your magnificent and believing consort did not need a letter of recommendation. For
               we will say both to you and to her in the words of the Apostle, "Ye are our epistle,
               written in our heart, and known and read by all men." However your actions seem
               gratifying, even those which are thought superfluous. As to the prelate of Arca,
               whereas you said in your letter that he reckons it an intolerable thing to do
               anything that annoys us, and this though he and those with him who are trying to
               bring him to this are making many prayers and entreaties, what was written seemed to
               be not clearly, but obscurely expressed: <pb n="264"/> but it informed me that he is
               pure in the communion which those men were desirous of rendering polluted through
               heretical association. And I for my part confess that this conduces to my pleasure.
               In fact the salvation of any man, especially of those that are loved like you, is
               fitly thought by me to be worth tens of thousands of talents of gold: or, to speak
               more justly, even worth all the pomp? and theatrical display in this world, But that
               you have rather bestowed a gift upon yourself, not upon me, by doing this is easy to
               show from the God-inspired scripture. For John the speaker of divine things in an
               epistle to certain believers says as follows: "If any man cometh unto you and
               bringeth not this sound teaching, receive him not in the house, and say not to him,
               'Hail.' For he that saith to him 'Hail' is partaker of his evil deeds." And Paul the
               wise in writing to Titus expressed himself thus: "A man that is an heretic after one
               admonition and two avoid: knowing that such a man is perverted and sinneth, being
               self-condemned." And the words written by him to the Corinthians also lead to this
               sense: for he says, "Therefore 'come out from among them and be separate,' saith the
               Lord, 'and approach not an unclean man.'" However, not to spin out the letter by
               using many words, know that the great Basil also, the teacher of all that is under
               heaven, wrote this in his letters as a kind of rule and canon, in this manner: [Here
               follows the citation <pb n="265"/> given on p. 259]. These sacred commands therefore
               you have followed, in that you would not at all consent to come to the communion of
               those who profess opinions contrary to the orthodox faith. So that, if your firmness
               had slackened (as I pray may not happen), how great repentance would you have needed
               for transgressing the strictness of such a law! Wherefore keep the gift that was
               given you by God, I mean that of the pure and unadulterated communion: for truly this
               is a gift of God. In fact Paul also somewhere speaks thus: "And this was not of you.
               For it is a gift of God: not of works, lest any man should boast." The saying also of
               one of the wise men without seems to be in a way suited to the present topic; "It is
               harder for us to keep good things than to get them." This too it is good to consider:
               if he who eats with the king's adversaries is thought to sin beyond forgiveness,
               where ought we to place him who eats the mysterious and heavenly bread with those who
               hold opinions adverse to God? Let these words that we have written concerning your
               salvation which is highly regarded by us suffice: words few compared with the need,
               but too many for the compass of the letter. But that the ruler of Arca, whom I
               mentioned a short time ago, is exactly like a beast of burden and a pack-ass, and
               that he belongs to those who lead him rather than to himself, experience showed even
               before your words. You were wise and very intelligent in considering that <pb n="266"
               /> that letter which exposes the false profession ought to be sent to those who
               conduct our <foreign>apokriseis</foreign> in the royal city: a thing which I have in
               fact done. But let it not be unknown to your greatness that he spoke the truth when
               he said that he had received a letter from his brother which hindered him from making
               the journey to us, or rather which led him to death, </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
