<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Father John Canopites</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">266-68</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.7">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to father John Canopites.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those that were found outside the 23 books, the 4th
               letter.</head>
            <p> We for our part, feeble although we are, write everything written by your holiness
               upon the tablets of our heart, as it is written, and do not, as a man might think,
               read it over hastily. And we pray, as sinners, that your words may with God's help be
               continued to us in the time of trial. For I am in the habit of mentioning Basil and
               Gregory, and having their names constantly upon my tongue: but there is nothing
               resembling their virtue in me, seeing that I have passed all my life in negligence.
               As for those who, as your holiness says, starting from this place, go to other
               provinces and communicate indifferently, my conscience does not smite me as not
               having given this injunction with all my power and all my capacity for <pb n="267"/>
               teaching, and said that want of carefulness in these things is great wickedness;
               whence I did not shrink from giving personal demonstration and proof even to women,
               when need called, that there is a great gulf, as in the passage in the Gospels,
               between the orthodox communion and that of the adversaries, and that we have no
               communion or association with those of p. 301. adverse opinions. But, if some men
               associate secretly in so great a number of cities and of provinces," your sanctity
               knows that this reflects no blame on us. So far was I from being satisfied with the
               matter that I even wrote an epistle to some of our brothers in Alexandria to say that
               they ought not, on the pretext of worshipping in the holy places, to associate in
               communion with men of other opinions. These are our proceedings, and this is the
               position in which they stand. However matters are placed as in a balance and a scale
               of a balance, and we do not know what will be the result of the things that are being
               stirred in the royal city and the things reported concerning the synod that is to be
               held, seeing that they are variously told and differently at different times. But of
               this one thing we for our part are assured, that, while God extends His hand, no one
               will be able to lead us away from the right faith, From places and from sees removal
               by force is possible: but from belief it is wholly impossible, unless we ourselves
               <pb n="268"/> desire it, and the fear of God be lacking in our souls. For "the
               Lord taketh pleasure in them that fear Him and in those that hope for His grace," as
               the singing prophet somewhere says. But you, father, help us with all the power that
               is in you by stretching forth your saintly hands. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
