<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Andrew the Reader and Notary</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">270-72</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="4.9">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Andrew the reader and notary.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 9th book the 62nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> By a wonderful chance, such as no one expects before it happens, the letter of your
               devoutness was delivered to me on the fourth day of the present month of September,
               on which is celebrated the memory of the thrice-blessed Dioscorus, the archbishop and
               holy martyr, who is now counted among the heretics in Alexandria and anathematized by
               the impious. With this letter was also joined a letter of the holy virgins who were
               expelled from Antioch: which in us <pb n="271"/> excited many sighs and tears, but
               for them has prepared right glorious heavenly blessings, such as are described in the
               book of life. <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> But you have rightly
               determined that the Christ-loving freewomen shall in no way be afraid to visit their
               <foreign>anepsios</foreign> or cousin," who is laid in the martyr's chapel of the
               holy Peter the archbishop and martyr. Where the bones of holy martyrs have previously
               been laid, it is right to pray without hesitation: especially when the place is in
               silence, and the heretics are not unlawfully conducting services or singing inside.
               In fact even Peter the bishop of holy memory from Iberia prayed in the house of the
               chapel of the glorious holy martyr and apostle Judas the brother of James, who is
               laid at Berytus (in the same fashion he prayed also at Tripolis in the house of the
               chapel of the holy victory-clad martyr Leontius). As to the fact which you mention
               that they are constantly busying themselves about the offering that they made to me,
               I say that here again is a timely act on the part of the sacred martyrs and divine
               virgins who are expected from the East, and are ready to show forth in themselves as
               pious women the love of God. For my part, if I be hungry or thirsty, I will rend by
               force the mantle and tunic with which they are clad, if they do not generously feed
               me. May the Lord therefore in return for everything give them a perfect reward for
               their good will! You did rightly <pb n="272"/> in informing us further of the decease
               of the pious bishop Zosimus, in order that we may praise God, who did not allow him
               to be wholly perverted to any of the deeds of the adversaries, but to depart while in
               some sort counted in the communion of the orthodox, and find mercy in the judgment
               before the awful tribunal: that is, unless he is perhaps stained somewhere at bottom
               with the leprosy of heresy and with impious belief. In the case of men of this kind I
               say with confidence that they will find no place of clemency, seeing that, as far as
               in them lies, they have given strength to the noose of error to destroy the souls of
               many. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
