<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To John the Tribune</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">275-82</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John the tribune, in the name of father
               Leontius.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 4th book the 2nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> For my part I thought that the negligence and sloth that has grown old with me, and
               the sleep of sins from which up to the present day I have not been roused, were
               unknown to the majority of men, but known to God only, "who knoweth the hearts," and
               makes "light the hidden things of darkness," and reveals the thoughts that are in the
               mind. But you by naming me a city set upon a height have caused me an increase of
               tears, if I not only injure myself by my <pb n="276"/> forgetfulness, but also make
               myself a bad example to others who know me. The holy scripture knows of such cities
               also and evil powers, and men who regard impiety, whose memory the Lord destroyed
               with tumult. However, I considered that you were led by love and your faith towards
               Christ to write thus, though you distressed my wretchedness. But, concerning the
               other part of your letter, I was much grieved: and I prayed that the earth might open
               for me, seeing that you have dared to open a blaspheming mouth against the saint and
               archbishop Timothy, the preserver of the orthodox faith, who was left as a remnant
               and a root for Israel, enduring long exiles, and bearing Christ's marks in him. What
               cause of blame is there, tell me, in the fact of his receiving canonically upon
               repentance those who were ordained by heretics, when they anathematized their heresy
               in writing? Are you not in the habit of hearing that Melitus, the archbishop of
               Antioch, was ordained by Arians, and that he afterwards showed himself an approved
               champion of orthodoxy, insomuch that he was thought worthy to suffer many things, and
               put on the crown of confession? What then? Did those who received this man at that
               time and honoured him with tens of thousands of praises, one of whom was the great
               Basil, also praise or receive the man who ordained him, holding as he did Arian
               opinions? Nay, him they justly repudiated as having remained in the nets <pb n="277"
               /> of Arius, while they admired Melitus as having by repentance purged away the dregs
               of heresy and combated on behalf of orthodoxy. But you say that the holy Timothy
               contradicted himself, seeing that at first he said that those who had been ordained
               should not be received, but at a later time received them. Being an old man and
               without learning and uninstructed I acquiesce in what you say. However, we find that
               the holy apostles also showed similar self-contradiction. For instance Peter, though
               he was in the habit of preaching the gospel to those of the circumcision only, and
               did not go on to preach to those of the nations also, because he thought it to be
               "unlawful to approach or join himself to anyone of another race," afterwards, when he
               had received a revelation from God, said, "God hath showed me also not to call any
               man common and unclean": and again, "God also who knoweth the hearts bare them
               witness, giving them the Holy Spirit even as unto us, and put no difference between
               us and them." In such cases the purpose is approved though the things done are
               thought to appear in some way contradictory. But, that you may learn that it is not I
               only the uninstructed who say these things, I remember to have heard a discourse of
               the holy John, bishop of Constantinople, read: and I have now again looked for the
               book, and have copied some sentences from it for your affection, which give us an
               example bearing upon this <pb n="278"/> present subject, that we are not to be
               scandalized without reason. The discourse in which the holy man writes these things
               is the encomium on Paul the Apostle: and he speaks thus: "So neither would Paul have
               been known to imitate his Lord, except that he became now a Jew, now as one not under
               the law. For now he would keep the law: now he would neglect the law. And at one time
               he would cleave to the life here; at another again he would despise it. And now he
               would ask for money: now he would refuse it even when given. And he would sacrifice,
               and shave: and again he would anathematize the doers of these things. And now he
               would circumcize: now he would reject circumcision. And the things done were
               contradictory: but the thought and intention from which these proceeded was very
               consistent and consonant with itself. For he sought one thing, the salvation of those
               who saw and heard these things. For this reason now he would keep the law: now he
               would subvert it. For it was not only in what he did, but also in what he said that
               he was versatile and rich in expedients: not being changed in his mind, nor passing
               from one disposition to another, but remaining that which he was, and treating each
               of the said matters in accordance with the need of the time. Do not therefore speak
               evil of him on account of these things, but celebrate and crown him the more on
               account of these things. For in fact in the case of a physician also, when you see
               him now burning now feeding; and using now iron now medicine; and now prohibiting
               foods <pb n="279"/> and drinks, now allowing the patient to enjoy these without
               stint; and at one time restricting him on all sides, at another ordering the man who
               has been seized with fever to drink a glass full of cold water, you do not blame him
               for the variation, nor because of the perpetual change: but you will then praise the
               technical skill the more, because you see it boldly applying methods that seem to us
               contradictory and hurtful, and pledging itself for a safe result. For such is the man
               of technical skill. But, if we accept a physician when he does these contradictory.
               things, much more must we celebrate the soul of Paul, which approached those in
               trouble in this way." So far the holy John: but I wish to say one other thing which
               also springs from rusticity and an uninstructed mind. I consider that all the bishops
               throughout the earth who are bound together with one another in the orthodox faith
               and combined in union are one. For all follow the model of one, of the great God and
               our Saviour Jesus Christ. Therefore, as, when Cyprian in Africa with the synod under
               him said that all who had been baptized by heresy ought to receive the laver of
               <sic><reg>regeneration</reg><orig>regenertion</orig></sic>, as if they had
               never originally been baptized at all, but at last the opinion of Sixtus of Rome, and
               of Dionysius of Alexandria and of the others prevailed, so that those who had been
               baptized by heretics in the name of the three substances, the Father, the Son, and
               the Holy Spirit, were not re-baptized, no one of sound <pb n="280"/> intelligence
               said that those saintly bishops contradicted themselves, but that upon later
               consideration they chose a better and more canonical course, so also the holy Timothy
               too at first, owing to the blasphemy and the impenitent heart of the Proterians as it
               was at the beginning, and the zeal of the orthodox people of the city of the
               Alexandrines, said that he would not accept those who had been ordained by the
               opposite party: but at last, when they canonically repented and he lawfully accepted
               them, he did not show himself self-contradictory, but rather very consistent, since
               he said those things on account of the zeal of the believers, but allowed the canons
               to prevail, and accepted those who repented in accordance with the final conclusions
               of the fathers, and further by signing the Encyclical united himself to all the
               bishops in the world. Though these things seem contradictory to many, yet
               nevertheless their one purpose was the salvation of those who had perished, and that
               those who stood upright might not under the influence of immoderate zeal leave the
               royal road, and turn away to that which is rather on the right side. Therefore, you
               that are beloved on account of our Lord Jesus, do not out of ignorance injure your
               soul: but hear me the unlearned and uninstructed, and do not revile the man of God,
               with whom all the fathers were satisfied at that time, not having received the
               satisfaction that is from men, but that which is from God: and I the mean and sinful
               <pb n="281"/> am, as I persuade myself, no false witness of this. We did not love
               Timothy as having been crucified for us, as you say, but as having been a true
               bondservant of Him who was of His own accord crucified for the race of men, and a
               faithful and wise steward of God's mysteries: who also contended against the heresy
               of the Diphysites or Nestorians, and the impious phantasy of the Eutychianists,
               proclaiming Emmanuel to be one nature out of two, the Godhead that is and the
               manhood, and the same of one essence with the Father in the Godhead, and of one
               essence with us men in the manhood. For He took of the seed of Abraham and was made
               like us His brethren in all things except sin, in order that He might redeem those
               who were under sin, and might save us by His blood, and we might thenceforth be
               called a holy people, inasmuch as we were created by the blood of God, who suffered
               for us in the flesh and remained impassible. Let your beloved person know that to all
               who came to my pitifulness of the holy fathers in Pamphylia, and of the Christ-loving
               laymen, I read what was written to me by you: and each of them urged me to write to
               you many things taken from the doctors who were eminent at various times in the
               church. For some of them actually knew you at the time when Promotus the count, whose
               soul is at rest, was living in the royal city: with whom you perhaps in fact
               discussed these things. But for my part, seeing that <pb n="282"/> as an uninstructed
               and unlearned man I avoid many words, I have sent you in an epistle the fruit of my
               rusticity: having besought the merciful God to place in you the wisdom which is
               gentle and obedient, in respect of the things that have been written by me. May the
               Lord of peace and of tranquillity grant us peace and tranquillity at all times and in
               all ways! </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
