<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3109">To John and John the Presbyters and the
               Others</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">325-37</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.11">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John and John the presbyters and the
               rest.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 71st
               letter.</head>
            <p> I owe thanks to God that after the winter-season I have again through your letter
               heard your sweet and cheerful voice. For to me to hold communication with you seems
               more cheerful and joyful than any spring. To delight and adorn ourselves with flowers
               from the meadows. that quickly bloom and wither is not like weaving together blossoms
               of spiritual words. The first blossom, one very well adapted for giving joy, was
               contained in your letter in the fact that the celebration of the saintly Theodore the
               presbyter! provided a crowded festival and feast to those who assembled, so that the
               believers are confirmed in future hope even by what is seen now. For the departure
               hence of holy men and the remembrance of them on the occasion of this is a means of
               instruction and of meditation on the blessed life: the life which Christ promised
               when He revealed to us by actual experience the mystery of the Resurrection. As to
               events in the East we also have certain know<pb n="326"/>ledge of the same things
               that were also stated in your letter: and nothing beyond. Nevertheless the pangs
               caused by the impiety compel us to bring the foul birth out. It rests therefore with
               you, saintly men, and with all who love God to make supplication and to stir up your
               fervent prayers like a censer, and cast upon them "fine composite incense" which is
               earnest and laborious supplication, supplication that at the same time reminds the
               divine ears of their wonders from eternity and is able to stop the corruption so that
               the Lord's congregation may not utterly perish, and the peoples say, "Where is their
               God?" As to Silvanus who is of heretical ordination, but begs to be received, you
               ought not to be in difficulty seeing that the regulations of the holy Timothy have
               marked out the proper course for you, and have laid down for you the method to be
               followed in this case: so that everything that goes beyond and surpasses him falls
               outside the limits of what is proper. However it will rest with you who are at hand
               and know the man to shorten or lengthen his time according to the character of his
               repentance. If possible therefore, the God-loving Isidore bishop of the city of the
               Chalcidians will release this man. But, if it is thought that this will stir up
               affliction to his bonds, as the Apostle says, it is easy for him to go with a letter
               from you to the God-loving Epimachus bishop of Rhinocorura, and receive forgiveness.
               Only beware <pb n="327"/> lest, when the man ts forgiven, he use the freedom as an
               assistance in causing disturbance in various places, since such is the character that
               you ascribe to him in your letter. As to John of blessed memory the reader and our
               scribe, I should perhaps have been sorry that he did not come to see me and was
               prevented from undertaking the daring journey which would have been in the winter and
               is full of dangers, had it not been that he met with such an end of life, and a
               gathering-place for which one might well pray and a holy tabernacle (I will not say
               grave), it being one that foreshadowed for him rest in the eternal mansions. We pray
               also that through your holy prayers he may receive the lot of the saints in all its
               fulness. However both he and the devout Sergius the reader when they came here
               injured many persons more than they edified them. One might hear them relating
               certain dreams and prophecies, on account of which, as they said, they hesitated to
               communicate with the holy churches in Egypt. From whom he heard these things I do not
               wish to say, lest I even seem to certain persons to be a hard man. Who is there who
               will not (and very rightly) pronounce against us as senseless, if we set ourselves
               against such prophecies and dreams, and while occupying ecclesiastical thrones forget
               these things, but, when we are outside and are expelled and driven out, again attend
               to dreams and repeat dreamy prophecy? However, since it is not my pleasure to make
               accusations, but to declare and explain to those <pb n="328"/> who love me what my
               position is, and proclaim it also to the adversaries, the communion that now prevails
               in the persecuted church of the East and in all the Egyptian church, and is pure in
               the proclamation of the faith, and in the rejection of the evil Chalcedonian impiety,
               and in purging itself of heretics and holding no association with them, this
               communion I so hold and to it I so draw near, as I drew near in it with the highest
               assurance and a fixed mind, when our holy father Peter the bishop from Iberia was
               offering, and was performing the rational sacrifice. We did not by our concession
               give anything like what we received. We waived the strict observance of names
               according to the fathers' ordinances for the sake of the salvation of so many cities,
               and instead of it we obtained besides the East the whole of Egypt also supporting us
               and ranging itself on our side with a pure heart, and not bound in a yoke with
               unbelievers, to speak in the words of the Apostle. Having cast this seed, we gained
               for fruits banishment of bishops: confession on the part of cities: martyr-like
               contests, such that men reckon every kind of torture small. This is to be seen not
               only in men, but also in women and in every sex, and every age: insomuch that the
               inhabitants of the whole of Egypt are ready to strip themselves for like contests, if
               the time summon. What manner of man then were we when we had these things granted us,
               a man deprived of bishops <pb n="329"/> and sitting in a corner, and resembling a
               pelican of the wilderness as the prophet sings, and possessing a fruitless accuracy,
               insomuch that some were eager to proceed to new and different divisions? But God,
               knowing clearly that our holy fathers and His true servants always endeavoured to
               walk in the royal road, cut away these things and made them cease as if they had
               never begun at all, and instead of them by invisible means bestowed upon us riches
               that we had never desired or been able to conceive in our mind. He exposed the
               feebleness of human thoughts and efforts, but by means of facts themselves said, "For
               what the holy God hath purposed who shall annul? and His high hand who shall turn
               away?" How then shall we be found speaking in a contrary sense, we whose duty it is
               to exhort those who communicate with us to show freedom of speech regarding these
               things? Indeed according to my information the wonderful Mitras showed himself more
               irrational even than irrational things by continually saying that he is not in
               communion with the holy churches here, and gave ground for laughter to those who have
               no soundness of their own, but apply themselves to find for themselves lines of
               defence and discoveries of methods of support from the weaker brethren among us,
               because he could not give a reason for this irrationality (I will not say "doubt").
               Who is there who will not be disgusted with men who like Abimelech the <pb n="330"/>
               offspring of Gideon's concubine, who illegally became king in Shechem by gathering
               round him depraved and profligate men, as the God-inspired scripture somewhere
               narrates, illegally receive bishops who have been canonically repudiated and received
               deprivation, and make prayers over them, and crucify Christ afresh, as it is said,"
               and think that they are practising religion: men, whom God has rendered more naked
               than a pebble as the text of Proverbs says, as their evil disposition deserves: men
               who have fallen so far into conflict with God as to presume to anathematize the
               Edict, under which, as those men say in so many words, the followers of Julian the
               presbyter, whose soul is at rest; continued joined in communion with Peter, who
               became bishop of the city of the Alexandrines after Timothy, unto this day, and went
               into the church with him; not knowing that they are laying under an anathema men
               whom, as they think, they ascribe to themselves as their fathers. For how is it that,
               the right confession being contained in the Edict, they sought to have that which is
               wanting added, i.e. a rejection of the Synod of Chalcedon, and when this was not
               added withdrew from communion? If the Edict deserved an anathema, they ought never to
               have assented to this at the beginning: but have demanded that it also be repudiated,
               like one of the repudiated doctrines. So great is the lack of instruction and the
               desire of amassing money: an object <pb n="331"/> that "blinds" even "the eyes of the
               wise," as the sacred text says, not to speak of men who turn their attention to their
               belly only: which they fatten every day and carry about like some honoured sister,
               making their cheeks red by constant feastings, and presenting them swollen with fat
               to those that meet them, and not hiding themselves at all. The good Anatolius also is
               one of these, who foretold death to some men who had in full assurance communicated
               with the holy church in Alexandria, claiming to draw prophecies from that fat belly
               of his: but, when the prophecy failed to be fulfilled, he changed his tack and acted
               as a suppliant to those who had received his menaces. Having fallen in with them on
               the road, he knelt down and kept begging those who had been threatened to give him
               forgiveness, and only to return to communion with him. But they after laughing for a
               long time left him lying on the ground his prophecies and all. I pray your sanctities
               to be assured that a certain quiet man who had received such a threat from him, after
               communicating the knowledge to the holy church and accepting its help in considering
               what was best to do, by God's permission was smitten with bright tumours on the side,
               which many are in the habit of naming carbuncles. He, coming up to me (for he was one
               of those who know our affairs), begged me to touch the afflicted part: and I,
               beginning to weep, applied to it the chrism of the holy cross, and its <pb n="332"/>
               venerated sign; and I sent this man away expecting to die. And on the next day the
               Lord of hosts made the swelling caused by the tumours to disappear, and he did not
               keep his bed for one single hour: but, going about and following his usual pursuits,
               he was delivered from the affliction, "walking and leaping and praising God"; for the
               sacred scripture will again express this also. But, if I have become a fool by
               relating this, Anatolius the false prophet compelled me, even as the false apostles
               did Paul; though I am not Paul, and am a sinner, yet not a breaker of the law or the
               canons, but an observer of the law of Christ. Many other things also might have been
               related, which expose the foolishness of those men, but confirm the power of the
               truth: but the limits of a letter are not suited for such stories, seeing that they
               need the extended range of oral conversation. For the same Anatolius thought fit to
               say to certain men, "Hosius an old man, in whom alone I had confidence, who also" (he
               says) "gave me the monastic garb, used to urge me, when I came to Palestine, to
               communicate with the bishop of the city of the Antiochenes, saying that he placed
               confidence in him. But, when" (he says) "I for my part went on to ask him whether I
               ought also to communicate with the bishop of the city of the Alexandrines, he
               answered that I ought not to do this. But I" (he says), "laughing at the contrariety
               and inconsistency of the words, declined <pb n="333"/> to follow the advice." And
               many other falsehoods he tells. To women:too he was to be seen prophesying, and
               presumptuously laying threats upon them, while not getting anything else from such
               practices but laughter only. However he does not perceive things that are of a nature
               to cause shame, because he takes his pleasure in loaves of bread and cooked dishes
               and various drinks that are offered him, and feeds his belly only. For this has in
               fact been his object for a long time. To such an extent did the good and excellent
               Mitras (for to him I return) use words without sense, that I almost even forgot my
               caution, and even asked to meet and speak with him, and prevent him from being
               shaken: but I have not been able to find a way of doing so, since the necessity that
               surrounds me hinders the accomplishment of my wish. For he put forward one and
               another counter-argument of contemptible character, swimming and tossing (?) in his
               own fatuities and driven hither and thither at random. Among these one is this. They
               used in fact to say of us that we communicated with Simeon who stood on the pillar:
               and against those who laid down this counter-argument some of our supporters brought
               forward the truth and said, "Accordingly on your principle Timothy also of holy
               memory will rightly incur blame in this matter, if one does not take into account
               considerations of expediency concerning the holy churches and the necessity of
               joining and binding them together. For indeed he also is shown to have sent clergymen
               to <pb n="334"/> the East: who communicated with Peter who at that time held the
               prelacy of the city of the Antiochenes, bringing with them a synodical letter, And,
               after all the names had been read, the bearers of this communicated in the oblation:
               one among whom was the man called Achillas." Then they out of contentiousness falsely
               disputed and said that Achillas had orders to remove the names, and he did not do as
               he was ordered, and after his return to Alexandria was visited with punishment and
               separation. But the fiction was refuted by the fact that Antiochene clergymen had
               come at that time to the city of the Alexandrines to buy wheat, Syria being afflicted
               with lack of wheat, and exercised the ministry here and communicated in the sacred
               oblation. And again those audacious men said, "why did I pronounce a laudatory
               discourse about him, when I ought to have held my peace, and to have given effect to
               the considerations of expediency by silence?" In answer to this I said to those who
               spoke, "The <foreign>prooimion</foreign> or preface of the discourse shows the whole
               truth. Because the unholy Nestorians, whose leader was Theodoret, wished to snatch
               for themselves the splendour of the man's character, and to attach this to the
               heresy, I in composing the discourse made the true statement that he actually drove
               away Theodoret and said that he did not even know the Synod: but that he believed in
               the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit. I added this argument also, which is very
               true, that a man who did not know letters did not <pb n="335"/> sign: and those who
               have grown old in the flock and yet survive showed this by many proofs. And in order
               to exclude the impiety I made this manifest in the discourse, and prevented the
               deception of the believing peoples who by this plea were being brought to what the
               heretics desired, and were spurning the substance of the sound faith." So far said J.
               But I find that the holy fathers also defend conspicuous men who are capable of
               attracting many by their reputation, and this while knowing that those men did not
               keep the accuracy of the faith, whom they enthusiastically and with many praises
               defended. Such was the conduct of Athanasius when he wrote on behalf of Dionysius
               against the Arians, who wished to snatch for themselves the reputation of the man in
               support of their heresy. The purpose of Athanasius that made him compose the defence
               and the encomium was very plain: and this was, not to give the adversaries a chance
               of priding themselves upon him, and of putting forward the glory of Dionysius as a
               covering for their evil belief. Basil the great, as you know, in writing to Maximus
               the philosopher utters a pronouncement about Dionysius, in which he says these words:
               "Wherefore also he is many-coloured in his writings: now taking away the
               co-essentiality, on account of him who uses it in an evil way for the destruction of
               the substances, now accepting it and making a defence to his name<pb n="336"/>sake.
               In addition to these things he has regarding the Holy Spirit also left utterances
               that do not at all beseem a spiritual man, exiling Him from the adorable Godhead, and
               reckoning Him with created and ministering nature in some lower place." What then?
               When we hear these things, shall we bring a just accusation against Athanasius on the
               ground that by his defence he extolled and praised a man who thus fell from the right
               standard of accuracy? or shall we accept him the more on account of this high
               spiritual service of his and the skilful policy by which he did not allow the Arians
               to pride themselves in such a man and thereby hurl the more simple down into the pit?
               In all things the methods and actions of the fathers were directed to the end that
               the orthodox faith might be spread abroad and that this might prevail in the
               churches, and to the end that they might hinder the plots of the heretics, and might
               bar every opening for deceit against them, and that they might remove the stones from
               the royal road that no one might go astray. I have given vent to these utterances, —
               I have grieved in my spirit as it is somewhere written over the wonderful Mitras,
               who, as was said by the wise Paul to the Corinthians, suffers fools though he is
               wise. For this reason I said like Job, "Wherefore neither will I refrain my mouth; I
               will speak in the anguish of my spirit; I will open my mouth being <pb n="337"/>
               constrained by the bitterness of my soul." I beg and entreat your holinesses, since
               still even now I have not had an opportunity of speaking with him (if I shall. find
               an opportunity, I will not neglect it), yourselves to fill my place, and suggest to
               his smallness of soul not only these few things which I have said, but all that it is
               in the power of your understandings to say. But, if I too "have erred" (I will again
               quote the words of Job), "and a deceiver dwells with me," "teach me: and I will be
               dumb"; and "I will lay mine hand upon my mouth: and, having once spoken, I will not
               go on to speak a second time." </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
