<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To John and John the Brethren, Presbyters
               and Archimandrites</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">337-42</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.12">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John and John the brethren, presbyters
               and archimandrites.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 72nd
               letter.</head>
            <p> Truly I say, and you ought certainly to believe me when I say, that it is not as the
               result of effort or of cogitation that I proceed to utter praises of you whenever I
               write an epistle to you, but out of the abundance of my heart according to the Lord's
               saying that does not lie my mouth is opened to speak. Wherefore, as soon as I reflect
               upon your actions, I find it hard to draw myself away from them and I continue to
               think of them, and I cannot bear to keep silence. I am in the same state as men who
               happen upon the <pb n="338"/> sight of a lovely body, and then, before they have
               sated themselves with the beauty or sufficiently gazed at it, are separated from it
               by force by someone. In order to explain to you the. astringent and instructive
               character of the salt that is in you, I will say this much only. You are honoured men
               and capable after the manner of great stars that shine and give light, such as were
               our Peter and Isaiah the renowned men, seeing that you do not remain hid, but with
               them give forth rays that are like theirs, or else in a small degree inferior, and
               give light to "them that sit in darkness and in the shadow of death "as it is
               written: but now the scarceness and lack of such men makes you more honoured and
               causes you to be more highly reputed than they. Do not therefore behave haughtily to
               us in our hunger. It is your actions that we want, not you. Remain in the flesh. In
               fact not only when writing an epistle, but also when engaged in any ordinary
               conversation, if I ever do converse with anyone, I bring forward the mention of you
               like some pleasant odour, and I please both myself and those that hear. Do not
               therefore think that the words written are as you say the words of a scribe who has
               scattered "things old and things new," but the words of love and of need only: since
               neither am I among those who praise at random, nor are you among those who delight in
               praises, and the subject of the letter itself is not concerned with praises. <pb
                  n="339"/> I incurred a great debt of gratitude to our God and Saviour Christ when
               I learned that you the saintly presbyter had been restored to health after the deadly
               sickness, and that you are in tangible reality officiating in the rational
               sacrifices. I am much surprised that you say that yow were in doubt about the letter
               that was written by the saintly bishops who are settled here. It was in fact free
               from all misunderstanding: especially in the matter of giving authority to the
               believers there and in particular to the solitary order to receive or not receive
               those who wish truly to repent: and, what is very important, that the forgiveness
               should await the assent of everyone, so that it should also require the unanimous
               opinion of the bishops who are absent. When all these things are put together, they
               both make those who made answer to the question blameless, and, when the precepts
               contained in the letter have been carried out, the reconciliation of all remains to
               be accomplished. I do not mention that the authors of the epistle followed the
               regulations of Timothy? of holy memory in all points. I do not say these things as if
               I had myself given counsel upon the: matter. No man has known our place of abode:at
               all or where we are, except only those whom we informed for the sake of the necessary
               requirements of our life. However the devout presbyter Thomas, having been invited by
               the bishops, in order that he might not be thought to be a haughty <pb n="340"/> and
               unsociable man, heard and answered them, and in proportion to the power that is in
               him often sowed the seed of caution in those that were willing. As to the sign that
               was seen in the sky, it was seen here also in the same way and for many days. Among
               wise men outside an appearance of this kind consisting in the rising of an unusual
               star is called a <foreign>dokias</foreign> or <foreign>krinthiya</foreign>: and, as
               thought even by those who have attained knowledge in such things, it betokens a
               change in affairs. In accordance with the purport of the divine words, the aforesaid
               star presented the shape of a rod: thus leading us, so to speak, to remember Him who
               says, "If they profane my statutes and keep not my commandments, I will visit their
               lawlessnesses with a rod, and their iniquities with stripes." Pray therefore that the
               other statement may be also added and applied upon our repentance, "But my grace will
               I not remove from them, nor will I do iniquity in my truth." Let your sanctities know
               that there was also an earthquake here on the fourteenth of October: a thing which in
               general rarely happens in the regions of Egypt; and no ordinary earthquake, but
               violent enough to shake buildings and cause them to tremble for a long space of time,
               passing over the small ones only, while everyone so to speak felt it. In certain
               cities of Egypt, especially in Athrib, a pestilence and plague has also been reported
               to have occurred. The books that were sent me by the presbyter <pb n="341"/> Stephen
               of God-loving memory I have not been able to look through, by reason of the shifting
               of the places in which necessity causes me to be. Indeed, as soon as I read some
               part, and think that I have collected some part towards the dissertation against the
               heretics at which I am working, often some report reaches me and makes me remove
               elsewhere, and what has been collected is annihilated. I am in the same state as
               Israel, when it was once under the hand of Midian: and as soon as they had sown
               warriors used to come up against them and encamp against them, as is written, and
               destroy the produce of the earth! Therefore it is necessary for me like Gideon to
               collect a few grains of wheat now and a few later, and pound these because I do not
               dare to thresh, since I flee from before the face of Midian; for this also I will add
               from the same scripture. As to what you say has happened in the city of Cyrrhus, this
               news has come to us too; indeed the minute has also been sent in which he who in a
               Jewish spirit holds the presidency of that city made a confession to the effect that
               Diodorus and Theodore and the detestable gang of Nestorius differ in no way from the
               Chalcedonian synod, which like a seed is justly and truly traced to those who sowed
               tares upon <pb n="342"/> the good seed. And this the minister of falsehood rightly
               confessed. Whereas, when you wrote before about Ascalon, I did not write any reply,
               being interrupted by constant anxieties, do not think to yourselves that any action
               taken by you is displeasing to me: for I am glad that there also you have again begun
               to plant a good plantation of faith, Even though the Philistines when they see us
               say, "Behold! the Hebrews come forth out of their holes where they hid themselves,"
               we like Jonathan will say, "Come up because the Lord hath delivered them into the
               hands of Israel." If therefore it shall at any time happen that we remain silent
               upon receiving anything written by you, do not think that it is because it is
               displeasing to us that we have remained silent. All things done by you are pleasing,
               and very pleasing. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
