<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3113">To Proclus and Eusebuna the Bishops</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">342-45</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.13">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Proclus and Eusebuna the bishops.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 3rd book the 35th
               letter.</head>
            <p> It was not without sorrow nor with a mind free from affliction that [ read the
               letter of your love of God: but, as is sung in the Psalms, "My heart was disturbed
               within me." <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> But what? If, even after
               taking all these offences that are so manifest into account we allow him to be
               purified by association only as Cyrus said, he will reckon this a <pb n="343"/> small
               thing, and a thing that does not injure the soul on the most important points, and in
               the matter of its very salvation. Let him therefore, if he likes, ask the Theologian
               Gregory, and he will answer clearly: for I do not know how it is that, when besides
               the holy scripture you pride yourselves in the teachings of your countrymen, and can
               obtain from them instruction in what is right, you have had recourse to my poverty.
               What therefore says the mouth of Christ, the mouth that at all times instructs the
               church, and catches souls out of the pit of destruction, upon the principle that we
               must not associate in any way whatever with the adversaries who make an accusation
               and a charge out of the fact that those who stand upright are not perishing with
               them? [Here follows the citation from Greg. Naz. given on p. 270 with the variation
               "we" for "they".] How is it therefore that the excellent Cyrus asks for association
               only as he says to be permitted him like a man innocent on the other matters? And how
               is it that after confirming the impiety in writing he wishes to become an orthodox
               man not enrolled in writing and in a corner? Or do we not hear the great Basil saying
               in his letters, "But, if they say that they have repented, let them show their
               written form of repentance and an anathema of the faith of Constantinople, and
               separation from the heretics, and let them not deceive those that are simple"? Look
               therefore, I beg, to these columns of the church and your progenitors, and emulate
               their glory. For they are your progenitors, after the true and spiritual family: and
               <pb n="344"/> for you to put their glory to shame is in truth a deed of great
               shame, and worthy of the final and endless fire. Cappadocia is in danger of becoming
               a tale of laughter in our age. For indeed, if, as I pray may not happen, you be
               caught in those sophistical traps, the enemies of the truth will count the latter as
               added to the former and will laugh and say, "Cyrus has lapsed: Soteric has fallen:
               Proclus and Eusebuna after many circuitous courses and useless movements have been
               cast down into the same ditch: and the whole trap has been spread abroad. Great
               champions of the faith Cappadocia displays to us." Therefore, even though there were
               nothing grievous to expect in the world to come, are these things tolerable to the
               ears of the pious? Will they not seem fraught with lamentations and tears to those
               that hope in Christ? Will they not mourn and instead of their garments rend their
               hearts, as the prophetic text says?" Be not, I beg and pray you, be not the cause of
               such lamentation. Short is our time: and "yet a very little while and He that cometh
               will come and will not tarry," and "will reward every man according to his works":
               and, while we are now gaping after the shadowy things of this world, He will come
               upon us and seize us in the midst of our pleasures: whereas we ought to have gone
               while watching. For, as the end of the life here finds us, so will He that shall
               judge us see us on the great effulgent day of the last judgment. May it come about
               that we are ready when <pb n="345"/> we appear before Him, and that we find Him
               gentle, and not pronouncing the sentence that condemns, but that which acquits, and
               giving us a share in the good things that are prepared for those that have hoped in
               Him! I have committed these things to writing in fear and trembling, and with caution
               lest anywhere I should think or utter anything contrary to the divine laws, and be
               found with those that are accused by the prophet as perverting justice, or as
               possessing two weights contrary to the law, and to be weighing the words of the
               Spirit not worthily nor intelligently, but inclining the balances of truth like a
               huckster, and making myself liable to the divine sentence. Pray therefore, saintly
               men, that I may receive forgiveness from Christ the great God and our Saviour, both
               for what has been written and for what has been omitted. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
