<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3121">To John and Philoxenus and Thomas the
               Bishops, Confessors on the Hill of Marde</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">345-50</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.14">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John and Philoxenus and Thomas the
               bishops, confessors on the hill of Marde.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 4th book the 21st
               letter.</head>
            <p> On reading your sanctities' letter I thought of Elijah the Tishbite prophet, who
               when persecuted by impiety betook himself to the hill of Horeb, and as a reward for
               his tribulation gained the privilege of seeing and conversing with God, so far as is
               possible <pb n="346"/> for men. When He that knows all things before they are as it
               is written approached him like a father, and assumed the appearance of ignorance in
               order to comfort him, like a father who comforts his beloved son by playing with him,
               and in order to lighten the weariness and distress that he had incurred from the long
               journey, and said to him, "What doest thou here, Elijah?", he stirred up the zeal
               that was blazing in him and answered very hotly (and that though speaking to Him who
               knows all things and whom nothing escapes), "I have been zealous for the Lord the
               All-Ruler, because the sons of Israel have forsaken thee. Thine altars they have
               thrown down: and thy prophets they have slain with the sword. And I only am left: and
               they seek my life to take it away." And He put fresh heart in him by revealing
               Himself to him in mightier fashion and initiating him in more perfect knowledge.
               Therefore I am convinced and assured that your love of God also, who have imitated
               the same pattern of zeal, and walk in the footsteps of a like mode of life, who
               engage as combatants not only in the contest of confession after the manner of
               martyrs, but also in the patient labours of the ascetic life, will also be gratified
               with the conversation and sight of God, and that you will render the hill called in
               the tongue of the country Marde no meaner than the hill of Horeb, but even more
               glorious than that. For by drawing to you companies of holy monks, and <pb n="347"/>
               of men who are living the coenobitic life while cleaving to orthodoxy, and by
               recalling and healing like shepherds and fathers at the same time those who have
               transgressed or otherwise become remiss and been swept away to follow the violence of
               the time you have also appropriated to your hill the glory of another higher and
               holier hill that is situated in Jerusalem, I mean on the corner-stone of Zion, the
               watch-house that is higher than all the earth, which you have surpassed by making
               more peculiar to yourselves in a higher sense the grace and title of the episcopate
               also, which were given you already by the Spirit, but are confirmed by works every
               day, as the Apostle says. Indeed I see many running and hastening to the summit of
               your hill also, even as to that hill, and saying the words of the prophecy that have
               been carried out in actual deeds, "Come let us go up to the hill of the Lord and to
               the house of the God of Jacob, and He will show us His way and we will walk in it."
               And I have confidence in saying that they will not be disappointed of their hope. For
               you teach those who stand to keep the orthodox faith, and to practise a devout and
               just life: while to those who have been led away to error you teach the way of
               repentance by giving them forgiveness canonical and legal. Wherefore also, showing
               humility in this point too, you ask <pb n="348"/> our meanness how those who have
               been baptized by this heresy that now prevails ought to be received. To this I made
               answer in writing at an earlier time also when I was living in the city of the
               Antiochenes, because certain persons in unthinking fervour had supposed that these
               ought to be perfected by chrism, just as the custom is for Arians and Fighters
               against the Spirit to be received. I think that the religious presbyter and
               archimandrite John also, who sent me your revered letter, has with him the treatise
               that was written by me on this point. But I will now also in the same way tell your
               sanctities in a few words a thing of which you too are not unaware: that at the holy
               oecumenical synod that assembled at Ephesus and effected the deposition of Nestorius,
               who raised the heresy of this Diphysite man-worship to a higher position, when
               Charisius a presbyter who came from the province of the Lydians, and registered his
               fathers' house at Philadelphia, with many others who had been swept into the error of
               that heresy, presented petitions to it and exposed the creed previously concocted by
               the impious Theodore of Mopsuestia, it both received him and admitted him to
               clemency, not making any canonical pronouncement in their case about chrism or about
               anything else of this kind: but it lawfully decided that they were to renounce the
               heresy itself in writing and condemn it by anathema, and so be received and become
               members of Christ's flock. <pb n="349"/> And all from that time to the present day
               have been received on these terms by the orthodox bishops who lived at different
               times; who did not do anything further with regard to them, nor abrogate the covenant
               confirmed by the fathers, or lay down any additional commandment beyond what were
               laid down, as Paul somewhere says in writing to the Galatians. Whence also a certain
               Theodotus, one of the bishops of Palestine, because he presumed to anoint certain
               persons, was repudiated and expelled, both by Timothy of holy memory, archbishop of
               the city of the Alexandrines, and by all who shared his opinions and were zealous
               with zeal that is "according to knowledge" and is pleasing to God. To remove in any
               matter whatsoever the landmarks that our fathers set up is wholly unlawful, even if a
               man is deceived by considerations that seem to be rather on the right side. Upon this
               point these things are sufficient for your perfection in Christ. But I beg you also
               to extend your diligent watchfulness which becomes shepherds to the God-loving
               archimandrites and devout solitaries, those that are near you and those that are
               geographically far from you, and not allow anyone to disturb those that are more
               simple, in the matter of the question about. the incorruptibility of the body of our
               Lord and God and Saviour Jesus Christ, which was stirred up among us by Julian who
               wantonly became impious, and has departed from the life here, but <pb n="350"/> shall
               answer for his blasphemy and evil belief to the Judge of all, and shall then regret
               that he was not converted to a right state of mind by the warnings that he received,
               and this though he was admonished in a gentle and brotherly manner, as your
               sanctities also who saw what was written will bear witness. It has come to my
               knowledge that certain men who do not perform any service as is written except things
               that are vain have torn away an occasional line or two from what I wrote, and have
               tried to lead astray those that are easily cheated. And no wonder, when even about
               the wise Paul's epistles Peter the divine, who was instigated by the same Spirit of
               concord and apostleship, wrote, "which the unlearned and unstable wrest to their
               destruction, as they do also the other scriptures." Therefore you will do an act
               worthy of you if you write a common letter to all who have been driven from the holy
               cloisters, condemning the unlawful statements, and warning them to adhere to the
               teachings of the holy fathers which our meanness has cited. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
