<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Sergius, Bishop of Cyrrhus, and Marion,
               Bishop of Sura</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">350-59</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.15">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Sergius, bishop of Cyrrhus, and Marion,
               bishop of Sura.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 4th book the 81st
               letter.</head>
            <p> I have read your sanctities' letter in no negligent way but very carefully indeed:
               for it was such as to <pb n="351"/> attract even those whose mind wanders and who
               stare vacantly at the stage-play of the life here and cleave to it. <add><emph>And
                  after other things.</emph></add> As to the sub-deacon who has fallen under a
               decree of separation from the miserable wicked Cyriac, if he repent of the sins that
               he has committed, the merciful sentence of God will absolve him through your
               holinesses. And, if anyone else also has committed or shall commit any such sin, as
               we pray may not be the case, he shall in an exactly similar way attain absolution
               according to your legal judgment, on account of Him who does "not wish the death of
               the sinner so much as that he be converted and live." In fact even in the ordinance
               regarding Cyriac we have mixed with the severity the mild drug of penitence by
               inviting him also to recognise the sin that has been committed. For we hear Paul
               saying in his epistle to the Romans as follows: "Behold therefore the mildness and
               severity of God; on them which fell severity, but upon thee the mildness of God if
               thou continue in mildness." For by everything this is what we are taught, to look to
               Him who sought the sheep that was lost, and bore it on His shoulders and carried it
               up and counted it in the flock of those that are being saved. Greatly did I rejoice
               in the Lord, as the wise Paul somewhere said, that the religious presbyter and
               archimandrite John, trained as he is to do all things with understanding and guided
               by the divine Spirit, <pb n="352"/> brought first to your sanctities the letter
               written by me to the saintly bishops Philoxenus, Thomas, and John, who were then
               living on the hill called that of Marde. For my part I say that your ears and your
               tranquil and thoughtful mind, which is built up with all devoutness, are like a
               furnace of fire, in that they have the capacity of distinguishing what is alloyed
               from what is sound. Wherefore also I have gladly accepted your action in keeping with
               you the letter written by me to them, and first giving me the benefit of your advice.
               If therefore it is in order to cause fear and trembling in those who have turned
               their eyes towards penitence that your sanctities are making the delay in the matter
               of the reception of the children who were baptized by heretics, I concur with your
               purpose: only unless perhaps the long delay cause those who have turned their eyes
               towards penitence to become inert, and despair of being received by you, and return
               to their first vomit as it is written, and wallow again in the same mire."
               Nevertheless the form of penitence that was once approved by the holy oecumenical
               synod that assembled at Ephesus in the case of those who have been baptized by men
               who hold the hateful profane doctrines of Nestorius must be maintained in full force,
               and there must be no thought either of second baptism or of chrism. Indeed those who
               did this when the impiety introduced as an innovation at Chalcedon first prevailed
               were repudiated both by the <pb n="353"/> holy Timothy who fed the great
               Christ-loving city of the Alexandrines in saintly fashion and by all the orthodox
               bishops, as having walked outside the royal and lawful road. But, if we are now going
               to discuss the question in what way those who are baptized by men who divide the one
               Christ into two natures after the ineffable union ought to be received, those who
               observe our actions carefully will say to us, and very rightly, "Why did you
               repudiate such an inquiry at the time when the impious wicked Flavian was driven from
               the see of the city of the Antiochenes, and all the bishops who deposed him were
               assembled together?" They will also blame us for receiving those who were ordained by
               him in the orders which they then held on merely anathematizing and renouncing the
               heresy. No one is so devoid of the sacred teachings of orthodoxy as not to call
               baptism given by any heresy imperfect and spurious: but those who know this look at
               the regulations of the holy fathers, and reflect that according to the character of
               the heresy treatment also must be applied, and the stain must be purged and expiated
               either by another baptism or by chrism, or by an anathema of the heresy, and the
               judgment of the orthodox priests and reception by them. The utterance of those who
               officiate with orthodox mind, whatever it may be, is accompanied also by the curative
               treatment and grace of the Spirit; since the word of the baptizer. perfects baptism
               also and causes the Spirit to come down upon the water, on account of Him who
               graciously allowed <pb n="354"/> us who creep upon earth to share in this power. For
               He cleanses the washing of water by His word, as Paul says in his epistle to the
               Ephesians. So also the word of the anointer is mingled with the chrism, and applies
               curative treatment and brings the grace of the Spirit into play. After the
               same fashion also an anathema of the heresy, when enjoined upon those who utter the
               condemnation by order of orthodox high-priests, and proffered by the mouth of those,
               as well as entrance into the holy of holies performed in accordance with the judgment
               of those who receive them brings healing to the sore, and causes the pure and sincere
               grace of the Spirit to flash invisibly upon those who have been accepted. With these
               things the sanction from above is also identified in the giving of the decision,
               according to the commandment plainly laid down in the Gospels of Him who said to
               Peter, "I will give thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatsoever thou shalt
               bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and whatsoever thou shalt loose on earth
               shall be loosed in heaven," and repeated the same again to all the disciples and
               said, "All things that ye shall bind on earth shall be bound in heaven, and all
               things that ye shall loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven." For there is nothing
               lawfully said by the orthodox high-priests, and performed in accordance with the
               divine commandments and canons, that is not full of the Holy Spirit, as David
               also the spiritual singer said, <pb n="355"/> "I opened my mouth and breathed in
               spirit because I longed for thy commandments." I beg your sanctities also to consult
               carefully the words written by me in Antiochus' city against those who dare to
               re-anoint contrary to the law, and to reflect what unhallowed objections we met on
               their part, and that we have not held different opinions at different times, but
               always have the same thoughts, endeavouring as we do all the days of our life to
               guide our short-sighted mind by the writings of our holy fathers and their lawful
               regulations. If you like, assign a certain time for converts from heresy to the
               orthodox faith, in order that they may expiate their sin by tears and weeping, being
               admitted, that is, to expiation through your holy prayers and entreaties, and the
               outstretching of your saintly hands. Wherefore like Jacob the divine patriarch show
               them the rod of orthodox teaching, which is white and shines with sound doctrines,
               and is cleared of every green and dead hue of heresy: in order that these rational
               sheep, fired by your teachings, may cast from them all the murkiness and darkness of
               heresy, and in its stead put on the white and full light of the orthodox faith: and
               may clothe themselves in the many colours of virtues, and may cease to be counted
               among the heretics unknown sheep, and may mix with those that are known, making up
               the one flock of the one Shepherd and God and our Saviour Christ. <pb n="356"/> I for
               my part have written these things to you the ministers of Christ, and careful
               stewards of God's mysteries, But it will rest with your discriminations at the
               present time to take what steps you like in the existing circumstances. Only please
               communicate what we have written to our brothers and fellow-ministers who brought
               before us the question concerning this present matter, in order that it may not be
               thought that we did not deign to answer your sanctities: and, after you have examined
               all the circumstances conjointly, take the right course. As to the mad dogs who have
               followed the witless Romanus and the stony Julian we have not a word to say, seeing
               that, while we walk according to the law in all respects, both in doctrines and in
               canonical actions, they are absurdly spreading these contrary opinions concerning us.
               For neither will we for our part by reason of rivalry with those filthy men abandon
               the middle of the royal road and walk upon the rocks on the other side. We must
               listen to Him who cries with a loud voice through Isaiah the prophet to those who
               keep His laws, "Hearken unto me, ye that know judgment, my people in whose heart is
               my law; fear not the reproach of men, and be not overcome by their derision; for like
               a garment shall it be consumed by lapse of time, and like wool shall it be eaten by a
               moth; but my righteousness shall be for ever, and my salvation to generations." <pb
                  n="357"/> This point also I have thought necessary to bring to the knowledge of
               your perfections in Christ our God: that the religious presbyter and archimandrite of
               the holy cloister of the blessed Bassus has sent two of his devout monks to the great
               Christ-loving city of Alexander, bearing a letter which states that they are in
               straits with regard to the sacred ministry, and in want of presbyters and deacons.
               Wherefore also he begged me to write to your holinesses, or else to some other of the
               saintly bishops who share the same persecution with us, in order that you may satisfy
               this their need by your saintly and lawful hand. And, since it was then the winter
               season, the letter remained, as I have been informed, in the same great city of the
               Alexandrines, because it was no longer possible for voyagers to cross the sea.
               Therefore I beg your sanctities not to be remiss in supplying such a need. In all
               good things it beseems you to show courage as well as to give comfort, and to be
               first in every action that is on the right side. For I intend, if God pleases, to
               write about this through you also, in order that either you or others with your
               sanction may carry out the duty which thus presents itself and is urgent: that is
               upon the archimandrites presenting with their testimony those who ought to be duly
               advanced to the ministry of the sacraments, lest any take necessity as an excuse for
               being appointed deacons and priests without discrimination and casually, without
               having any <pb n="358"/> virtue to qualify them for this, except that they desire the
               priesthood and diaconate. Therefore, now that you know these things, speaking with
               God's permission, I beg you, when the winter has passed, as soon as sailing begins,
               to write us a careful answer, saying what your opinion is on all the matters
               mentioned in the epistle, and to put our meanness in a safer position through your
               understanding in the Lord. For the safety of the learned and Christ-loving scholastic
               Maximin we offer prayers of thanksgiving as sacrifices at all times, as we also
               stated in the previous letter: and we moreover give him loving greeting through your
               sanctities. Against the last fatuous work of the wickedly impious Julian, which
               promulgates the same arguments upon the same subjects, I have not up to to-day begun
               to write, although it is refuted beforehand by what has been already written by me
               before, so that everyone who meets with it will know its feebleness and the futility
               of the erroneous phantasy which he confessed. During the whole time of the summer,
               and that though I have been hiding in corners, I have never ceased being worried by
               constant letters from men who in various ways ask different questions at different
               times, and beg to have now scriptural expres<pb n="359"/>sions, now doctrinal
               theories explained to them. Also the loneliness of solitude, and the fact that I have
               not men at hand to serve as scribes when I want it in addition to the other things
               hinder me from writing. But I think that I shall be strengthened through your saintly
               prayers, and that I shall be sufficient for everything, if Christ our God grant me
               life and grace from above. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
