<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3063">To Theotecnus, Presbyter and
               <foreign>archiatros</foreign></title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">286-90</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.4">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Theotecnus the presbyter and
               <foreign>archiatros</foreign>.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 6th book the
               161st letter.</head>
            <p> With regard to the case of Mark the devout monk and presbyter you have written
               throughout wisely and with the religious feeling and the intelligence that belongs to
               you. Know however that, even if we had not the instance of the saintly bishop
               Eleusinius, we have many other examples provided by the holy fathers in the times of
               the Arians, which charge us not to repel those who have been often perverted, and
               recurred to the evil thing as before, but, as far as is possible, to allow them the
               last repentance. It ts related in church histories that Asterius, who was a sophist
               and author among the Arians," was often received and often returned to his vomit,
               insomuch that this expression of his is cited in histories. He cried out lying on his
               face before everyone and saying, "Trample upon me, the salt which has lost its
               savour." Hosius also, the bishop of <pb n="287"/> Corduba, the old man, whom
               Athanasius who is among the saints often called "a man of goodly old age," was often
               perverted and overcome by the times and again received, and many others. Therefore
               with Mark also this same principle should hold good, and he should be received on the
               basis of a written document, upon his anathematizing the heresies of the Diphysites
               and of the Massalians, together with the impious men themselves and their impiety.
               For indeed "both the impious man and his impiety are equally hated before God," as a
               wise man said; although the fathers as pilots from motives of policy received some
               men upon the impiety alone being anathematized (I refer to the
               <foreign>pepragmena</foreign> or things done at Chalcedon), thinking that those
               who did them were also anathematized at the same time in silence, When this is done
               it is absolutely necessary that the office of superintendent should also be entrusted
               to Mark, seeing that the majority of the brethren and, if one may so say, all are
               asking for him as you write. Indeed after considering the matter from many points of
               view I have come to this conclusion, that it is better that he should be canonically
               received now while he is humbled, than that, desired as he is by many persons, he
               should betake himself perhaps to the royal among cities, and do things that many are
               wont to do, and with money buy independence, and get the monastery <pb n="288"/>
               under his control with liberty to follow the impiety with head bare and unashamed. I
               have also received the letter that you wrote about the hateful opinions of Romanus,
               in which you state that you have read the tome written by me cursorily. But I wish
               you to read it yet again and pay attention to the contents, and to condemn more
               strongly the impious man, and induce the saintly bishops also to do the same, and
               repudiate that wicked man by a common synodical letter addressed by them to my
               meanness. There is yet another thing that I had almost forgotten to make known to
               your religiousness, viz., that the devout Mark in what he said displayed an
               appearance of shrinking from the superintendence of the monastery, and seeking only
               to live at peace, and besides this asserted further that a royal letter had assigned
               the monastery to the apostolic see of the city of the Antiochenes, and that the
               clergymen in Tarsus had a spite against them, and prevented them from lesson-reading
               and the offering of oblations if they were in need, the holy remnants of the
               bloodless sacrifice being often lacking to them. And I said to him and to the man who
               was with him, "You cannot raise these matters now: but for the present you Mark must
               certainly show true repentance by a form of satisfaction and by a change in your
               deeds, and then, if you have the witness of time to the blamelessness of your future
               conduct, we will also go on to settle the said points, if <pb n="289"/> anyone try to
               act perversely towards you, and to do any spiteful and injurious action to your holy
               monastery." Therefore, in order that the questions raised upon these subjects too may
               not be unknown to you, I have added these few words in the letter. Moreover on second
               thoughts I have determined to warn your religiousness of this further point also:
               that, when I was composing the letter to the metropolitan, and I thought that the
               number of brethren living in the monastery was large, I came to the following
               decision: that is that the entrusting of the superintendence to the devout Mark
               should depend on the opinion of the majority. But I learn that there are not more
               than fifteen: and distinct information has been sent me that one or two only are
               thought to be opposed to him, and that it is certainly he who ought to receive the
               post of superintendent, upon giving complete satisfaction with sincerity and with his
               whole heart, so far as men can see. We have also sent an <foreign>ison</foreign> or
               copy of the form of satisfaction which our notaries have drawn up, having compiled it
               from other forms that were previously composed by me in the cases of various persons.
               The God-loving Basil bishop of Pompeiupolis has informed us that he has been
               compelled by the God-loving Dionysius bishop of the metropolis to undertake an
               unlawful laying on of hands or ordination. If this is really so, it is also proper
               that your love of <pb n="290"/> God and the religious presbyter and logothete John
               should take care that it too receive correction. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
