<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Dionysius Bishop of Tarsus</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">290-94</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.5">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Dionysius bishop of Tarsus.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, the 6th book the 178th
               letter.</head>
            <p> Having by many circuitous and roundabout methods succeeded in mastering the various
               aspects of the case of the devout monk and presbyter Mark, and having considered all
               the circumstances that had come to my knowledge, and finding that he is repeatedly
               changing, I remembered Him who speaks through Jeremiah the prophet and says to Israel
               who had sinned, "Behold! I will enter into judgment with thee when thou sayest, 'I
               have not sinned'; because thou hast been very scornful so as to repeat thy ways"; and
               again, "if a man put away his wife, and she go from him and become another man's,
               shall she return to him again?"; and again, "Lift up thine eyes to uprightness and
               see where thou hast not been defiled." But the same may be seen holding forth the
               broad path of repentance and saying through Isaiah the gracious words, "I held forth
               my hands all the day unto a disobedient and gainsaying people, who walk in a way that
               is not good but after their sins"; and the day is the whole of this life according to
               Paul the Apostle who says, "Exhort yourselves daily while it is called to-day, that
               none of <pb n="291"/> you may be hardened by the deceitfulness of sin." Therefore my
               conclusion and judgment is that an opportunity for penitence be given to the said
               devout presbyter and monk Mark, in order that he may anathematize in writing the
               heresies in which he has shared, viz., that of those who divide our one Lord and God
               Jesus Christ into two natures after the union, and that also of the Massalians with
               the persons themselves and the doctrines, as we also here caused him to draw up a
               form of satisfaction? here in writing. For indeed we find certain men in the times of
               the Arians who removed themselves from the communion of the holy fathers and fell
               away to the error of the heretics, and were again converted and were not repelled.
               However the devout Mark must henceforth be cautious and know clearly that it is not
               possible for him to retain our communion and that of those who do not think the same
               as we do, seeing that Paul who had Christ speaking in him warns us to shun even
               communications with such men, saying, [Here follows the citation given on p. 264].
               And John the speaker of divine things writing an epistle and holding the same opinion
               speaks thus; [ Here follows the citation given on p. 263]. And Basil, who was moved
               by the same Spirit as these, and is an accurate teacher of the sacred laws, wrote in
               the letter to Urbicius the monk as follows; [Here follows the citation given on p.
               259]. If the circumstances of the present case concerned <pb n="292"/> only the
               person of the devout presbyter and monk Mark, I would perhaps have closed the letter
               with these texts. But, since it is a habitation of many brethren, and a headship of
               rational souls that have taken upon them the philosophic life, in singing of the
               comeliness of which and the pleasure that it gives to God and in chanting those
               harmonious spiritual songs the prophet David sang crying, "Behold! what is good and
               what beautiful except that brethren should dwell together, as Ointment upon the head
               that runs down upon the beard, the beard of Aaron?", it is your sanctity's duty to
               look at the number of the brethren dwelling in the monastery, and to comply with the
               opinion of those who are the majority, provided firstly that the often-mentioned
               devout Mark did not intrude himself by force and violence, and secondly that he is
               not by his association disturbing and dissolving the bond of unity, to speak in the
               language of the Apostle, and the concord of those who are living a life that has no
               association with the world's confusions, and is beautiful and lovely and resembles
               ointment. Repentance is not a thing of the same kind as the spiritual headship and
               superintendence of a monastery. Such men must be of approved character, and men who
               have walked in all virtue, according to the utterance of the Lord which says in the
               Gospels, "Who then is the faithful and wise bondman, whom his lord set over his house
               to give them the food in due season? blessed is the bondman <pb n="293"/> whom his
               lord shall come and find so doing." I therefore upon the devout monk and presbyter
               Mark showing penitence in canonical form and confessing his sin have opened to him
               the door of repentance. But it rests with you, as I said, to determine the question
               of the headship and superintendence of the monastery, according to the opinion of the
               brothers who form the majority: because in such cases it is the more fitting course
               to acquiesce in the wish of the greater number. This I say because I have received a
               written petition pleading for the devout presbyter and monk Mark, and containing
               signatures given by the devout clergymen and monks of the same said monastery, which
               are in number ten only. Therefore, since it was not my part, being at a distance, to
               give a judgment upon the details of such a question, I have of necessity committed to
               your holiness the duty of making a detailed investigation of the matter. Considering
               therefore both points, I mean the superintendence of the cloister, and the gain or
               loss in regard to the brothers themselves, give a proper decision upon the disputed
               questions with help and inspiration and grace from above, without which it is
               impossible for any right action to be done. As to the devout presbyter Julian, the
               brother of the God-loving bishop Serenus, I forbear to say anything, being convinced
               that after such an experience he would never have dared to convey false <pb n="294"/>
               information to the pious ears of our serene Christ-loving king. If in addition to
               what has already been done he have presumed to do this also, he falls by divine and
               human laws, from which there is no possibility of escape. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
