<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3088">Against Those Who Say that Converts from Diphysitism Should be Re-anointed</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">294-317</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.6">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same against those who say that men who have
               communicated with the Synod of Chalcedon, and are penitent and anathematize those who
               call our one Lord and God Jesus Christ two natures after the ineffable union and come
               over to the orthodox faith must be re-anointed.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 9th book the 1st
               letter.</head>
            <p> I for my part am not conscious in myself of any quality such as that to which you
               bear witness, when you say that the fame of our meanness has gone out over all the
               earth, and that we are one competent to teach and to heal the afflictions of the
               soul: but I know clearly that, if I utter anything that is on the right side and is
               capable of profiting, it is out of the writings and labours of the God-clad educators
               of the church that I utter and speak this: and I think that I hear plainly from God
               what is said by the wise Paul, "And what hast thou that thou didst not receive? but
               if thou didst indeed receive it why <pb n="295"/> boastest thou as if thou didst not
               receive it?" For I for my part am not competent to break the bread of knowledge for
               those that are hungry: on the contrary I gather the food of learning by picking up
               the crumbs of the orthodox shepherds, and so I seem to give this to others also.
               Wherefore it is from their labours that I make answer to your affection also, and it
               is by adducing their utterances that I find a solution of the doubts that have been
               raised. Whereas you say that those who assembled at Chalcedon, and divided our one
               Lord and God and Saviour Jesus Christ by calling Him two natures after the union fell
               under the anathema laid down against abominable godless heresies, and that men coming
               from them are not to be received, but their "end is to be burned," because they are
               devoid of the grace of the Holy Spirit, know that you have missed the truth. That by
               denial of the faith they are stripped of every spiritual heavenly gift it is
               impossible for me to gainsay; but that when they repudiate and renounce the heresy
               and condemn it by anathema, and come over to the church, they are according to the
               ordinances of the fathers to be received, I will try to show in what I am about to
               say (by the church I too mean the confession which is founded on the true faith,
               since Peter also heard the words, "Thou art Cephas and upon this rock will I build my
               church, and the gates of Hades shall <pb n="296"/> not prevail against it": and I
               find that Gregory the Theologian also says of the Arians who formerly held the
               temples of God, "They have the house, we the dweller in it: they the temples, we the
               privilege of becoming temples of the living God"). Now, when Cyprian held a prominent
               position at Carthage in Africa, and God-loving bishops assembled there, who were in
               number eighty-seven, some from the same Africa itself, some from Mauretania and
               Numidia, they determined that those who come from all heresies should be perfected by
               the true baptism of the church, as if they had not been baptized at all, not
               distinguishing the character of each of the heresies, but bringing all under one
               pronouncement. It was from God-loving zeal that these adopted this resolution: as is
               clearly shown by the words which the holy Cyprian who has been mentioned wrote in
               epistles to Juvian and Quintus and Magnus, where he also includes a reference to
               those who are baptized on their beds during sickness. And soon afterwards Dionysius
               to whom it fell at that time to feed the church of the city of the Alexandrines,
               writing to Dionysius his namesake and Stephen, who presided over the holy church of
               the city of the Romans, made a distinction, saying that those who had been baptized
               in the name of the three substances, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, even
               though it were by heretics <pb n="297"/> that they were baptized, but still such as
               confess the three substances, should not be re-baptized: but converts from the other
               heresies should certainly be perfected by the baptism of the church. This opinion the
               three hundred and eighteen fathers who assembled at Nicaea also followed, and those
               who fed the churches after them. Those who assembled in Africa in the days of
               Cyprian, looking at the common name of the heresies only, applied a single method of
               cure. But the contemporaries of the great Dionysius and those who came after him
               distinguished the varieties of diseases, and so applied to each of them the cure
               suited for it. Just as in bodily troubles every infirmity is termed disease, and they
               are expressed by this general name, which however covers many different diseases,
               fever for instance and dropsy and elephantiasis, so also in the weaknesses of the
               faith every aberration from the sound word is named generally heresy, but every one
               of the diseases that are included in this term is not of the same character: for
               neither do they hold an equal eminence in impiety. But, as a skilful physician heals
               a man with fever in one way, and in another a man who has ague maybe or dropsy, or is
               troubled by a swelling of the spleen, in the same way those also who healed and fed
               the churches with more than ordinary spirituality and sagacity judged it right to
               distinguish the nature of each heresy, and did not think the same cure fit to be
               applied to those who shared in the sickness of Novatus and of Photinus, and to those
               who had <pb n="298"/> been stained with the corruption and mire of Paul of Samosata.
               The nineteenth canon of the three hundred and eighteen fathers requires those who
               come from Paul of Samosata to be re-baptized: but in the case of converts from
               Photinus and Novatus to the orthodox church the hundred and tenth canon, which was
               enacted by the synod that assembled at Laodicea in Phrygia, decided that they should
               be perfected by chrism: although much the same folly gives birth to the miserable
               heresy of Paul of Samosata and of Photinus, and they do not differ from one another
               except to a slight extent. And yet we for our part follow the regulations of the
               fathers and do not make ingenious investigations, nor have recourse to that which in
               former times pleased Cyprian and those who assembled in Africa, whom we mentioned
               shortly before. For we must follow the common conclusions made at different times by
               the God-loving orthodox rulers of the churches, and not adduce the private
               conclusions of different men, or opinions which seem to contain self-created
               scrupulosity or strict teaching, and lay down a contrary law, and presumptuously
               contend against the holy fathers. Indeed the holy Cyprian himself, as if laying down
               a general canon in his letter to Quintus, enjoins that we ought to follow later
               principles adopted as a matter of expediency and for the sake of the union of the
               church, and not be <pb n="299"/> shackled by prejudices held at an earlier time: and
               I am convinced that he was moved by the Holy Spirit to say this beforehand: and that
               though he was then insisting that converts from all heresies should be perfected by
               the baptism of the church. This is what he says: "Moreover also Paul the Apostle,
               being himself also concerned for peace and concord, entreats and teaches in his
               letter in such words as these: 'Let two or three prophets speak: and let the rest
               discern. But, if a revelation be made to another while sitting, let the first keep
               silence.' By this he clearly taught and showed that many things are revealed to each
               man for the better: and therefore each man ought not to be constantly and at all
               times contending for the opinions which once won his approval and prevailed: but, if
               anything better and more beneficial show itself, gladly accept it. For, when better
               things are brought before us, we are not conquered, but are instructed: especially in
               things that conduce to the unity of the church, and to the hope and assurance of our
               salvation." Therefore it is right to consider what was determined by those who
               assembled at Ephesus to depose the impious Nestorius and anathematize his doctrines.
               Now after the examination of the heresy and its refutation, and the deprivation of
               that wicked man, Charisius a presbyter from Philadelphia (this is a city of the
               province of the Lydians) came through into the midst, and laid before everyone a
               silly <pb n="300"/> symbol composed by Theodore of Mopsuestia the teacher of the
               folly of Nestorius, and showed that there were many from that country who had denied
               the accurate faith of the three hundred and eighteen fathers, and had fallen away to
               this alien and spurious symbol. And they were moreover brought in and anathematized
               the hateful heresy of Nestorius; and they did not put forward any such canon
               declaring that converts from his perdition to the bright light of orthodoxy must be
               perfected by baptism or by chrism; nor has anyone been shown to have been anointed at
               that time: and this though the schism lasted a long time, and the bishops of the East
               supported Nestorius, and separated themselves from the Catholic synod, and afterwards
               joined themselves to the same and were reconciled at the time when Paul bishop of the
               city of the Emesenes went to Alexander's city and acted as mediator of the union
               between the churches in Egypt and in the East. As it seemed necessary to the men of
               earlier days that converts from heresies should be perfected through baptism, but
               afterwards a sagacious discrimination regarding the matter introduced the principle
               that some must be re-baptized, others re-anointed, so concerning the Nestorian heresy
               the fathers after examining the character of the heresy decided that the impious
               doctrine should only be anathematized by those who repent. Paul of Samosata and
               Photinus sinned <pb n="301"/> against the very substance of God the Word; and assert
               the Lord born of Mary to be a mere man. But Nestorius says that He is the Word which
               existed before the ages, but divides the mystery of the. dispensation into two by
               saying that it was not in substance but by brotherly conjunction that God the Word
               was united to the flesh containing the intellectual soul. Therefore we embrace the
               conclusion adopted by the fathers, and the cure that was introduced by them with
               reference to converts from the Nestorian heresy we hold as a law that cannot be
               shaken, and we do not have recourse to the conclusions that were adopted and
               introduced by the men of earlier days with reference to other heresies: but we decide
               that each conclusion has its own validity in the case of those with reference to whom
               it was introduced: for everything whatever that God's priests decide, this is a law.
               As the men of earlier times gave the gift of the Holy Spirit to the heretics who were
               devoid of His grace by means of the true baptism of the church, and those who came
               later filled up what was lacking in those that repented by means of chrism, so in the
               case of converts from the evil belief of Nestorius also the fathers thought that an
               anathema of the heresy ought to be sufficient to fill up what is lacking in them;
               and, whatever was determined by them to be sufficient, this we, as I said, observe as
               a law. For it is written; "the lips of a priest shall keep knowledge: and they shall
               ask law at his mouth, because he is an <pb n="302"/> angel of the Lord the
               All-ruler." And, since this course was approved by them, we believe that it was
               "rightly approved, in accordance with the apostolic statute that says, "With the
               heart man believeth unto righteousness, and with the mouth man confesseth unto
               salvation," according to the Lord's utterance that does not lie which says, "By thy
               words thou shalt be justified." This same principle one may see in the case of
               ordinations also. For the statute ts that converts should be re-ordained, or should
               be ordained, when they come from those same heresies from which when men come over to
               piety after having received a spurious baptism from them they are perfected by the
               true baptism. And I will show you clearly that ordinations also that were performed
               by the Arians were accepted by those who then presided over orthodoxy. Now in the
               times of the Arians there were two sections among our brothers who confessed the
               orthodox faith in this great Christ-loving city of Antiochus, because of the wrongful
               expulsion of Eustace; and each of the same sections had an orthodox bishop, one
               having Paulinus and the other Melitus: and, Paulinus having left the life here and
               uncanonically appointed Evagrius his successor (for he ordained him alone without
               having two or three bishops with him as the ordinance of the church commands), after
               Melitus decease and his departure to God the other section lawfully and according to
               the <pb n="303"/> canons nominated Flavian, by the <foreign>psephisma</foreign> of a
               large number of bishops, and Evagrius and Flavian disputed the throne; and, the
               ordination of Evagrius (who had also departed from the life here) having been
               repudiated as unsound, Theophilus who was bishop of the city of the Alexandrines
               writes to Flavian to accept the clergymen who had been ordained by Evagrius, speaking
               thus: "Therefore in your days allow those also who assemble apart by themselves to be
               united to the clergy under your religiousness, and to the whole people. If we are in
               communion with the devout Anastasius, bishop of the church of the Romans, and he
               gives the communion of clergymen to those who assemble by themselves, and
               communicates with them all, you understand to what the conclusion points. Therefore,
               seeing that the reverend Anastasius our fellow-minister has communicated with them, I
               think it henceforth necessary that a concession on the ground of policy should be
               made to them, in order that the peace with our beloved fellow-ministers in the West
               may not be disturbed on account of anything that is wanting. Therefore I pray you to
               assume a salutary courage for a good end, in no point yielding to those who maintain
               the principles of strictness. Being an old man, you are well aware that our holy
               fathers cured more difficult matters than these, and that, adopting intelligent
               counsels, they became 'to those not under the <pb n="304"/> law as not under the
               law,' and checked things difficult to cure, and did not disturb the whole body of the
               church. Wherefore Ambrose also of blessed memory [received those who had received
               ordination from Auxentius his predecessor in Milan: and they received many others in
               the East who had not been ordained by the orthodox, lest, if these remained outside,
               the heresy of the Arians should strike root, and the flocks perish, and the greater
               portion of the body of the nations be lost. In this way they treated both those of
               Palestine and Phoenice and many others; properly relaxing the strict rules of
               ordination for the sake of the salvation of the nations, so that after these things
               the universal concord might remain firm and unshaken. Accordingly, since things that
               are serious and are incurable were by making a great concession as far as was
               possible healed without turning to evil, it is not difficult, but very easy, for
               these things to be now managed; since we have chosen by comparison the faults of the
               orthodox rather than the virtues of the Arians." Bearing these things in mind, show
               us that men who come from the heresy of Diphysitism, that is of the Nestorians, ought
               to be re-baptized, in order that we may be compelled to insist upon re-ordination
               also; or, if you do not show this, respect the laws laid down by the fathers, and
               orderly administration. For neither has Timothy of holy memory, who fed the church of
               the Alexandrines in apostolic fashion, <pb n="305"/> been shown to have been
               inconsistent with himself, as you vainly suppose. When the people under the influence
               of ardent enthusiasm were unwilling even to look at those who had received ordination
               from Proterius, he, wishing to soften their sternness and to follow a course opposed
               to them, spoke to them in such words as these, "Regard them just as if they had
               received ordination from me"; or, as you say, "I have determined to give them
               ordination" (for we will allow it to be thus): and, after seeing that by the
               application of this remedy the sternness of the zeal was softened, he did not in the
               matter of the reception of those who derived ordination from Proterius transgress
               against the moderation of the canons, nor was he carried away by the violence of
               zeal; but he restrained enthusiasm by the cords of politic action; and he induced
               them to acquiesce in the established canons. And, when he accepted the repentance of
               the converts, he did not give them ordination at all, a thing contrary to the
               intention of the canons; nor did he recur to the strictness of the men of early days
               and their stern method. As to the principle that these things are rather matters of
               politic administration, and not inconsistent, the divine Paul also signifies it to be
               so in that he circumcised Timothy by reason of the policy which he adopted towards
               certain persons, as the Book of the Acts clearly states, saying: "And he took and
                  circum<pb n="306"/>cised him, because of the Jews who were there in the country.
               For all these knew that his father was a Gentile." But to the Galatians, who had
               turned to the observances of Judaism, he writes as for the general profit, and as if
               laying down a law for the whole church, and says: "Behold I Paul say unto you that,
               if ye are circumcised, Christ will profit you nothing." And that this is so the
               saintly John will bear witness, who with wisdom fed the holy church at
               Constantinople, in that in the fifth book of his Praises of the apostle Paul he
               speaks thus: "For he desires those things only which bring him advantages in God,
               even though it happened that these were contrary to the previous actions. For he was
               something versatile, and rich in expedients; not that he acted hypocritically (far be
               it!); but he became everything which the necessity of the preaching and the salvation
               of men required: and in this also he imitated his Lord. For God too would appear as a
               man also when it was necessary for Him so to appear; and again in fire when the time
               required this; and at one time in the form of an armed man and a soldier; and at
               another in the guise of an old man; and at another in the breeze; and at another as a
               wayfarer; and at another He becomes human, and did not refuse even to die so. But,
               when I said that this was necessary, let no one think that there is reference to
               compulsion; but to His mercifulness only. And He sits sometimes upon <pb n="307"/> a
               throne; sometimes again upon the cherubim. But all these things He did in accordance
               with the subservient dispensations. For this reason He said through the prophet also,
               'I have multiplied visions; and through prophets I have made myself like.' [Here
               follows the citation given at p. 278 ff. I give such variations only as are nearer to
               the original, which are as follows: l. 5 'Paul, who imitated his Lord, have been
               condemned. He becomes now a Jew, now as one not under the law; now one who keeps'; l.
               12 om. 'again'; l. 19 'For this reason he now supports the law, now subverts'; p. 279
               l. 9 'For this the man of professional skill does'.] I For those that are diseased in
               soul require treatment and cure no less than those that are sick in body: and, if you
               simply offer them everything, the cause of their salvation will be ruined." Holding
               this same opinion, the holy Theophilus also in the letter to Flavian, which we
               mentioned shortly before, speaks thus: "Therefore carry out this policy boldly. If
               the Apostle 'became to them that were without law as without law, being not without
               law to God, but under the law of Christ,' and 'became everything to every man that he
               might by all means save some,' the reception of those who assemble apart according to
               the rank which they hold does not steal away your reputation, but rather indeed
               increases it; nor yet are you acting inconsistently when the urgency of the case
               compels the adoption of a <pb n="308"/> policy of concession for the sake of profit.
               You know that the blessed Paul also, looking to what was of advantage, circumcised
               Timothy; but puts the Galatians, who were circumcised, to shame, in that he writes,
               'If ye are circumcised, Christ will profit you nothing.' And, among wise men, he does
               not appear to be inconsistent, but to be acting in a politic manner towards living
               men, while healing troubles that occur with great profit." But perhaps when you hear
               these things you will say, "Who is there among orthodox bishops who received those
               who assembled at Chalcedon, or rather those who succeeded to their sees, upon
               repentance?" But I as against this will bring before you a scriptural law which shows
               how the God of repentance accepts and justifies a sudden conversion to virtue, such
               as has now taken place in the countries of the East, where all by the divine counsel
               under behest from above have cast forth and banned the heresy of the duality of the
               natures with definite anathemas, and have in pure fashion confessed the faith of the
               fathers, which is pure from all corrupt mixture and alien addition. When in old times
               the Jews had lapsed, and had fallen into the pits of idolatry, and had so much
               neglected the law of their fathers that even the places for the performance of the
               priestly service that was commanded by Moses were no longer maintained, then Hezekiah
               was established as king, and, his mind having been en<pb n="309"/>lightened by God,
               he wished to sacrifice the passover according to the law, and according to the law he
               commanded that Aaron's sons only should offer the sacrifices, as is said in the Book
               of the Priests: "And they shall kill the calf before the Lord, and the priests
               Aaron's sons shall bring the blood near, and pour it out all round by the side of the
               altar that is before the doors of the tent of witness. And they shall flay the
               burnt-offering, and cut his limbs in pieces." But at that time, since the priests
               were too few, contrary to the intention of the law, Levites also were brought forward
               together with Aaron's sons, to perform the service: and the passover was celebrated
               without the purification of the whole people having been strictly carried out. And
               God accepted the pleasant savour, having had regard to the completeness of the
               repentance of their hearts, though it was thought to be defective in the matter of
               lack of faith. But it is well also to recite to you the actual words of the Holy
               Spirit, which are written as follows, in the second part of the Book of Chronicles:
               "And the priests received the blood from the hand of the Levites, by reason of the
               numbers of the congregation, and they were not sanctified. And the Levites had the
               charge of sacrificing the passover, for everyone who could not be sanctified to the
               Lord, by reason of the multitude of people from Ephraim and from Manasseh, and from
               Issachar and <pb n="310"/> from Zebulon, and they were not sanctified; but they even
               ate this passover contrary to the scripture. And Hezekiah prayed for them, saying,
               'The good Lord God be propitious toward every heart that has turned in sincerity to
               seek the Lord God of their fathers, and not according to the purification of the holy
               things.' And the Lord hearkened to the voice of Hezekiah, and healed the people."
               Observe clearly the reason for which God accepted such repentance, as stated in the
               divine scriptures; because they had prepared their hearts to seek the Lord God of
               their fathers. And even after the coming of Christ in the flesh one may see that this
               happened in the church also. Socrates, who wrote the Church History, related a
               similar thing in the seventh book and the second chapter; and he writes thus: "At
               Synada, a city of Phrygia Pacatiana, a certain Theodosius was bishop, who vigorously
               persecuted the heretics of the religious party of the Macedonians, of whom it
               contained many, expelling them not only from the city, but from the country-districts
               also. And this he did although it is not the practice of the church of the orthodox
               to persecute; and not out of zeal for the right faith, but because he ministered to
               the passion of avarice, and was desirous of amassing gold from the heretics. For this
               reason he set everything in motion against those who held the opinions of Macedonius,
               putting arms into the hands of the clergymen who were subject to <pb n="311"/> him,
               and using countless tricks against them; and he did not even refrain from putting
               them in bonds: in law-courts: and especially their bishop, whose name was Agapetus,
               he harassed in various ways. But, since the governors of the country seemed
               insufficient for his purpose in the infliction of punishment, he betook himself to
               Constantinople, and asked for orders from the prefects. And, while Theodosius was
               for. this same reason spending time in Constantinople, Agapetus, the leader as I said
               of the religious party of Macedonius, came to a good resolution. For he consulted
               with the whole of his clergy, and summoned the people who were under subjection to
               him, and persuaded them to accept the faith] of the co-essentiality. And, having
               arranged this, he ran immediately to. the church as fast as he could with a great
               multitude: or rather with the whole people. And after conducting prayer he occupies
               the throne on which Theodosius was wont to sit. And, having united the people, and
               preaching from that time the faith of the co-essentiality, he took possession of the
               churches under Synada. And, these things having happened in this way, not long
               afterwards Theodosius arrives, bringing with him assistance from the prefect. But,
               not knowing anything of what had happened, he made his way to the best of his ability
               towards the church. But, being driven from it by all alike, he again: made his way to
                  <pb n="312"/> Constantinople. And, when he was there in the presence of bishop
               Atticus, he bewailed his fortune as having been without reason driven from the
               bishopric. But Atticus, since he knew that the affair had turned out for the benefit
               of the church, consoled Theodosius in words, persuading him to embrace a retired life
               without anger, and taught him to prefer the common good to his own, while he writes
               to Agapetus to keep the bishopric without imagining that any annoyance would result
               from Theodosius' anger." Tell us therefore in this case, my excellent man, what
               chrism or what laying on of hands, or what ordination, confirmed these proceedings.
               Or is it matter of previous knowledge that the uprightness of their heart, to use the
               words of the divine scripture," made these also genuine instead of spurious," and
               this though they had been converted from the stinking heresy of Macedonius which
               blasphemes against the Holy Spirit, in the case of which the perfecting rite of
               chrism is in fact laid down as necessary for those who repent from it? But perhaps
               under the influence of a mistaken feeling you will further bring up against us that
               you do not accept the testimony of Socrates who is a Novatian in heresy. But know
               plainly that especially in historical narratives even the statements of those that
               are such are accepted. For instance the holy Basil in his letter to Amphilochius
               cited the testimony <pb n="313"/> both of Eusebius known by the name of Pamphilus and
               of Origen, who in doctrines are faulty, saying that they are trustworthy owing to
               their great experience. And Basil cited the testimony of those men to support
               doctrines: but we do so only for a statement of bare historical fact. But it is well
               that we quote to you the actual testimony of the holy doctor, which is as follows:
               "But, if Eusebius the Palestinian also is trustworthy in any man's eyes on account of
               much experience, we produce the same expressions from him too in the 'Difficulties
               concerning the polygamy of the ancients.' For he speaks thus, encouraging himself to
               deal with the subject: 'Inviting as a guide the holy God of the prophets through our
               Saviour Jesus with the Holy Spirit.'" Upon Origen also, a man who has not much that
               is sound in him in all his tenets concerning the Spirit, we now find that under the
               Spirit's direction he bestows praise in many of his comments on the Psalms. Follow
               therefore the statutes of the divine scripture, and the dispensations of the fathers
               of which they made use from time to time, under the influence of more subtle
               consideration and being much concerned for the abolition of the divisions and for
               church unity. There is in fact no one who denies that heretics are base and split
               coin, and in need of the grace of the Spirit. But the educators" of the church
               supplied this want in many ways; in some cases by fresh baptism, in others by chrism,
               in others by those who repent <pb n="314"/> merely condemning the impious belief by
               anathema, and renouncing the stain of heresy, and attaching themselves to orthodox
               opinions. If you have recourse to what was approved by the men of earlier days, and
               say that the Holy Spirit must be given through chrism to converts from heresies,
               inasmuch as the heretics cannot give what they have not, it is time for you to have
               recourse to the other rule too and say that it is also absolutely necessary for them
               to be re-baptized, according to the opinion held by Cyprian. But it is very plain
               that we must follow the more recent precepts of the fathers, and the methods of cure
               which they introduced for each disease, and not issue commands out of presumption and
               pride, and lay down a law going beyond what seemed to them to be good. For "the
               Spirit bloweth where it listeth", as it is written, and it determines the regulations
               of the high-priests, and accompanies their sacred utterances. I am convinced that it
               was for this reason that in the Acts of the Apostles also, when Cornelius the
               centurion and those with him had with all their heart believed in the preaching of
               Peter the chief of the apostles, the Holy Spirit went in advance of the water, so
               that Peter said, "Can any man forbid water to these that they should not be baptized,
               which have received the Holy Spirit even as we?" If you think Theodotus a man of
               strict practice <pb n="315"/> because he recently introduced chrism in the case of
               the heresy of the Diphysites, know clearly that others also among those who were
               zealous against this heresy were afflicted with a madness that surpassed his in
               strictness. For instance a certain Cassian, who was a disciple of father Romanus who
               is among the saints, who after an approved fashion was distinguished in Palestine for
               ascetic life and excelled at that time in tens of thousands of gifts of the Spirit,
               caused many of the disciples to secede: and he betook himself to Skanthin (?), and
               used audaciously and illegally to baptize converts from the Chalcedonian evil belief.
               About this same Theodotus, who went through tens of thousands of changes, and
               contradicted himself, and is led in different directions at different times like the
               teachers of the adverse party, I might have said much, which I pass over. For he
               further also adhered to the fatuities of John the Rhetor, who said that it was in His
               essence that the Word of God endured the saving cross and took upon Himself the
               passion on our behalf, and would not consent to call the one Lord and our God and
               Saviour Jesus Christ of one essence with us in the flesh: a point which you also
               omitted in the preface of the document that was published in which you make
               confession of faith, and thereby. dealt us no small blow and gave cause of offence.
               Nevertheless, just as I said, it becomes us to pass his affairs by in <pb n="316"/>
               silence: for we do not draw a defence from the sins of others for propositions
               advanced by ourselves, nor do we take the weakness of others as a support to
               strengthen our own position, but we establish our own case by the good and invincible
               arguments that we have, adducing the ordinances of the church and the dispensations
               of the fathers. As to this other statement of yours, i.e. that difficulty has been
               caused to your mind by the fact that the God-loving bishops who assembled at Laodicea
               call those who cleave Emmanuel into two natures Paulianists," you must on no account
               be alarmed by this. It is in fact a custom of the fathers to refer heresies to the
               roots from which they sprang by way of reducing them to something shameful. Hence
               they called the corruption of Arius idolatry, inasmuch as it exhorts us to worship a
               creature, and the witlessness of Sabellius they termed Judaism, inasmuch as it
               includes the three substances in one person after the Jewish fashion. But they did
               not on this account receive those who repented from these heresies as Gentiles or
               Jews, and men who have never been initiated. In consonance with this principle which
               I have just stated they also term those who are infected with the phantasmal tenet of
               Eutyches Manichees: not because they are in all respects enveloped in the nets of the
               Manichees, but because the fatuous idea of a phantasy is part of the vitiated
               conception of Mani, <pb n="317"/> and is derived from him. After this manner the holy
               Cyril also in writing against Theodore of Mopsuestia said, "'Sodom has been justified
               more than you'; you have surpassed the babblings of the heathen which they uttered
               against Christ, 'reckoning the cross foolishness'; you have shown that the charges
               against Jewish arrogance are nothing." Therefore neither is anything shameful said by
               the saintly bishops who assembled at Laodicea, who called those who cleave the one
               Christ into a duality of natures after the ineffable and incomprehensible union
               Paulianists: nor ought we on this account to re-baptize those who repent from them
               like converts from Paul of Samosata. Thus much we have written to your affection as
               in a few words, lying as we are under a mass of many affairs, and not able, as we
               wished, to extend the refutation of your propositions," so as to cover a wider field
               of examination; but, since you have a right disposition, and are not subject to
               prejudice, even what has been written is enough. We have in fact dealt with each of
               them in no defective manner in accordance with our ability, quoting the testimonies
               of the God-clad doctors of the church. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
