<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3102">To the Orthodox Clergymen and Laymen of
               Antioch</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">319-23</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="5.8">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the orthodox clergymen and laymen of
               Antioch.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 2nd book the 24th
               letter.</head>
            <p> In everything the consideration of your vigour, church in Antiochus' city, causes me
               wonder, and the fact that you not only hold yourself readily and courageously against
               disturbing elements coming from without, but also manage your internal government
               wisely, and are guided in the right way by the gospel law. There has only just now
               come to the hearing of our meanness, far distant as we are in geographical situation,
               the epistle that was canonically addressed to <pb n="320"/> you by the saintly
               bishops, who followed Christ who said to His disciples, "If they persecuted me they
               will also persecute you," and chose instead of their sees the sojourn in a strange
               land, and are settled in the great Christ-loving city of the Alexandrines, about
               those who have erred and fallen away to heretical communion, and have repented and
               wish to come back to the truth by the path of legal penitence, and to take thought
               for their salvation; and that, after you who are in the city among the holy clergy
               and the believing people, who confirm the fact that you are clergy and people by
               keeping the orthodox faith, and are taught to "prove all things" and to "hold fast
               that which is good," as Paul says, had read the letter of the said holy bishops, you
               accepted the purport of the epistle, the contents of which are corroborated by the
               fatherly precepts of Timothy of apostolic and combatant memory, who died, if one may
               so say, or to speak more correctly came to life, amid the toils of exile. Wherefore
               also I have praised and gladly accepted the unanimity and concord of you all in this
               matter too, and have cried in admiration over your city that which is really said by
               Micah the prophet, "The Lord's voice shall be named over the city, and He shall save
               them that fear His name:" for one will not fall outside the limits of what is seemly
               if one call you the Lord's voice. For what <pb n="321"/> is the Lord's voice but
               assuredly that which is made known by the laws of the Spirit, and confirmed by works,
               and in everything sets forth what is lawful, which also saves us? For it is seemly
               that you who have shown courage in the contests on behalf of piety should also not be
               without the virtues that are akin to this. Courage is then shown to be courage and
               not ferocity, when it stands boldly against the man who opposes, but towards the man
               who is bent bends itself pitifully. This is to "become everything to every man "and
               from all sides to gain the power of assigning the proper treatment to different times
               and persons, and measuring out to each man that which suits him. Hold therefore to
               the words canonically addressed to you, and walk in them without turning aside to the
               tight or to the left as it is written, but opening the door of penitence to every
               man, according to the different methods of healing and the character of the sins
               committed. Whereas some, as I learn, of those who are said to have been re-ordained,
               a thing horrible even to hear, assert that this mockery was not performed over them,
               and in some cases no witness of such presumption is now forthcoming, I have come to
               the conclusion that there is no violation of right principle in the discreet and
               practical course proposed by the religious presbyter Philip of letting them assert
               this by oaths in writing. But in cases where there is confession, and an anathema of
               the man who ordained <pb n="322"/> them has been put forward by them, and a hateful
               and unlawful prayer has followed, such men everyone must regard in no other way than
               as men who have been re-ordained, and, as has been resolved, await a common inquiry
               by the saintly bishops at the proper time. After these rules have been thus observed,
               we ought not as I have said to block the lawful path of penitence. How shall we be
               able to block this, when the Lord cries from heaven and from above and says, "Knock
               and it shall be opened unto you" It lies with us therefore in brotherly love to
               admonish those that are remiss to knock vigorously and wait: but to open lies with
               Him, not with us. Let us not usurp the Lord's authority. Let us leave Him His part:
               but let us perform ours with earnestness. Let us show ourselves mild to our
               fellow-slaves, not harsh exactors of what is owing, inasmuch as we also are in need
               of mildness at the day of judgment. If you do this, and practise the exercise of each
               virtue in due season and in accordance with right, you will be, as is said by Micah
               the prophet who was mentioned shortly before, "a marvellous remnant of Jacob among
               the kindreds amidst many peoples, as dew that falleth from before the Lord," and
               cools those that have undergone the assault of the devil's "fiery darts": and all who
               see and hear that you are guided by God in your actions "will say, 'This great people
               is a wise and understanding people.' And what great people <pb n="323"/> is there who
               hath God nigh unto them, as the Lord God in all things wherein we call upon Him?" Now
               that this has been begun let it also be carried further and brought to a conclusion,
               through the prayers of all saints. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
