<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Eleusinius the bishop</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">359-63</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="6.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Eleusinius the bishop.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 1st book the
               121st letter.</head>
            <p> Many men after gazing on the likenesses of those whom they love are refreshed and
               comforted, and think that by this they satisfy their affection. But I, not having
               fashioned a likeness of your sanctity for myself, but having joined it. to myself, am
               the more attracted to the picture, and every hour, if I may so Say, am smitten in my
               soul and yearn in thirst for your delightful and spiritual conversation, and wish to
               <pb n="360"/> be immediately gratified by speaking with you, and to have again the
               former joy. But this I am well assured the Giver of all good things will give me and
               at no distant time. However I rejoiced excessively at the contents of your holiness'
               epistle, and that the affair of the trial concerning the presbyters in the country
               did not come upon you as a snare. For it is manifest that, seeing they are still of
               this disposition, if you meet with them, you will envelop and catch these also in
               your spiritual nets. You have also described very well and like men who are wise in
               all things the character of the many-footed Isidore, the unphilosophic and deceitful
               solitary, who for the destruction of the holy churches, as he thought, emulated the
               character of the cunning fox, and who composes his outward appearance only to an
               expression pleasing to everyone, but within carries a smoking firebrand according to
               the prophetic saying: by which we believe that he will be utterly consumed, and will
               become fuel for it like faggot-material, and will not be changed into another man but
               reduced to ashes. As to the man who has just been instituted and holds the prelacy of
               the royal city, we have learned that he is John called by the name of Florentinus,
               who held the post of syncellus to him who is dead; who is thought to be inclined to
               the right opinions, <pb n="361"/> and holds out some pleasing hopes to the orthodox,
               but is more desirous of adopting a deceitful middle course, and of walking himself
               also according to that model which Timothy his predecessor adopted in his synodical
               letter. There are therefore two ways; for we must say briefly what ought to be done
               as it occurs to my feeble mind. Either you must accept the synodical letter, though
               it does not contain the same sense as the document of the ten bishops or anathematize
               the transactions of Chalcedon and the Tome of Leo and those who called and call our
               one Lord and God Jesus Christ two natures after the union; or you must write what is
               repugnant to you and say that if he show himself such and such you will accept
               communion with him. But I am wondering whether a man who accepts a synodical letter
               is not obliged to communicate with those who bring this to him. But the advice which
               I have given you is that which I also am endeavouring to carry out, God supporting my
               feebleness. Know that the God-loving bishop Soteric also is going up to the royal
               among cities with a similar purpose to that which you too declare in your letter. For
               the saintly bishop Entrechius has done him much good since the time that he has been
               more thoroughly on our side. Now however, now that he also has learned that Timothy
               is dead and his successor has been appointed, he wishes to put off the journey, and
               <pb n="362"/> see by events themselves what position the man who now presides over
               the royal city is inclined to take up, and so prepare himself for the questions that
               will arise. But he too intends, if he stay where he is, not to accept the synodical
               letter, unless it contain something that tends to heal the division of the holy
               churches. But keep this to yourself and tell no man whatever. But know this too: that
               the anathema which has been reported to have been pronounced against us by him who
               has now been instituted is quite untrue. Certain men, in number very few, tried to
               make use of such rumours, and they were exposed and it became known by whom they were
               employed to do this: and the bishop who has now been instituted never consented to
               turn his attention to the rumours put about by those men: but on the next day we hear
               that some of them were actually arrested. However on New Sunday so great an assembly
               of orthodox was purposely collected that those who were collected by a gleaning
               process by the heretics did not dare even to appear, but only to slink away and hide,
               and they were in great fear, and by flight gained freedom from all harm. The
               magnificent and believing silentiary Conon, when in conversation with him who now
               ranks before me, found that with regard to unity and with regard to our meanness he
               said such things as those who are <pb n="363"/> exceedingly orthodox would say. But I
               am wondering, as I also said before, whether he will withdraw from the middle
               position which inclines to both sides. My reason for writing about the anathema that
               has been reported was that I wish merely to inform you of the sequence of events:
               otherwise I take no account whatever of such things. Anathemas by men who are not
               united in communion with those who hold right opinions, but walk contrary to us, are
               similar to what one would consider those to be that were pronounced by the Arians
               against the holy Athanasius and decreed his complete deposition without touching his
               faith at all) He who on account of his sound faith was able to hear from Christ the
               words, "Thou art Cephas and upon this rock I will build my church," has consequently
               also the power of binding and loosing, inasmuch as the heavenly mandate also
               sanctions such things. But, if he is carried beyond this rock, it is manifest that
               such a man does not escape detection as beating the air, as the Apostle says. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
