<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Valieriana the Deaconess and
               Archimandritess</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">364-68</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Valieriana the deaconess and
               archimandritess.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 3rd book the
               10th, 15th letter.</head>
            <p> I rejoiced greatly on learning that your religiousness had by God's decree received
               the headship of those <pb n="365"/> sacred virgins. <add><emph>And after other
                  things.</emph></add> Wherefore gird up the loins of your understanding, and
               with watching and strenuousness guide the rational souls over which you have been
               appointed to be head to every good action. Require from them not only asceticism of
               body, but also purity of mind. Make the virgins' holy convent inaccessible to every
               male, and let none whatever set foot within their sacred precincts: neither if he be
               a boy in his time of life, nor if he has reached advanced old age, except the priest
               who performs divine service for you. Neither let the virgins look freely at one
               another, but with eyes turned downwards let them say what is needed. The lust of the
               flesh obtains occasions from the lust of the eyes, as the divine John the Evangelist
               says in his epistle. Paul the wise also writes to the Ephesians, "Let no foul speech
               proceed out of your mouth: but that which is good for needful edification, in order
               that it may give grace to them that hear." To this also your religiousness must
               carefully see: <foreign>i.e.</foreign> that all the virgins do not take their food separately, lest one
               be hungry and another drunken: but be at one and the same table, as it is written in
               the Acts of the Apostles concerning those who in the beginning believed on the name
               of our Lord Jesus Christ, that they were all together, and they broke bread in a
               house and "took food, with gladness and singleness of their heart praising God"; and
               that "the heart and soul of the whole number of <pb n="366"/> those who had believed
               was one, and none said of any of the things that he possessed that it was his own,
               but everything that they had was common." But neither let any of them keep a
               bondwoman within to minister to her: but let those that are young minister to those
               that have grown old. It is not lawful for a virgin or a solitary, who have promised
               to imitate Christ, to keep a bondman or bondwoman. "The Son of man," He says, "came
               not to be ministered unto but to minister, and to give His life a ransom for many."
               If therefore the bondwomen are willing to be bound with the yoke of virginity, after
               due examination receive these, and let them live with the rest as freewomen; and let
               them have no liberty of intercourse with their former mistresses, nor for the future
               perform service for them. "He that was called as a bondman in the Lord is the Lord's
               freedman," as the divine Apostle says. But, if they desire to minister to their
               mistresses in the monastery while yet bondwomen and living a secular life, use all
               your power to expel these women. If "evil communications corrupt gentle
               dispositions," much more does the servile character cause corruption in the
               characters of the freeborn when it lives with them. But do not exert yourself to
               apply correction to all these things immediately, lest you grow weary of labours, and
               load yourself with an excessive burden: but cut away the <pb n="367"/> evil practices
               little by little, and provide the proper remedy for every disorder, like the most
               skilled physicians: and, when you have healed one disorder according to the method
               proper for it, then bestir yourself to cure another also; and thus you will make the
               whole body sound by gradual corrections, and will win the reward of wise stewards.
               Enforce God's laws: but slanders against you or contumelies despise; and thus you
               will be a good example of humility of mind to those under your headship. Those that
               are ill comfort: before those that are well hold out readiness for ascetic exercises.
               Those that are harassed by cares help and sympathize with them, inasmuch as you also
               are clad in bodily infirmity, and strengthen them with hopes for the future: teaching
               them that "the fashion of this world passeth away." Warn them not to despise the work
               of their hands. In fact even the wise Paul used to work: and he would say, "These
               hands ministered to my necessities and to them that were with me. And I have showed
               you all things, how that ye ought so to labour and work and help the weak." Warn them
               to have ever in their mouth meditation upon the divine scriptures, and to sing night
               and day the songs that the. Holy Spirit delivered to us through David's mouth, not
               men's hymns, which are made to give pleasure, and which weaken the soul and relax the
               vigour of asceticism. "Meditate upon these things: think upon these things: <pb
                  n="368"/> in order that thy progress may be manifest to everyone": and you may be
               as a ship that is engaged in commerce and gathers the spiritual profit from every
               quarter, in Christ Jesus our Lord. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
