<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Jannia the Deaconess and
               Archimandritess</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">368-71</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.2">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Jannia the deaconess and
               archimandritess.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those before episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               118th, 12st letter.</head>
            <p> The religious deacon, father Theodore, has asked me about the commands which he
               received from your devoutness. But I, being poor in knowledge and having no right
               even to open my mouth, seeing that I am doing no good service that gives me freedom
               to speak, have been under the necessity of writing these things, since I yielded to
               his entreaties accompanied by adjurations, and I also shrink from distressing you by
               silence. Therefore I wish your religiousness to know that she who is entrusted with
               the governance and headship of rational souls must possess unlimited fear, and a
               heart of mercy: fear, lest she neglect any of God's judgments or commandments, and do
               not teach them to the sisters or enforce them upon them: goodness of heart, lest in
               enforcing strict discipline she harshly and without sympathy make the Lord's gentle
               yoke heavy, and render His light burden grievous to be borne, though He Himself says
               in the Gospels, "For my yoke is gentle and my burden is light". <pb n="369"/> You did
               well therefore in showing condescension towards her who has been weak and has been
               tempted by the evil one, and in restoring her to repentance by displaying the mercy
               of pity towards her. Do not cease bearing with her as long as she displays penitence
               by works of asceticism that is worthy the name and able to wash away the pollution of
               sin. However, if her faults are such as to injure and stain the others also and
               inflict her leprosy upon them, like the stains of men of corrupt mind mentioned in
               the Apostle, cut her off and cast her from you: "for it is good for thee that one of
               thy members should perish, and not that thy whole body should fall into hell." Only
               so long must you bear with her as the detriment is confined to her, and does not pass
               to the others also like some grievous flood. Expel from the company of the sisters
               all license and idle speech, unrestrained and unseemly laughter, and adornment of the
               body or of clothes, from which spring fornication and foul and filthy thoughts. For
               one may wear the lowly and dark tunic itself or cloak in no modest or chaste fashion,
               but wantonly and immodestly, and walk unbecomingly, and turn one's eyes about in a
               disorderly way, and use dissolute language, and place one's limbs in a languishing
               posture, and so satisfy the passion of elegance, and excite the lascivious desires.
               Command them therefore to keep their heart "with all carefulness," and with David to
               cry, "My flesh trembled for <pb n="370"/> fear of thee: for I was afraid of thy
               judgments." If the fear of God reach our mind, and we persuade ourselves that
               to-morrow we shall be dust and ashes, and that the fire of hell that is not quenched
               will receive us, we shall slay all carnal pleasure. For he that trembles for fear of
               God is dead to deeds of sin: but he is alive to works of righteousness: and he takes
               no account of the labour of watching: but he rejoices and delights in the consolation
               of song; and at working with his hands he is ready and cheerful, seeing that, having
               fled from the greed and covetousness of the world, he gains by his own toil his daily
               bread to eat, and often also to give of it to a poor man, and to feed Christ when
               hungry. To all kinds of obedience also such a one is prompt, and carries out what is
               commanded without cause for blame and immediately, saying according to the Lord's
               commandment, "That which is my duty to do I have done," and fears to open his mouth
               and speak idle and inexpedient words, and lose his toil. Let us pray therefore that
               the fear of God may be bestowed upon us, which is itself the beginning of good works
               and their preservation and completion. For "the fear of the Lord is the beginning of
               wisdom": and "let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall." Besides all
               other things I wish you to know this: <pb n="371"/> that, if you do not through your
               honourable demeanour offer yourself as a model of good works to those who are being
               taught, and by your actual conduct show them uncorruptness and modesty, as the
               Apostle says, during your teaching, though you perish ten thousand times every day,
               you will profit nothing: but you will be "as sounding brass," and as "a tinkling
               cymbal": since our teacher and God Jesus Himself first began to do, and then to
               teach, thereby giving us a model of virtue. The prophet David also shows that a man
               cannot otherwise open his mouth and speak spiritual words, unless he has first loved
               and served God's commandments: for he says, "I opened my mouth and breathed in
               spirit, because I loved thy commandments." I have out of affection reminded your
               religiousness of these things as in a few words: but do you in your deeds show better
               things than these. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
