<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Naunus Bishop of Seleucia</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">373-78</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.4">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Naunus bishop of Seleucia.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 10th book the
               384th, 385¢h Letter.</head>
            <p> Be it known to your love of God that Pelagius, having been afflicted with disdain of
               the divine laws of the Spirit, and having disobeyed our summons which very gently
               summoned him, because he was not conscious in himself of any soundness, and could not
               make a defence to the accusations against him, derived so much benefit from his great
               presumption that he obtained many further witnesses to his own audacity and impiety.
               He was in fact required to give account or be tried for what he had done before the
               glorious count of the East, who was present in the honourable bishop's house," and he
               did not need the expressions of his accusers, or any witnesses: but by his own words
               he was convicted of trying to make a defence in a crooked and crafty manner. For
               truly speaks the <pb n="374"/> sacred text which says,"He that is incautious with his
               lips being perverse shall be tripped up": and again, "A fool's lips lead him to evil
               things, and his presumptuous mouth calleth down death upon him." Our Lord and God and
               Saviour Jesus Christ Himself also, who uttered these words and words like them in
               those that said them, says in the Gospels, "Out of the abundance of the heart the
               mouth speaketh," and, "The evil man out of the evil treasure bringeth forth and
               putteth out evil things." Not to make many words, he was shown to be liable to many
               punishments: but by reason of the clemency to which the aforesaid glorious count of
               the East also as well as my meanness was by inclination disposed, he was adjudged
               indeed to be wholly unworthy to reside in the holy monastery situated by the
               chapel-house of the glorious apostle Thomas in the city of the Seleucenes, because he
               sows disturbances among the brethren: but for the present as a discipline for his
               sins to live for a short time in any monastery that we please. For he has not ceased
               sinning against the brethren as the Apostle says and wounding their consciences, and
               so injuring Christ, to whom every sin that is sinned reaches, since in graciousness
               He makes our afflictions His own. How was it anything but shameful that he should
               bring his brother into the monastery, who is a Nestorian and will not consent to set
               foot even in the <pb n="375"/> outer court of the holy church or on the path to it,
               and admit him to be received by him; and further in the case of a man who was
               formerly a solitary, who is stained with the hateful belief of Nestorius, and calls
               our one Lord and God Jesus Christ two natures after the divine and ineffable union,
               and was reproved and after the reproof said, "It is the same thing for us to speak of
               two natures and of one incarnate nature of God the Word," not only admitted him to
               entrance into the monastery, but even to give the divine communion to the brethren?
               And how could it be tolerable to those who know how to give right judgments that,
               while the commemoration of Epiphanius is allowed as an indulgence by me, he should
               take this man as a support for his own wickedness, and should in psalms and hymns of
               praise call one who has been admitted to indulgence a theologian, insomuch as to put
               down a certain small jug or flask and say, "It is a relic of the holy Epiphanius,"
               and use this turbid filth, as the prophetic text says, to give drink to the rational
               sheep? Not to prolong the letter by citing every one of the facts established by
               examination, by committing these and like sins he was shown to be drawing into his
               own impiety those of the brethren also who are. specially. simple and have specially
               rustic minds. The archimandrite also of the monastery that has been often mentioned
               fell under great blame for keeping silent on these matters, and closing his eyes, as
               the <pb n="376"/> saying is: and, had it not been that I and the glorious count of
               the East yielded to his white hairs and advanced old age, and he received
               forgiveness, he would perhaps have been taught to be watchful in the case of sins
               directed against God. For it is written, "If a man sin against a man, they shall pray
               for him: but, if he sin against God, who shall pray for him?" For this reason we
               also, being concerned for the conscience of the brethren, and desiring to give no
               entrance to impiety, have disallowed what was previously permitted as an indulgence,
               I mean the commemoration or mention of Epiphanius. It was also resolved that the
               <foreign>programma</foreign> or superscription of the faith should be put up
               before the gate, after the model of the other monasteries of the orthodox, on account
               of Him who said "What I tell you in the darkness speak in the light; and what ye hear
               in the ear preach upon the housetops." For that which He when He had become man for
               reasons of expediency delivered in quiet, and to few in number, speaking to His
               disciples, this He ordered to be clearly preached throughout the world. The reason
               that a man obtains an indulgence and a concession is not that he may by means of it
               rebuild the impiety, but that he may by gradual ascent increase the strictness of his
               practice. In this way, after God had allowed the sons of Israel, who had been brought
               from heathen denseness, the sacrifices through "the blood of bulls and goats," as the
               Apostle <pb n="377"/> says, men like David the prophet, advancing towards knowledge,
               said, "In burnt-offerings thou delightedst not; a sacrifice unto God is a broken
               spirit." The apostles also, after having allowed circumcision to those who believed
               from among the Jews, after these things, when the preaching of religion had advanced
               further, said and taught and wrote in their epistles, "Ye who are justified by law
               have fallen from grace": and, "If I yet preach circumcision, why am I again
               persecuted?": and, "Now therefore why tempt ye God, to put a yoke upon the neck of
               the disciples which neither we nor our fathers were able to bear?" These things were
               carried into. effect; and those who received the concession that was allowed on
               account of imperfection forgot this, and pressed on to perfection: and neither did
               the true Israelites lapse into demon-worship because of the indulgence of sacrifices,
               nor did those who believed among the Jews in the beginning and were circumcised recur
               to the shadowy worship. Therefore, these things being so, the matter of the
               superintendence of the monastery too was ordered and settled in writing, the
               magnificent count of the East also being present, if order that the seeds of all
               disunion may be removed from before the feet: against which we urge your holiness
               also to keep a watchful mind, and not suffer anything of the kind to <pb n="378"/>
               happen henceforth in the same holy monastery. All the devout brethren were charged
               with threats both by me and by the glorious count of the East not to bring forward
               any matter tending to disturbance or confusion unsuited to solitaries, but to be
               subject to their religious archimandrite, and in all things to think, say, and do
               what is in harmony with the orthodox faith and with the solitary life. But, if they
               do anything contrary to these things, they must no longer expect the castigation
               suited to monks, but that which is suited to men living the unregulated and
               undisciplined life in the world. But these things your love of God ought to have
               first arranged and settled yourself, and not have thrown such labours upon me, who am
               harassed by the great turmoil of affairs. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
