<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3047">To Victor, Bishop of Philadelphia</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">378-80</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.5">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Victor bishop of Philadelphia.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 4th book the
               156th letter.</head>
            <p> That the thing which holds Christianity together is love we are all assured. But
               what is the peculiarity of love except to regard a neighbour as itself? Therefore,
               since we have heard a report that is not good about. the devout John, who formerly
               ministered to the presbyter Aelian who is among the saints, to the effect that he has
               lapsed into love of money and the vileness of filthy lucre, and the other vices that
               are akin to <pb n="379"/> these (if the text is not false which said that "the love
               of money is the root of all evil things "), we urge your holiness, who besides your
               other good qualities are rich also in the virtue of obedience, to send this man to
               his own monastery in order that he may keep quiet: especially since he came to us in
               an improper way and as one may say self-invited, and not by invitation and as one who
               is carrying out an order so that he might also receive a reward. For I have learned
               that his evil repute has also reached our holy fathers of the house of the saintly
               John and Theodore. In what way I do not intend to say: but that those who related
               these things are not liars, and that they have "the fear of God before their eyes,"
               and that they are greatly devoted to your love of God I know and am assured, and I
               have gained this knowledge from actual experience. I remember also that the devout
               John often showed a lucre-loving character in affairs, in the neighbourhood of the
               holy monasteries where I and your love of God lived, and that he did not edify us
               much (for we must speak thus moderately), The occasion of this hunting after lucre in
               him was that old man, and the attendance on that invalid, and the disguise thence
               derived, coloured with Melian earth of this kind. Therefore I beg your holiness to
               purge away this blot also and reflect that nothing is likely to impair the whole
               administration of those who preside over a people (not <pb n="380"/> only spiritual
               administration but also political or any other kind whatever) so much as intercourse
               with those who are constantly with them and serve them and are entrusted by them with
               things that cannot be entrusted to those without. For this reason the prophet David,
               leaving us a rule and a statute for an illustrious life, sang to the God of all,
               "When the wicked man turned aside from me I did not know": and, "Mine eyes are upon
               the faithful of the land that they may sit with me: and he that walked in a blameless
               way he ministered to me": and the passages that agree with and resemble these, words
               which everyone sings and takes into his mouth, but few, and those such as you,
               display in act. These things have been written by us with the love of Christ going in
               advance and filling up the measure of the letter. Though we are sinners, we are in
               the habit of endeavouring to do what is good not for the sake of anything else, but
               for the sake of goodness itself only. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
