<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To the Wife of Calliopius the Patrician on
               a Diptych</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">382-84</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.7">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the wife of Calliopius the patrician on
               a diptych.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 8th book the
               157th letter.</head>
            <p> Being engaged in hearing a certain cause, I had not time to attend to what was
               written by your highness immediately. But, now that I have read it, I have this much
               to say: that concerning the confession of faith it is necessary for me to give you an
               admonition. For in such things as these it is not right to be negligent. For we hear
               the Apostle saying, "For necessity is laid upon me: and woe unto me if I preach not
               the gospel." Indeed, even when such a <pb n="383"/> thing is said in simplicity as
               you say, it is foreign and alien to the right confession, I mean that Christ should
               be reckoned as an addition to the Holy Trinity, or, vice versa, that we should place
               Him before and in this way confess the Trinity. Having positive knowledge that you
               are sound in the faith, and that you rejoice at such an admonition, I have written to
               you, and that with very just confidence. But, since the same apostle says in writing
               in another place, "Let your speech be always seasoned with grace as with salt," with
               grace that does not fall outside the limits of devoutness I have added also the case
               of that woman: and that though it is certainly in no way alien to believing women to
               help one another, especially in such urgent matters. The practice of women teaching
               in public and giving expositions to men the wise Paul disallowed, saying, "I suffer
               not a woman to teach, nor to usurp authority over a man: but let her be in silence."
               But that they should correct their sisters in their assemblies and conversations he
               properly permitted, especially those who are advanced in age, calling them "teachers
               of good things," in order that they may give an example to the others also in
               everything. Also the women who were taught at that time by the Lord show that
               instruction in religion is not foreign even to the female sex. For this reason too he
               accepted Mary who was industrious in this matter, saying, "Mary hath chosen for
               herself the good part, <pb n="384"/> which shall not be taken from her." Accordingly
               both to learn and to teach such things, in a proper manner and according to the
               character of each person, belongs to every sex and is praiseworthy and blessed. I
               forbear to go on to refer to Paul who says in his epistle to the Philippians about
               certain women, "Which combated with me in the gospel with Clement and my other
               helpers," in order not to be thought to be prolonging the argument, and doing
               detriment to the brevity of an admonitory letter. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
