<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3128">To Eustace a Young Monk</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">384-86</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.8">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Eustace a young monk.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 5th book the 38th
               letter.</head>
            <p> Your devoutness acted rightly and lawfully in informing both that saintly old man at
               an earlier time and our meanness now of the thought that troubles you. <add><emph>And
                  after other things.</emph></add> Know therefore that our Lord and God Jesus
               Christ, by way of making the road that leads to salvation broad for us (for His
               "commandment is exceeding broad," as the singing prophet says, although it seems
               narrow to many by reason of the hardness and difficulty of works of virtue), when in
               the Gospels urging us to bear the cross and follow Him, and to despise the worldly
               matter that draws our mind away from heavenly things, and press on to perfection, in
               one place says, <pb n="385"/> "If thou wilt be perfect, go sell that thou hast and
               give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven, and come follow me": while
               in another place He laid down a principle saying, "Everyone that hath forsaken house
               or brethren or sisters or mother or father, or wife or children, or lands, for my
               name's sake shall receive an hundredfold, and shall inherit eternal life." Since
               therefore you also have by God's grace chosen for yourself and completed one of the
               said roads by forsaking all for His name, do not Jet your thoughts distress you and
               think that you ought in all points and under all circumstances to carry the other
               method into effect also, I) mean that of selling what you have forsaken and giving to
               the poor. Indeed Basil the great in divine teaching, when drawing up the ascetic
               canons for us, ordered us to testify to a charge of sacrilege only against men who
               hold property that belongs to us, saying that the voice of religion does not permit
               us to go to law about it. If therefore you be able to do so out of a superfluity (for
               neither is there any need for you to do even this as a matter of necessity and
               compulsion), I mean to take a part also of your father's or mother's inheritance to
               help the poor, without relaxing the laws of the Spirit and being involved in the
               confusions of courts, the action is good and not to be disallowed, and it ought not
               to be despised. For the same doctor said, "But every<pb n="386"/> where let us take
               care lest by. reason of one commandment we be seen to be breaking another." You are
               therefore in need of a believing man, one who is powerful in the state, and able to
               receive instructions and commissions from your devoutness as to the claims which it
               is proper to make, in order that he may hold the fear of law-courts only before those
               who hold your property, and when they have given way demand from them some of the
               things that can be demanded. For you do not require him to be led into suits in the
               courts, if those men be very unjust, and to be further found to be yourself going to
               law through the instrumentality of the man who has received the instructions and do
               violence to the laws and rules of the Spirit, which prohibit you from going to law.
               This,I say, because among the things written by you stated that, if you do not at
               once remind those who hold the things that belong to you, you will be barred by the
               time that has elapsed from any claim or indictment. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
