<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3138">To the Christ-loving Isidora</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">386-91</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="7.9">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the Christ-loving Isidora.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 9th book the 13th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The fact that I learned from your Christ-loving modesty's letter (to speak with
               God's permission) that <pb n="387"/> both you and our common children are sound both
               in soul and in body was a cause of great joy to me. <add><emph>And after other
                  things.</emph></add> And she is blessed because of her departure: but you are
               more blessed in that you did not see her in the body, for the sake of the law of the
               Spirit and the future eternal hope. You will assuredly see her there, since by
               enduring not to see her here you have consecrated your endurance as a sacrifice to
               God. This principle is also stated in the sayings of the holy old men who after an
               approved fashion gained distinction in the solitary and immaterial life. Once indeed,
               when father Poemen was following the life of philosophic quietude with his brothers,
               and the door of his cell was shut, his mother stood outside the house, and he spoke
               to her thus in so many words, "Do you wish to see us here, or to see us in that
               country?"; and the old woman said to him: "If I do not see you here shall I certainly
               see you there, my son?"; and he answered her, "If you force yourself not to see us
               here, you will see us there." And she went away rejoicing and saying, "Shall I
               certainly see you there? I do not seek to see you here." These things were said and
               done by those understanding old men, and fathers of the holy and solitary life, not
               because they were cruel and unkind men in respect of the. claims of nature, but
               because they were taught by the: God-inspired scripture that those. who have been set
               apart and consecrated to God have no <pb n="388"/> family on earth, but among angelic
               hosts and the heavenly spirits. For this reason Moses in his blessings said of the
               tribe of Levi that was set apart to perform priestly functions, from which was Aaron
               the first high-priest, and those who after him wore the robe of judgment and the
               revelation and truth upon their breast (these were bright stones, which signified the
               fact that all things that are true and are not revealed to most men are revealed by
               God to the high-priests),"Give to Levi his revelations, and his truth to the saintly
               man." Then also he adduces the cause of such honour, saying, "Who saith to his father
               and to his mother, 'I have not seen thee': and acknowledged not his brethren and his
               sons." For this reason Elisha also, who was working at the tilling of the earth, and
               was looking after twelve yoke of oxen ploughing, when he suddenly received the
               heavenly calling from. Elijah the prophet, was not allowed to see his parents and bid
               them farewell: but, when he said,." Let me kiss my father and my mother and I will
               follow after thee," he heard the prophet indignantly commanding him and saying, "Go
               and turn back, what have I done to thee?" Jesus Himself also, the teacher and God of
               the prophets, and of the righteous men who have been from all time and from the
               beginning of the world, for the sake of example and instruction to us made answer in
               the sacred Gospels to the man who said to Him while <pb n="389"/> He was teaching the
               multitudes, "Behold! thy mother and thy brethren stand without and seek to speak with
               thee," and said in the ears of. everyone, "Who is my mother? and who are my
               brethren?": and He stretched forth His hand towards His disciples, and said: "Behold!
               my mother and my brethren. For, whosoever shall do the will of my Father which is in
               heaven, he is my brother and sister, and mother." <add><emph>And again after other
                  things.</emph></add> With regard also to the burial of that blessed God-loving
               virgin's body, if you determine upon a course worthy of the perfection of Christians
               and the high garb of virginity, you will allow her,to be buried in the place where
               she placed her: spirit in the heavenly Father's hands, an expression which Christ,
               the new first fruits of our race, left us as an inheritance, when He died the
               voluntary death for our liberation and said, "My Father in thy hands I place my
               spirit." For "the earth is the Lord's and the fulness thereof" says the singing
               prophet: who also in another place teaches that the whole earth is a foreign land to
               holy men, and that they have no country, in that he sings thus to God over all: "I am
               a denizen with thee, and a sojourner, like all my fathers." The reason that
               patriarchs such as Jacob and Joseph desired to be removed from the country of the
               Egyptians to. the land of promise, and there receive perfect burial, was that with
               prophetic <pb n="390"/> eyes they foresaw our God and Saviour's Resurrection, which
               was to take place there; for which reason also the observances of the divine service
               and worship were confined to these places only, so that in the legal writings also
               the following command is given by Moses, "Take heed that thou offer not thy burnt
               offerings in every place where thou shalt see, but in the place which the Lord thy
               God shall choose." But now, when the gospel service and the worship in spirit has
               embraced all the ends of the world, and one sacrifice has been offered for the sin of
               the whole world (for, "Behold!" He says, "the Lamb of God which taketh away the sin
               of the world "), it is lawful for us to do spiritual service and to worship and pray
               everywhere, and no one can any longer be found among saints and those who conducted
               themselves according to the perfection of the gospel who gave injunctions or who
               greatly concerned himself about being buried in this land or in that. For they looked
               to the hope of the resurrection, and the last trump, which shall in the same manner
               awake those who sleep from the dust of earth, as says Daniel the divine among
               prophets,.and "from end to end of heaven," as Jesus Christ who spoke in the
               prophets said in the Gospels; who to the Samaritan woman. also:who thought that the
               observances of worship were limited and confined either to Mount Gerizim according to
               the <pb n="391"/> folly of the Samaritans, or to Jerusalem according to the opinion
               of the Jews, said, "Woman, believe me, an hour cometh when neither in this mountain
               nor at Jerusalem shall they worship the Father"; and again after a little more; "But
               an hour cometh, yea now is, when the true worshippers shall worship the Father in
               spirit and in truth; for the Father also seeketh such worshippers. God is spirit; and
               they that worship him must worship in spirit and in truth," Following these things
               the wise Paul also in writing to Timothy said, "I will therefore that men pray
               everywhere, lifting up holy hands without wrath or cogitations." </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
