<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3077">To Stephen the Reader</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">391-93</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="8.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Stephen the reader.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 7th book the
               392nd letter.</head>
            <p> I confess that I rejoiced greatly when I received the letter which your
               religiousness sent me by the <pb n="392"/> magnificent Sergius, the governor of the
               second people of the Syrians, for two reasons: both because it was yours, and because
               its contents were what they are. For we have now by experience found the man such as
               you described him in your words to be: and in this great thanks are due to your
               God-loving soul. By asking after you have received the discourse produced by us upon
               the saintly Simeon that we should compose another also in the form of a historical
               Narrative you seem to me to be doing the same as a covetous and strict lender, who,
               when he sees that his debtor is unfruitful, desires to receive the principal only,
               but, when he has received it and seen the gold in his hands, is induced to demand the
               interest also, which before receiving the principal he despised, determining in a
               friendly way that his own only should be repaid without increment. Know clearly
               however that it was our endeavour in that discourse, even while applying ourselves to
               the festal and laudatory style of composition, not to neglect the historical and
               narratival aspect also: in order that it might contain both at once, and the hearer
               might be more gratified at receiving a history adorned with flowers of praises, and
               at the same time as far as possible not failing in ecclesiastical gravity. That the
               praises of the saints are read even in <pb n="393"/> churches is witnessed by the
               discourse of the wise Basil on the forty martyrs, which is read to the people in the
               city of the men of Berytus, as well as by that of the holy Pamphilus, both there and
               in the city of the men of Caesarea, which is the metropolis of First Palestine. The
               laudatory discourse also that was delivered upon Gregory the Wonder-worker we
               ourselves have known to be read in many churches, and in the royal city itself:
               similarly also that upon the great Basil. We who are scrutinizers of the laws must do
               you an injury, and so stop your greedy ears. I think that the preface of the same
               discourse that we wrote on the same holy Simeon will cause you difficulty, seeing
               that it is unacceptable to the Byzantines, But it is easy for you to use three or
               four passages that stand at the beginning, and leave out the things that cause
               difficulty, and read the rest continuously. But the lawful freedom of speech of your
               love of God, or rather to say what is more true your confession on behalf of piety,
               we have heard from others. And you are blessed both in the distinction enjoyed here,
               and in the expected reward, which is promised to those who have fought well. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
