<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3129">To John, Scholastic of Bostra</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">397-412</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="8.4">
            <pb n="397"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to John the scholastic of Bostra.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 5th book the 39th
               letter.</head>
            <p> I praise the man who addressed an epistle to your Christ-loving erudition, and is
               earnestly desirous of learning the intention of the commandments of the Spirit, and
               rightly shrinks from the crime of transgressing the commandment of the divine laws,
               which leads to manifest death. For the God-inspired writings somewhere say, "The
               commandment of the Lord is a fountain of life: and it makes one turn aside from the
               snare of death." Wherefore I also of necessity answer with what comes to my
               knowledge, since it is not a safe thing for me to keep silence and neglect the
               question. If men who have been admitted to act as priests to God do not make manifest
               to those that are in need the path of what ought to be done, it is equivalent to
               committing murder. For He that speaks in Hosea the prophet says, "Priests have hidden
               the Lord's way: they have slain Shechem: because they have wrought iniquity in the
               house of Israel." For the sharp sword that provides the devil with an instrument for
               the slaughter of our souls is an iniquity. Wherefore we will set the question of him
               who asks before our answer, as he requested. It is word for word as follows. <pb
                  n="398"/> Question one. "The loud-voiced Isaiah admonishes those that thirst to go
               to the water. Having therefore for a long time disputed about the points to be
               mentioned without being able to find anyone here to explain these clearly to us, and
               yearning greatly in thirst, we have now had recourse to your wisdom as to fountains
               of salvation, you who are able from your own resources and by the help of the
               God-taught men there to explain to us what the right opinion is concerning the
               propositions submitted by us. But let the story be taken as relating to imaginary
               persons. There were with a certain man two deacons who had received the habit from
               him, and were admitted to the diaconate by his hands: not both at one time: but each
               of them separately. These concerted a partnership in wickedness: and having corrupted
               one another left their archimandrite, having perhaps even before their departure made
               an agreement to trample under foot the anathema that would be launched against them.
               Therefore, after they had withdrawn themselves, these men's archimandrite, wishing to
               check the evil, immediately through a certain brother placed them under an anathema,
               the exact terms of which were that they were not to be together nor talk with one
               another, nor taste wine for some short stated time. For it was thought that what had
               been done was chiefly due to the indulgence of the belly. But these men treated the
               anathema with contempt, and on the very day <pb n="399"/> were together and in
               company, and did not refrain from the drinking of wine even for the space of one day
               only. "That if they had observed the pronouncement they would not have been under the
               anathema, and that after the anathema had been removed also it would have been easy
               for them to be together is, I think, obvious to everyone: but, since they were
               infected with contemptuousness and did not take account of the anathema, in what
               light must we hold these men? and is it possible for him who placed them under
               anathema to give them forgiveness when the ban has once been broken contrary to his
               pleasure? Or, even if he who pronounced the anathema shall forgive them, will the
               Lord also with him forgive their contempt of the anathema and their neglect of the
               pronouncement? What I ask is whether even if the author of the ban himself wishes to
               grant release it is difficult for him to do so, or if it is in fact upon him that the
               whole matter depends so that he may even change his mind and give way, or if it
               depends upon a certain definite penance and strict observance of the things that were
               forbidden them before, and whether this is to be observed for ever, or is to be
               applied to them for a space of time as a discipline. "To speak generally, if a man is
               under an anathema, and on his own authority deliberately transgresses against it,
               what does he deserve? And is the act of release after the transgression free from
               danger for the author of the ban? and does God grant forgiveness with him, and judge
               the man who has sinned inno<pb n="400"/>cent? I ask further also whether
               pronouncement and anathema and separation differ from one another in meaning, or if,
               the meaning being one, it is only the articulation of the syllables that is
               different." Answer. Since Moses who was named a faithful servant in all God's house
               says to those who are to judge, "Ye shall not recognise a person in judgment; judge
               according to the small and according to the great; thou shalt not be afraid of the
               person of a man, since the judgment is God's," and Koheleth too gives us wise
               instruction, speaking plainly thus, "There is a time for everything under the sun,"
               we the mean one also must, as far as is possible for us, so make answer to the
               question as if the judgment were divine and not human, and produce a solution of the
               doubt in accordance with the distinctive character of the time. If therefore the head
               of the monastery reproved the brothers who have now left while they were within and
               living under his power, and found fault with them for disorderliness of conduct, and
               forbade them the corrupting intercourse, he would have reason for laying an ordinance
               upon them after they left also, and ratifying this by an admonitory anathema. But, if
               he is shown to have been silent the whole of the time during which they were under
               his authority, and not to have found any such fault with them at all, he is now
               giving ground for suspicion that he is rather inflicting a man's vengeance upon them
               for his own <pb n="401"/> injury, not applying a correction out of concern for their
               salvation. Everyone who wishes is allowed to leave a cloister freely without any
               blame following him. A man who leaves a monastic community does not, as in the case
               of the holy churches and of those who are included in the honourable clergy, need a
               dimissory letter or similar permission: for this is not laid down in any of the holy
               canons. In conformance with this distinction therefore we say that the pronouncement
               that has been laid upon the brethren shall hold or not hold. If they received a
               warning while within the cloister, it is manifest that they have sinned, inasmuch as
               they have trampled upon the pronouncement. But, if they left without having had any
               fault found with them, they are not subject to the pronouncement that was laid upon
               them after their departure: but for their disorderly character they shall give
               account to the righteous Judge, when they shall themselves bear the burden of their
               own sin: "for everyone," as the Apostle says, "shall bear his own burden". But, if
               they fall under the ordinance, it is manifest that penitence will help them. Every
               sin, even one that is very grievous, is cured by the method of sincere penitence, and
               those who show penitence worthy the name have nothing incurable about them; and the
               man himself also who laid the ordinance upon them can remove the interdict: not
               introducing thereby human favour, but serving the divine will. But, if he shall be
               wrathfully and <pb n="402"/> hostilely disposed, and be unwilling to release those
               who sincerely repent, it rests with another authority higher than his, viz., that of
               the bishops, upon learning the truth, to remove that which out of human bitterness
               and malice is maintained even after sincere penitence. But it rests with him who has
               authority to remove the interdict to approve the measure and character of sincere
               penitence, where nothing is explicitly stated by the church canons, as in the case of
               certain sins. Such pronouncements the divine scripture is able to term both
               "ordinances" and "pronouncement", For it is written in Numbers as follows: "This is
               the word" which the Lord commanded. Any man who shall vow a vow unto the Lord, or
               swear oaths, or lay down an ordinance concerning himself, shall not make his
               pronouncement void. All that proceedeth out of his mouth he shall perform." Also,
               when Samuel the prophet had commanded Saul, and had ordered him to arm himself
               against Amalek, and deliver to death everything soever that he captured of men and of
               cattle, and he was victorious and gained mighty success in war, and he transgressed
               the ordinance and kept the goats and oxen alive, and he angered God, the divine
               scripture introduces the prophet himself saying thus: "Because thou hast. rejected
               the pronouncement of the Lord, the Lord shall reject thee from being king over
               Israel." And Saul said to Samuel: "I have sinned in that I have transgressed <pb
                  n="403"/> against the word of the Lord." You see Samuel called the divine
               commandment and ordinance "the pronouncement of the Lord", and Saul "the word of the
               Lord." Jeremiah the prophet also applied the term "commandment" to the ordinance that
               the righteous Jonadab established for his sons and his sons' sons, commanding them
               not to taste wine at all, nor possess a house or field, but to live in tents.
               Jeremiah was commanded by God over all to take a jar of wine and a cup, and urge his
               sons to drink, contrary to what was commanded them by their fathers' father: and they
               made answer saying, "We have hearkened to the voice of Jonadab our father, that we
               should not drink wine all the days of our life, we and our wives and our sons and our
               daughters, besides not building houses to live in them. And we have had no vineyard
               or field or seed: and we have dwelt in tents: and we have done all the things that
               Jonadab our father commanded us." And thereupon He that commanded the prophet to do
               these things, in order to convict the disobedient people of Israel, speaks thus: "The
               sons of Jonadab the son of Rechab have maintained the commandment of their father:
               but this people hath not hearkened unto me." This ordinance the Spirit-inspired
               writings are also in the habit of calling "covenant." For instance, when the chiefs
               of the Jews had with the knowledge of King Zedekiah agreed after the space of six
               years to let the Hebrew <pb n="404"/> handmaid and slave go free according to what is
               written in the law, and they had transgressed the ordinance that was enacted by them,
               the same prophet Jeremiah speaks thus; "The word that came from the Lord unto
               Jeremiah, after King Zedekiah had completed a covenant with the people in Jerusalem
               to proclaim a release, and to let every man his Hebrew slave and his Hebrew bondmaid
               go free, that no man might be in bondage from Jerusalem; and all the great men and
               all the people who entered into the covenant turned aside from dismissing every man
               his bondman and his bondwoman, and releasing their bondmen and their bondwomen."
               Also, when those who had returned from Babylon joined themselves to foreign women, of
               the peoples of the countries that were near them, from among whom God had forbidden
               them to make marriages, and Ezra was roused to wrath on account of the sin, those who
               had offended agreed and ordained to send away from them the women that were united to
               them: and one of them is described in the second book of those that were written by
               him as speaking in this manner: "We for our part have been false to our God, and have
               taken strange women of the peoples of the land: and now there is hope for Israel
               concerning this. And let us now make a covenant to our God, to put away all the women
               and such as are born of them. As thou willest, arise, and frighten them by the
               commandments of our <pb n="405"/> God: and let it be done according to the law.
               Arise, because the word is upon thee and we are with thee. Be strengthened, and act."
               You see here also he called that which was resolved and ordained both "word" and
               "covenant": so that in the God-inspired writings the same thing was named "word" and
               "ordinance" (or "prescription") and "pronouncement" and "commandment" and "covenant."
               An anathema fills the place of punishment for him who transgresses what has been
               ordained. But you must know that there are two kinds of anathema. For the expression
               "anathema" is also applied to that which is devoted and consecrated to God, gold it
               may be and silver, and garments and slaves, and cattle and fields: in some cases for
               the honour and adornment of a prayer-house building, in others for the service or
               support of those who are in need, or "those who constantly attend upon the altar" as
               Paul says. Such things it is in no way lawful to transfer to private use after they
               have been consecrated, and to remove from the use whereby they are appropriated to
               God. This principle is stated as follows in Leviticus: "Every anathema that a man
               shall devote unto the Lord of all that he hath, from man unto head of cattle, and
               from the plot of his inheritance, he shall not sell it, nor redeem it. It shall be a
               holy thing unto the Lord." Thus it is written that Judith acted. <pb n="406"/> 
               Judith set apart all the goods of Holophernes that the people gave
               her, and the net that she took for herself from his chamber, and gave it as an
               anathema to the Lord." But the other kind of anathema is when persons are by the
               sentence and judgment of God set apart for death, as Joshua the son of Nun ordained
               in the case of Jericho according to the determination of the Lord, saying, "This city
               and all that is therein shall be anathema to the Mighty Lord; however Rahab the
               harlot and all whom she hath in the house save alive." After the same fashion the
               divine Samuel also said to Saul about Amalek: "And thou shalt destroy and make
               anathema him and all that he hath, and shalt not spare him: and thou shalt slay from
               man unto woman: from babe unto suckling: and from ox unto sheep: and from camel unto
               ass." Wherefore also Moses to the words cited shortly before from Leviticus adds
               these expressions which distinguish this other kind of anathema as we said: "And
               every anathema which shall be set apart by men shall not be redeemed, but shall
               surely die." The anathema therefore that is laid upon those who transgress against
               the divine ordinances, or commandments or commands, is of the second kind, the
               anathema which ordains death to the man who transgresses or sins. But death is
               separation from God. For God is life. Accordingly it follows <pb n="407"/> that death
               also is deprivation of life, and it consists in our being separated and removed from
               God. Into this kind of anathema Paul also cast those who preach to us contrary to
               what we ourselves have received: and he said in the epistle to the Galatians, "But,
               even if we or an angel from heaven preach unto you contrary to what we preached unto
               you, let him be anathema. As we have said before, I say now also again: if any man
               preach to you contrary to what ye received, let him be anathema." In, the first
               epistle to the Corinthians also he wrote in a similar fashion: "If any man loveth not
               our Lord, let him be anathema." However he that tramples upon an anathema decrees
               against him double and manifold death, and he is alien to the blessed calling and
               name of Christians: whence by transgressing against the pronouncements of the laws
               that hold the church of God together he becomes disobedient to the church: and the
               man who becomes disobedient to the church our Saviour and Lord and God Jesus Christ
               in the Gospels consigned to the lot of the nations, saying, "But, if he also hear not
               the church, let him be unto thee as a Gentile and as a tax-gatherer." In general
               therefore an anathema is a separation. For it separates the man who is guilty and is
               removed from God's people, as is said by Isaiah, "Let not a foreigner that is nigh
               unto the Lord say, 'The Lord shall then separate me from His people.'" <pb n="408"/>
               But the word "separation" is also used when a man is separated for a time from
               ministering, or from communicating in the sacrifice that is offered. Question two.
               "Men who cut off their own members are rejected by the great synod: with the
               qualification that it grants remission to those who have suffered this at the hands
               of masters or of barbarians, or by reason of disease, or some other imperative cause.
               This is manifest to those who look at the canon: but for the sake of a searching
               investigation let a case in point such as this be presupposed. A certain man among
               those with us, who had worn the monastic habit from his childhood, as soon as he
               began to reach physical puberty, fearing the enticements of nature, and thinking that
               he was doing a great thing, did not consider the consequences beforehand: but, being
               deceived by ignorance or by enthusiasm, cut off his own members without his superiors
               having knowledge of it. At the time he underwent many punishments for his
               presumption: but, when he attained to manhood, he adopted a very devout mode of life,
               giving himself up to fasts and to the singing of psalms accompanied by many tears,
               and shunning women and bringing his body into subjection by abstinence; though it is
               for the sake of these things that those who cut off their own members generally fall
               into. this audacity, since they then associate with women without suspicion, and
               expect thenceforward to minister to their belly without dis<pb n="409"/>crimination.
               But the man whose case we are considering is not of this kind. He is temperate in all
               things: his hand is unsparing in deeds of mercy: and his whole life he is, if one may
               so say, mourning for the presumptuous deed that he committed against himself: and so
               much so that he is often brought even to despair. But some bid him despair of grace,
               and say that the sum of his many labours is useless to him. Wherefore, even though
               after his audacious act he was admitted first to the diaconate then to the
               presbyterate, he is in distress because he has learned that this is forbidden by the
               canons. Therefore let your God-inspired wisdom explain to us what ought to be thought
               about men who so conduct themselves, or what is the penitence proper for these, and
               what is the benefit derived from that penitence, and whether the hopes of these men
               are vain, and they have no expectation of salvation, and in this matter only the
               power of penitence is weak, seeing that, not even when he is penitent for what he has
               done, and weeps constantly and wears himself out with supplication, is he to expect
               forgiveness for the sins committed: or if his upright life and sincere penitence are
               enough to blot out the presumption of the deed; and if he should continue to hold his
               <foreign>axia</foreign> or function, or must inevitably be stripped of this, being
               expelled by the canons?" Answer. The decision and answer upon this question is
               manifest. If a man who has cut off his own genital members and destroyed them was to
               have forgiveness, be it on the ground of ignorance or immature age, or <pb n="410"/>
               fear, or a devout life after the presumptuous deed and evil act, the exactitude of
               the canons, pronounced as they were through the inspiration of the divine Spirit, by
               the holy apostles and by the saintly shepherds who were after them, would have
               foreseen it. The twenty-first canon of the Constitutions? published to the nations by
               the apostles through Clement speaks thus: "Let not a man who has mutilated himself
               become a clergyman. For he is a self-slayer, and an enemy of God's creation." And the
               twenty-second canon also speaks thus: "If a man being a clergyman shall mutilate
               himself, let his deprivation be effected. For he is a slayer of himself." Next
               follows the twenty-third canon also, which says these words: "Let a layman who has
               mutilated himself be separated for three years. For he is an offender against his own
               life." The first canon also of the great synod of the three hundred and eighteen holy
               men, of which the question also made mention, proclaimed principles consonant with
               the declarations of these apostolic constitutions, placing those who have cut off
               their own members outside the whole clergy, even those who have already been admitted
               to any kind of ordination. For it spoke thus: "But, if any man being sound in health
               has cut off his own members, this man even if enrolled in the clergy must be set
               aside. And henceforth no such man ought to be presented." But the practice of
               penitence prepares those who have com<pb n="411"/>mitted this presumption for
               forgiveness in respect of the sins committed, in order that they may not fail to
               attain the expected life and the kingdom of heaven. But, if any man thinks penitence
               profitless, and fancies that this is feeble, because it does not contrary to the
               intention of the holy canons introduce into the clergy a man who has cut off his own
               members, and restore him to the sacred ministry, he misses the right conception. No
               one is blamed on that dreadful day of judgment because he was not a clergyman, but
               because he did not produce fruits worthy of penitence. A man who is sincerely
               penitent and conscious of his own position, even if he is a man free from every
               canonical impediment that might prevent him from officiating as a priest and
               ministering, shuns such an honour. In fact a man does not take "honour unto himself,
               but by being called of God, as also was Aaron", as said the apostle Paul in the
               epistle to the Hebrews. The ninth canon also makes these general provisions about
               those who have fallen under canonical impediments and been presented to the
               priesthood: "If any have been presented as presbyters without examination, and when
               examined have confessed the sins committed by them, and after they have confessed any
               men being moved in a direction contrary to the canon have laid a hand upon them, such
               men the canon does not accept. For the catholic church <pb n="412"/> requires
               blamelessness". To the same object the tenth canon also is directed. These things I
               for my part have considered and written down in answer to the questions sent me by
               your believing wisdom; not as one who has high thoughts (far be it!), and who exalts
               himself above those who sin; but I have poured forth a flood of sympathetic tears
               over the sinners, and I also am clad in weakness of flesh, as the Apostle somewhere
               says; and of necessity as well as in consequence my speech has borrowed the
               exactitude of the canons, and has uttered their words; to listen to which and delight
               oneself even for a short time in this transitory life that flits away sooner than a
               dream is a cause of great and unending joy, and of the exaltation of the angels and
               the festival of the spirits above, and of ineffable bliss. May the holy Unity in
               Trinity, for that is our God, keep your believing wisdom: while you increase in zeal
               for the orthodox faith, and bear troubles for its sake with firmness, and walk
               blamelessly in the evangelic commandments; and may It admit you to the future endless
               life in the kingdom of heaven, through the prayers of all the saints, Amen! </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
