<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Andrew the Reader and Notary</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">413-17</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="8.5">
            <pb n="413"/>
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Andrew the reader and notary.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 9th book the 61st,
               51st letter.</head>
            <p> The letter of your devoutness which has now been brought, I received on the last day
               of the month of July, on which was the commemoration of the saintly Timothy, who was
               archbishop of the city of the Alexandrines, who completed a long residence in exile
               after the manner of a martyr, and of King Theodosius the younger, piously deceased,
               who in zeal and in the maturity of his intellect surpassed all who reigned before
               him: to whose prayers I also ascribed the receipt of the letter, since I had been
               expecting it for many days, and I was disturbed by various anxieties, and I was
               anxious lest it too had been overlooked and lost. <add><emph>And after other
                  things.</emph></add> As to John the scribe who threw himself into a river and
               departed from this life, I am in doubt, and I have no sure decision to give. Know
               that since the times of Christ's coming in the flesh we find in church histories that
               this is allowed to women, to remove themselves I mean from this life, and throw
               themselves on to rocks or into water: on account of the weakness of their nature, and
               the fact that they are exposed to double danger, that of the pollution of the body I
               mean, and that of denial of the faith: but in the case of men we have nowhere known
               this principle to have been accepted or <pb n="414"/> sanctioned. But it is written
               about one of the holy Maccabean martyrs that the torturers thought he was drawing
               back, and that he was showing signs of change: and upon their releasing him for a
               short time he leaped upon the implements of torment glowing from the fire and the
               instruments of torture, and separated his soul from his body and flew to heaven.
               Therefore, what has thus happened must certainly be judged according to the
               disposition of his heart and the character of the words that John said. But may the
               God of mercy, who desires our salvation rather than our destruction, grant him the
               portion of those that are saved! Indeed the holy John the bishop not only treats such
               a death as a subject of praise in the case of the holy Pelagia the martyr, but also
               pronounces a festal discourse over three other women, I mean Domnina and Prosdocia
               and Berenice, who by reason of the urgent dangers to which they were exposed threw
               themselves into the waves of the Euphrates. Eusebius also in his Church History
               recorded acts like these on the part of females. <add><emph>And after other
                  things.</emph></add> But you did well in sending <foreign>isa</foreign> or
               copies of the synodical letter and of the other letter to those in the East, for
               their comfort and establishment in the faith. <add><emph>And again after other
                  things.</emph></add> But the fact that <pb n="415"/> you have continued to
               reside at Alexandria we also regard as the effect of great prayer, although I am in
               no small degree weary, since I write letters to everyone with my own hands, and fill
               the place of a notary, and I am moreover annoyed at the confusion of the letters,
               since my handwriting is ill-regulated, although the recipients of them are good
               believers. If you are obliged to come to us, seek the lord James the man of the
               count's retinue (?), and he will appear before you more quickly than words can
               express, and with God's help you will be free from care in other things.
               <add><emph>And again after other things.</emph></add> But as for those who,
               after knowing of the death of the wicked Gaian, hold assemblies in which a dead
               service is performed in his name, and commit impieties like those of the heathen, who
               celebrate symbolic services in honour of dead men as of gods, it is quite clear that
               some divine wrath of no gentle kind will come upon them in common, as may be inferred
               from the divine scriptures. But may God grant them to be roused from their error, and
               to be converted from their recklessness while there is time! As to the passage in the
               letter addressed to father John the son of Aphthonia which you say was a difficulty
               to you, it is a perfectly recognised construction, and it ought not after such long
               consideration to have baffled you. After the conjunction "indeed" the conjunction
               "but" is used, either immediately, or after other things <pb n="416"/> that have been
               said in a parenthesis: as is also to be seen clearly apparent in the place that was a
               difficulty to you. It stands thus: "And let these things indeed be both conceived and
               understood in this way: and let them keep us away indeed from things that are evil,
               but let them lead us to the hope of things that are excellent." If we inquire into
               things that are so well recognised, it will even give rise to an accusation of
               foolish speaking among those who are versed in outside learning. Such constructions
               may be found plentifully used, both in every one of the ancients, and in the holy
               fathers. For such a construction is a piece of fine and artistic composition. For
               instance, an expression of the holy Basil, taken from the letter to Amphilochius
               about the Holy Spirit, follows so to speak in the very track and confirms what I say.
               "Therefore the names indeed are of exalted nature and great like these, and names
               that have not indeed any excess of glory. But of what kind are the operations?
               Ineffable indeed on account of their greatness, but innumerable on account of their
               abundance." You notice, I think, how the doctor after saying "Therefore the names
               indeed are like these," again employed another conjunction "indeed", saying "names
               that have not indeed any excess of glory." But this clause is a parenthesis, and the
               sentence composed by him fits together as if it had never been inserted at all: as if
               he had said, "There<pb n="417"/>fore the names indeed are of exalted nature and great
               like these. But of what kind are the operations? Ineffable indeed on account of their
               greatness, but innumerable on account of their abundance." Since this book was found
               lying at hand by me, I have quoted this to you from it. If it had not been so, as I
               said before, one may find similar constructions like showers of rain in every book. </p>
            <trailer>Not the end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
