<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3061">To the Fathers</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">417-20</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="9.1">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to the fathers.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 6th book the 4th
               letter.</head>
            <p> Aeneas and Zacharias the devout deacons, and Elijah the devout monk, who have
               obtained a testimonial from you, of which I also was not unaware, have been admitted
               by the Holy Spirit, the two former to the honour and second seat of the presbyterate,
               the last to the rank of the deacons, and to the status of the diaconate. I would that
               all were like these, men who are advanced to this position with a good <pb n="418"/>
               and sound testimonial, and because they are called by reason of being needed, and do
               not put themselves voluntarily forward out of unseemly ambition and self-will.
               <add><emph>And after other things.</emph></add> But those who received the name
               of clergymen from Gregory the follower of Theodotus the Re-anointer must in all
               points and by all means be reckoned among laymen. However, in the case of those who
               have been admitted to baptism by them, let no one say that they must be enrolled
               among the unbaptized. In fact we hear that. many when beset by a storm at sea, or by
               other pressing circumstances of a similar kind, in order not to miss the invocation,
               have conferred baptism upon themselves, either with their own hands or with the
               assistance of others who however were laymen, the rite being made complete for them
               by the invocation, and the anointing with the holy chrism being added afterwards:
               although it is a matter of presumption for us to say anything decisive in such cases,
               and not to speak by way of investigation and consideration. As to the follower of
               Isaiah the Armenian, let him not even be named, a man who like Dathan and Abiram rose
               not against Moses but against the high-priestly chrism, and wished not so much to be
               as to be called that which he also coveted. About him one might find many things to
               say, a man who, besides. his illegal pretence in contravention of the canons, <pb
                  n="419"/> has also committed the very serious sin of oath-breaking, not once but
               twice also and thrice and many times, and instead of the character of oath-keeping
               has gained that of oath-breaking. And no wonder. In fact in the times of the holy
               Timothy also they say that Cyrus the simple thus arose suddenly and out of self-will
               and fatuously pretended to hold the high-priesthood, and perished together with this
               drunken supposition. <add><emph>And again after other things.</emph></add> You write
               also about the bishop of the city of the men of Berytus, finding fault with the
               indiscriminating character of his clergymen; and you are unaware that he has in fact
               fallen into the nets of Eutyches and of Valentine, and of those who have contracted
               the disease of the phantasy and deny the true Incarnation. He has had the infirmity
               latent in him all this long time, and I do not know how it is that he has now brought
               it to light. For this reason also I have sent the religious presbyter and steward
               Eusebius and the God-loving presbyter and entertainer of strangers Victor to the said
               city of the men of Berytus, in order to convert the man who has erred if he accepts
               correction, or if he is contentious expose him by refutation, and subject him to the
               canons. This same man also admitted the man who was prelate of Scythopolis to honour
               after his decease, a man who was scarcely even a Christian as you yourselves also
               know, thus committing a deed full of all folly and without discrimination. <pb
                  n="420"/> Wherefore also I meet with daily deaths, since I fight and strive with
               greater severity with those who are thought to be catholics than with those outside.
               For everyone who sins and receives any kind of admonition arms himself for strife and
               battle. <add><emph>And again after other things.</emph></add> But I beg that the
               letter be also read as usual to the saintly presbyter Zoninus and Irenaeus and
               Zenobius and Eubulus and the rest. Through the persons mentioned, who appropriate the
               superscription, this epistle was addressed to their love of God also; and through you
               I greet all the God-loving fathers and brothers who are with you, and I ask to have
               your God-beseeming prayers, given with great earnestness. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
