<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/">To Theodore Bishop of Olbe</title><!-- FILL IN TITLE AND WORK URI -->
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">420-23</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="9.2">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Theodore bishop of Olbe.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those during episcopacy, from the 9th book the 8th
               letter.</head>
            <p> The questions asked by your love of God no one will be able to decide, from the
               written laws of divine scripture, or from the spiritual constitutions? of those who
               at one time and another instructed the holy churches. To some extent it seems to be a
               dangerous thing for us to say anything at all on such matters. But again, on account
               of the importance of the question and its bearing on salvation, I considered it an
               im<pb n="421"/>pious thing to hide in silence what has come to my knowledge
               without written source, and not make it clear to your sanctity. You say in fact that
               one of the barbarian slaves bought with money, after communicating in the communion
               of the divine mysteries as a baptized man, after this said that he did not know at
               all whether he had been admitted to the laver of regeneration. Know that I heard some
               old Alexandrine monks, whose mind has been trained by long asceticism, tell the
               following story. In the great city on the day called that of the recipients (thus in
               accordance with the custom of the country they name what we call "first baptisms"), a
               great multitude having as usual thronged together, especially of little babies at the
               breast, and being admitted to the divine grace, it so happened that two women were in
               doubt about their infants, whether that of the one or that of the other had been
               baptized; for there had in fact been an interchange, and the two babes had been
               received, and it was already manifest that one had been admitted to the laver of
               forgiveness, while the other had not passed through the rite; only it was not known
               which of them it was. This came to the ears of the holy Cyril the teacher of exact
               orthodoxy who at that time adorned the high-priestly seat; and, taking the two
               infants, by the inspiration of the wisdom from above, he dipped them in the
               life-giving water, speaking over them as follows: "He that has not been baptized is
               baptized in the name of the Father and of the Son and <pb n="422"/> of the Holy
               Spirit"; and so he settled the point that was in doubt. I remember that in the holy
               monastery of father Romanus of saintly memory also, which is situated in Palestine,
               that a certain monk, who by race was an Ethiopian, after he had for a long time
               communicated in the sacred mysteries, since he was also counted in the order of those
               who had taken upon them the solitary life, upon seeing certain persons baptized
               there, thinking that he had seen a strange sight, secretly confessed to one of the
               brothers that he had not been admitted to the divine laver. And the man who was at
               that time archimandrite of the said monastery (this was Eupraxius the holy old man),
               fearing lest perhaps, if he were baptized, some might fasten the stigma of men who
               re-baptize upon them, informed the prelate of the city of the men of Beth Gabrin of
               what had then happened: and he concluded and judged that the brother who was
               unbaptized ought to be admitted to holy baptism. This action was very right, and not
               outside the scope of the divine laws of the Holy Spirit. For, since our Lord plainly
               decreed and said to Nicodemus, "Verily verily I say unto thee; unless a man be born
               of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God," it is absolutely
               necessary to follow the safe course, and to use the holy Cyril's expression and say,
               "So-and-so is baptized if he has not been baptized, in the name of the Father and of
               the Son and of the Holy Spirit." <pb n="423"/> For in fact by ineffable graciousness
               the immanent power of the Holy Spirit baptizes at the word of the baptizer and
               accompanies it. For the wise Paul also says that we are cleansed "by the laver of
               water by the word," and so put off every spot and wrinkle of sin. This power He who
               became poor for our sake gave to those that perform priestly functions, in order that
               we "through his poverty might be rich"; and He said also to the holy apostles, and to
               those who succeeded these afterwards, "Verily I say unto you, all things that ye
               shall bind on earth shall be bound in heaven; and all things that ye shall loose on
               earth shall be loosed in heaven." This same power He also named "the keys of the
               kingdom of heaven." Therefore with the knowledge of these things direct your steps to
               that which it is right to do, and follow the safe course as I said before, not as by
               stealth and with fear, but "with open face": because "we are not of fear that leadeth
               unto perdition, but of faith that gaineth the soul," as the same wise Paul again
               somewhere says. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
