<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="http://syriaca.org/work/3117">To Thecla the Countess</title>
            <author ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus of Antioch</author>
            <sponsor>Center of Digital Humanities Research, Texas A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Daniel L. Schwartz</principal>
            <editor role="editor" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>XML created by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#ewbrooks">E. W. Brooks</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>OCR corrected by</resp>
               <name type="person" ref="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Daniel L. Schwartz</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <placeName>Center of Digital Humanities Research, College Station, TX, USA</placeName>
            </distributor>
            <authority/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON NAME -->
            <idno/><!-- FILL IN AFTER DECIDING ON URI/URL FORMAT -->
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>Creative Commons — Attribution 4.0 International — CC BY 4.0</p>
                  <p>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <editor ref="http://syriaca.org/person/403">
                     <persName xml:lang="en">
                        <forename>E. W.</forename>
                        <surname>Brooks</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <title type="main" xml:lang="en" level="m">
                     The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/51">Severus Patriarch of Antioch</persName>
                     in the Syriac Version of
                     <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1014">Athanasius of Nisibis</persName>
                  </title>
                  <title type="sub" xml:lang="en" level="m">Vol. II (Translation) Part II</title>
                  <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/669</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher xml:lang="en">Williams and Norgate</publisher>
                     <pubPlace ref="http://syriaca.org/place/861">Oxford</pubPlace>
                     <date>1903</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>Vol. 4 of 4</extent>
                  <biblScope unit="vol">2.2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope unit="page">423-27</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/><!-- FILL IN -->
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <origDate type="composition"/><!-- FILL IN. La Route Royale dates are probably preferable to Brooks' dates. -->
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2019-11" who="http://syriaca.org/person.xml#dschwartz">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter" n="9.3">
            <head type="main" resp="#compiler">Of the same to Thecla the countess.</head>
            <head type="sub" resp="#compiler">From those after banishment, from the 3rd book the 53rd
               letter.</head>
            <p> The letter of reminder that was given by your magnificence to the learned and
               believing grammarian Stephen <pb n="424"/> showed me by the reading of it that still
               even now you remain that Thecla whom Theotecnus the presbyter, who is in all things
               steadfast and religious, would depict to me in words of piety, tracing the likeness
               as in colours: who so much attracted me by his words that I was then the first to
               begin to write a letter to you. Wherefore also I confess myself indebted to God our
               Saviour that neither has his testimony which he bore on your behalf been falsified,
               nor my faith in your God-loving modesty which I then gained. The devoutness of your
               character is shown by the fact that your own judgment was not enough for you, and you
               had not confidence enough to presume to things to which it is not proper to presume
               before being confirmed by a lawful utterance of high-priests. And now you are blessed
               on account of your praiseworthy fear, by the text of the sacred writings that says,
               "Blessed is he that feareth everything through devoutness." Further praise I assign
               to you from the divine law also which ordered a man in disputed causes, and that
               while the service consisting in shadowy things and types yet prevailed, to repair to
               the place where the Levites and priests dwelt, and the judge who had the headship
               over all things at that time, and from them obtain a solution of the doubt. It is
               good and very beneficial to quote in the letter the words of the law itself, which
               are as follows: "But, if any matter be too hard for thee in judgment, between blood
               and blood, and between judgment and <pb n="425"/> judgment, and between stroke and
               stroke, and between reviling and reviling, words of judgment in your cities, thou
               shalt arise and go up to the place which the Lord God shall choose for His name to be
               called there: and thou shalt go in unto the priests the Levites and unto the judge
               that shall be in those days, and they shall inquire and show thee thy judgment: and
               thou shalt do according to the commandment which they shall pronounce to thee that
               are from the place which the Lord thy God shall choose for His name to be called
               there: and thou shalt observe well to do according to all things that shall be
               ordained for thee. According to the law and according to the judgment which they
               shall pronounce to thee do: thou shalt not decline from the sentence which they shall
               pronounce to thee, neither to the right hand, nor to the left." The intention of
               these expressions of the law you have fulfilled in actual deed, both by feeling
               intelligent doubt, and by referring the question as to the doubt to the pronouncement
               of the high-priests, in that you have stated that a certain baby, having been seized
               with severe illness, and having already reached the very gates of death, was sent to
               a prayer house building to receive the laver of regeneration, and the communion of
               the divine light; and, it so happening that the presbyter of that place was not
               there, you say that the deacon by reason of the urgency of the case dipped the boy in
               the water of life, and performed the legal ceremony; and after the action <pb n="426"
               /> the presbyter came and complained of what had been done as unlawful, and sought to
               subject the deacon to punishment. For it was doubted among you whether the boy who
               was baptized received the perfect grace. You must know that in matters that are
               doubtful and rarely occur one cannot find broad statutes: since those who made the
               statutes took care to avoid giving occasion through absence of restraint for the
               rules of strictness to be corrupted. Therefore concerning this problem? also and
               concerning its rareness it is written in the Constitutions" or in the Commands of the
               Apostles, which they named the Testament of the Lord, that a deacon also may
               administer the laver of regeneration when a presbyter is not present, by reason of
               the imminence of the necessary end of death: this same rare observance being
               proclaimed in these words: "In case of necessity, if a presbyter is not present, let
               a deacon baptize". Therefore the presbyter did well in paying attention to what was
               done by the deacon out of necessity, and performing the ceremonies that follow
               baptism, and laying upon the boy who had been baptized the anointing with the holy
               chrism, and the seal of the perfection that results from this. As to the other
               question about the other strange and unknown boy who could not repeat any mystic
               symbol, by which you might have been able to learn whether he is a believer or an
               unbeliever, as not having received <pb n="427"/> the laver of regeneration, a letter
               has been written by me to the God-loving bishop Theodore of a certain city in Isauria
               named Olbe, and I have determined to quote the same to you at the end of this letter,
               as being sufficient to provide you with a solution of the doubt. May you be preserved
               to us, noble God-loving woman, who show your strict practice regarding faith in God
               even by the questions which you ask in doubt! That strictness continue to keep till
               your last breath: for "without faith it is impossible to please" says the Apostle. </p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
         </div>      
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
